<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2009-03-15 j.h: reviewed for v2.6. No change
  2008-03-31 JPL reviewed de for GIMP 2.4
  2008-03-15 Mr.Dust : added korean contents
  2008-02-20 j.h: updated to v2.4 en;fr. Added Fill feathered selection
  2007-10-07 lexa: reviewed de for GIMP 2.4
  2007-06-16 kost: added norwegian
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-11-30 informalfigure replaced by figure by lexa
  050815 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<!--2009-11-15-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">
  <title lang="en">Bucket Fill</title>
  <title lang="ja">塗りつぶし</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Bucket Fill</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Bucket Fill</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ツール</primary>
    <secondary sortas="ヌリツブシ">塗りつぶし</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="ヌリツブシ">塗りつぶし</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Toolbox Fill</title>
    <title lang="ja">
      ツールボックス上の<quote>塗りつぶし</quote>ツールアイコン
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/toolbox-fill.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    This tool fills a selection with the current foreground color. If you
    Ctrl+click and use the Bucket tool, it will use the background color
    instead. Depending on how the tool options are set, the Bucket Fill tool
    will either fill the entire selection, or only parts whose colors are
    similar to the point you click on. The tool options also affect the way
    transparency is handled.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The amount of fill depends on what Fill Threshold you have specified. The
    fill threshold determines how far the fill will spread (similar to the way
    in which the magic wand works). The fill starts at the point where you
    click and spreads outward until the color or alpha value becomes
    <quote>too different</quote>.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    When you fill objects in a transparent layer (such as letters in a text
    layer) with a different color than before, you may find that a border of
    the old color still surrounds the objects. This is due to a low
    fill-threshold in the Bucket Fill options dialog. With a low threshold,
    the bucket tool won't fill semi-transparent pixels, and they will stand
    out against the fill because they have kept their original color.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    If you want to fill areas that are totally transparent, you have to make
    sure that the <quote>Lock</quote> option (in the Layers dialog) is
    unchecked. If this option is checked, only the non-transparent parts of
    the layer will be filled.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    このツールは選択範囲を現行の描画色で塗りつぶします。 <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
    キーを押しながらだと背景色が使われます。 ツールオプションの指定に拠り、
    選択範囲の全体を塗りつぶす場合と、 クリックされた位置と同じ色の部分だけが
    塗られる場合があります。 ツールオプションは透明度の扱い方に係わる
    ものもあります。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    塗られる部分の大きさはオプションで定める <guilabel>しきい値</guilabel>
    に左右されます。 しきい値は塗る広さにも関わります。 
    (<link linkend="gimp-tool-fuzzy-select">ファジー選択</link> での
    しくみと同じです。) クリックした始点から塗りつぶしがはじまり、
    画素 (ピクセル) の色またはアルファ値に<quote>大差が無い限り</quote>
    先へと広がります。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    透明なレイヤーに描かれた形象 (例えばテキストレイヤー上の文字) をそれまで
    とは違う色で塗り直したとき、 形象の縁だけ以前の色が残っている場合が
    あります。 これはしきい値 (塗りつぶしツールのオプションダイアログに
    ある) が低かったことによるものです。 しきい値が低いと塗りつぶし
    ツールは半透明の画素を着色しないので、 以前の色が残ってしまい
    目立ってしまったのです。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    完全透明な領域で塗りつぶしをするときは、 <quote>透明保護</quote>
    オプション (レイヤーダイアログにある) がロックされていないことを
    確かめてからにしましょう。 このオプションが有効だと半透明及び不透明な
    領域だけが塗られます。
  </para>
  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Activating tool</title>
    <title lang="ja">呼び出し方</title>
    <para lang="en">You can activate the Airbrush tool in several ways :</para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <quote>塗りつぶし</quote>ツールを起用する方法はつぎのいずれかです。
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can find the Bucket Fill tool from the image-menu through:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Paint Tools</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Bucket Fill</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像ウィンドウのメニューより
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>ツール</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>描画ツール(</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>塗りつぶし</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          You can also call it by clicking the tool icon:
          <guiicon>
            <inlinegraphic
              fileref="images/toolbox/stock-tool-bucket-fill-22.png"/>
          </guiicon>
          in the toolbox.
          </guiicon>
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          ツールボックスのツールアイコン
          <guiicon>
            <inlinegraphic
              fileref="images/toolbox/stock-tool-bucket-fill-22.png"/>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          or by pressing the
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo> keys.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          キーボードショートカット
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <tip lang="ja">
      <para lang="en">
        For more convenient way, you can fill selection with a solid color,
        by clicking and dragging a color symbol from the Toolbox or the
        FG/BG Color dialog and dropping it into the Image Window. Filling
        with a pattern, also, can be made by the same way with a pattern
        symbol of the Toolbox or the Pattern dialog.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        より簡単に選択範囲を塗りつぶすために、 ツールボックス底部の色領域や
        描画色/背景色ダイアログで描画色もしくは背景色をクリックし、 画像
        ウィンドウまでドラッグして放つ方法があってこれは単色で塗りつぶせます。 
        パターンによる塗りつぶしもツールボックス底部のパターン表示や
        パターンダイアログから同様にできます。
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers (Defaults)</title>
    <title lang="ja">修飾キー (初期設定)</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> toggles the use of BG Color Fill or FG
          Color Fill on the fly.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> キーは、 単色塗りつぶしに用いる色を
          描画色から背景色に切り替えます。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          <keycap>Shift</keycap> toggles the use of Fill Similar Color or
          Fill Whole Selection on the fly.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <keycap>Shift</keycap> キーは塗る対象領域を、 類似色領域から
          選択範囲に切り替えます。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="ja">オプション</title>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en"><quote>Bucket Fill</quote> tool options</title>
      <title lang="ja">
        <quote>塗りつぶし</quote>ツールのツールオプション
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-fill.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <xi:include href="about-common-options-display.xml"/>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Mode; Opacity</term>
        <term lang="ja">モード; 不透明度</term>
        <listitem>
    <!--<para lang="ja">
      描画ツールに共通して使えるオプションについては
      <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">描画ツール</link> をお読みください。
      ここでは塗りつぶしツールに特有のオプションについてのみ取り上げます。
    </para>-->
          <xi:include href="about-common-brush-options.xml"/>
          <!--<para lang="ja">描画ツール共通のオプションです。</para>-->
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Fill Type</term>
        <term lang="ja">塗りつぶし方法</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en"><acronym>GIMP</acronym> provides three fill types:
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は塗りつぶしに3つの方法を提供しています:
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">FG Color Fill</term>
              <term lang="ja">描画色塗り</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  sets the fill color to the currently selected foreground
                  color.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  現在指定されている描画色を塗りつぶしの色とします。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">BG Color Fill</term>
              <term lang="ja">背景色塗り</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  sets the fill color to the currently selected background
                  color.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  現在指定されている背景色を塗りつぶしの色とします。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Pattern Fill</term>
              <term lang="ja">パターン塗り</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  sets the fill color to the currently selected pattern. You
                  can select the pattern to use in a drop down list.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  This drop-down list allows the user to select one of many
                  fill patterns to use on the next fill operation. The manner
                  in which the list is presented is controlled by the four
                  buttons at the bottom of the selector.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  現在指定されているパターン (文様) を用いて塗りつぶします。
                  引き出し排列から使いたい文様を選択できます。
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  この引き出し排列で数多ある文様から次回の塗りつぶしに用いる
                  文様をひとつ選び出します。 排列選択枠の底部にある左寄り4つの
                  ボタンを使って見本の並べかたや大きさを調節できます。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Affected Area</term>
        <term lang="ja">塗りつぶし範囲</term>
        <listitem>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Fill whole selection</term>
              <term lang="ja">選択範囲を塗りつぶす</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  This option makes GIMP fill a pre-existent selection or the
                  whole image. A quicker approach to do the same thing could
                  be to click and drag the foreground, background or pattern
                  color, leaving it onto the selection.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  このオプションは既に用意してある選択範囲か画像全体を
                  塗りつぶすときのものです。 
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Fill similar colors</term>
              <term lang="ja">類似色領域を塗りつぶす</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  This is the default setting: the tool fills the area with a
                  color near the pixel onto you have clicked. The color
                  similarity is defined by a brightness threshold, that you
                  can set by a value or by a cursor position.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  既定はこちらです。 クリックした場所の画素の色に類似した
                  色のある隣接領域が塗りつぶされます。 色の類似性は
                  明度のしきい値で定められ、 しきい値は実値もしくはカーソルの
                  位置で設定できます。<!--明度のしきい値? カーソル? -->
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Finding Similar Colors</term>
        <term lang="ja">類似色の識別</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">Under this section you can find two options:</para>
          <para lang="ja">この区画では2つ<!-- 4つ -->のオプションがあります:
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Fill Transparent Areas</term>
              <term lang="ja">透明領域を塗りつぶす</term>
              <listitem>
                <indexterm lang="en">
                  <primary>Fill transparent areas</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm lang="ja">
                  <primary sortas="トウメイリョウイキヲヌリツブス">
                    透明領域を塗りつぶす
                </primary>
                </indexterm>
                <para lang="en">
                  The option <guilabel>Fill Transparent Areas</guilabel>
                  offers the possibility of filling areas with low opacity.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  <guilabel>透明領域を塗りつぶす</guilabel> オプションで
                  不透明度の低い領域も塗りつぶせます。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Sample Merged</term>
              <term lang="ja">レイヤー結合色</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  The option <guilabel>Sample Merged</guilabel>
                  toggles the sampling from all layers. If Sample Merged is
                  active, fills can be made on a lower layer, while the color
                  information used for threshold checking is located further
                  up. Simply select the lower level and ensure that a layer
                  above is visible for color weighting.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  <guilabel>レイヤー結合色</guilabel> オプションは色抽出の対象
                  を単レイヤーから全てのレイヤーに切り替えます。 この合成色抽出
                  が可能になると、 しきい値と比較される色情報をとるレイヤーから
                  みて下 (背面側) のレイヤーであっても塗りつぶしができます。
                  その条件は、 最前面以外のレイヤーを選んだうえで、 前面側の
                  レイヤーが視覚的に色を評価できるものであることだけです。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Threshold</term>
              <term lang="ja">しきい値</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  The Threshold slider sets the level at which color weights
                  are measured for fill boundaries. A higher setting will fill
                  more of a multi colored image and conversely, a lower
                  setting will fill less area.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  しきい値スライダは塗りつぶし範囲の輪郭をとるための色評価
                  の水準を定めます。 彩り豊かな画像で高い値を設定すると
                  塗られる範囲が広くなり、 反対に低い値を設定すれば範囲は
                  小さくなります。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term lang="en">Fill by</term>
              <term lang="ja">塗りつぶし手段</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  With this option you can choose which component of the image
                  GIMP shall use to calculate the similarity and to determine
                  the borders of filling.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  The components you can choose from are
                  <guimenuitem>Composite</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Red</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Green</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Blue</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Hue</guimenuitem>,
                  <guimenuitem>Saturation</guimenuitem> and
                  <guimenuitem>Value</guimenuitem>.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  This option is not easy to understand. You have chosen,
                  for example, the Red channel. When you click on any pixel,
                  the tool searches for contiguous pixels similar for
                  <emphasis>the red channel</emphasis> to the clicked pixel,
                  according to the set threshold. Here is an example:
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  Original image: three strips with gradients of pure
                  colors. Red (255;0;0), Green (0;255;0), Blue
                  (0;0;255). We are going to use the Bucket-fill tool
                  with the magenta color and a Threshold set to 15.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  Image 1: Fill By = Composite. We successively clicked in the
                  three color strips. Every strip is filled according
                  to the threshold.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  Image 2: Fill By = Red. We clicked in the red strip. The
                  tool searches for contiguous pixels which have a similar
                  value in the red channel, according to the set
                  threshold. Only a narrow area corresponds to these
                  standards. In the green and the blue strip, the value
                  of pixels in the red channel is 0, very much different from
                  the red channel value of the clicked pixel: the color
                  doesn't spread to them.
                </para>
                <para lang="en">
                  Image 3: Fill By = Red. We clicked in the green strip.
                  There, the value of the clicked pixel in the red channel is
                  0. All pixels in the green and the blue strips have the
                  same red channel value (0): they are all painted.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  このオプションで<acronym>GIMP</acronym>が類似色を算出し
                  塗りつぶし範囲の境界を定めるために画像のどの成分を根拠と
                  するかを指定します。
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  根拠となる成分を <guimenuitem>コンポジット</guimenuitem>、
                  <guimenuitem>赤</guimenuitem>、
                  <guimenuitem>緑</guimenuitem>、
                  <guimenuitem>青</guimenuitem>、
                  <guimenuitem>色相</guimenuitem>、
                  <guimenuitem>彩度</guimenuitem>、
                  <guimenuitem>明度</guimenuitem> からひとつ選びます。
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  このオプションを理解することは簡単ではありません。
                  試しに赤チャンネルを選択したとします。 どこかの画素
                  をクリックすれば、 その画素の <emphasis>赤チャンネル
                  </emphasis> の値からしきい値を越えない範囲で近い値を、
                  このツールは隣接する画素を辿って探し出します。
                  さらに例を挙げましょう:
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  元の画像: 三原色すなわち赤(255,0,0)、 緑(0,255,0)、
                  青(0,0,255) それぞれの帯にグラデーションをかけたもの。
                  これからこの画像をしきい値が15の設定でマゼンタ色で
                  塗りつぶします。
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  画像その1: 塗りつぶし手段 = <guimenuitem>コンポジット
                  </guimenuitem> 。 3色の帯をつぎつぎとクリックしました。
                  どの帯もしきい値の許す範囲で塗りつぶされています。
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  画像その2: 塗りつぶし手段 = <guimenuitem>赤</guimenuitem>。
                  赤の帯をクリックしました。 塗りつぶしツールはクリックした
                  点の赤チャンネル上の値をとり、 そこに隣接する画素から
                  順にしきい値の許す範囲で赤チャンネル上に近似値をもつ領域
                  を探して辿ります。 この基準に見合う領域は狭いものです。
                  緑と青の帯上の画素の赤チャンネルの値はいずれも0なので、
                  赤チャンネル上ではクリックされた画素の値とはまったく
                  異なります。 したがってマゼンタ色はこちらには拡がりません。
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  画像その3: 塗りつぶし手段 = <guimenuitem>赤</guimenuitem>。
                  緑の帯をクリックしました。 すると赤チャンネル上のクリック
                  された画素の値は0ですが、 緑と青の帯上の全ての画素も
                  赤チャンネルでの値は0ですから、 両者とも塗りつぶされました。
                </para>
                <figure>
                  <title lang="en">Example for <quote>Fill By</quote></title>
                  <title lang="ja"><quote>塗りつぶし手段</quote>の例</title>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/toolbox/fill-by-0.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                      <para lang="en">Original image</para>
                      <para lang="ja">元の画像</para>
                    </caption>
                  </mediaobject>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/toolbox/fill-by-1.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                      <para lang="en">Image 1</para>
                      <para lang="ja">画像その1</para>
                    </caption>
                  </mediaobject>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/toolbox/fill-by-2.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                      <para lang="en">Image 2</para>
                      <para lang="ja">画像その2</para>
                    </caption>
                  </mediaobject>
                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata format="PNG"
                        fileref="images/toolbox/fill-by-3.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                      <para lang="en">Image 3</para>
                      <para lang="ja">画像その3</para>
                    </caption>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Fill a feathered selection</title>
    <title lang="ja">境界のぼけた選択領域の塗りつぶし</title>
    <para lang="en">
      By clicking repeatedly in a selection with feathered edges, you
      progressively fill the feathered border:
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      境界をぼかして作成された選択領域を繰り返しクリックすると、
      塗りつぶされる範囲は徐々に拡がってゆきます。
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">
        Example for <quote>Fill a feathered Selection</quote>
      </title>
      <title lang="ja">
        <quote>境界のぼけた選択領域の塗りつぶし</quote>の例
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/fill-feathered-1.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">Original image</para>
          <para lang="ja">元の画像</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/fill-feathered-2.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            After clicking 3 times more with the Bucket-Fill tool
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">塗りつぶしツールでさらに3回クリックした後の図</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
