<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2009-02-19 j.h: revised for v2.6
  2007-08-27 lexa: replaced list by sect3
  2007-04-24 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-02-21 lexa: changed top level from chapter to sect1
  2006-08-18 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-06-19 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-05-15 HdJ: Added dutch translation.
  2006-05-13 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-03-10 changed structure
  2006-02-20 fixed #322305
  2005-11-30 replaced informalfigure by axel.wernicke
-->
<!--2010-04-19-->
<sect1 id="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">
  <title lang="en">Getting Unstuck</title>
  <title lang="ja">固まったときの対処</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Getting Unstuck</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary sortas="カタマッタトキノタイショ">固まったときの対処</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <secondary sortas="ムハンノウ">無反応</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-getting-unstuck-general">
    <title lang="en">Stuck!</title>
    <title lang="ja">反応しなくなった!</title>
    <para lang="en">
      All right, okay: you're stuck. You're trying to use one of the tools on
      an image, and nothing is happening, and nothing you try makes any
      difference. Your fists are starting to clench, and your face is starting
      to feel warm. Are you going to have to kill the program, and lose all
      your work? This sucks!
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Well, hold on a second. This happens pretty frequently, even to people
      who've used <acronym>GIMP</acronym> for a long time, but generally the
      cause is not so hard
      to figure out (and fix) if you know where to look at. Lets be calm, and
      go through a checklist that will probably get you GIMPing happily again.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      了解しました。 おまかせください。 動かなくなったのですね。 画像にツールで
      何かの操作をしたら、 全然反応がなくなって、 しかも何をやっても変化しなく
      なったのでしょう。 あなたの手首は硬ばりだし、
      額には脂汗が浮かんで&hellip;。 もしやプログラムを強制終了しようかと
      思ってませんか？ それまでの成果は無駄になってしまうのに。 駄目じゃん。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      まずは一回深呼吸です。 実は<acronym>GIMP</acronym>を長年使っている人にも
      たびたびこういったことが起こっているのですが、 見方を変えるとその
      原因をつきとめたり (修繕したり) するのは案外簡単な場合が多いのです。
      落ち着いて、 つぎの点検項目をじっくりたどれば必ずや
      楽しい<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の時間が戻ってきます。
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gimp-using-getting-unstuck-common-causes">
    <title lang="en">Common Causes of GIMP Non-Responsiveness</title>
    <title lang="ja">
      <acronym>GIMPが</acronym>反応しなくなるほとんどの理由
    </title>
    <sect3>
      <title lang="en">There is a floating selection</title>
      <title lang="ja">フローティング (浮層) 選択範囲がある</title>
      <figure>
        <title lang="en">Layers dialog showing a floating selection.</title>
        <title lang="ja">
          フローティング選択範囲があることを示すレイヤーダイアログ
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/unstuck-floating-sel.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en"><emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
        If there is a floating selection, many actions are impossible
        until the floating section is anchored.
        To check, look at the Layers dialog (making
        sure it's set to the image you're working on) and see whether the
        top layer is called <quote>Floating Selection</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en"><emphasis>How to solve:</emphasis>
        Either anchor the floating selection, or convert it into an
        ordinary (non-floating) layer. If you need help on how to do this,
        see <link linkend="glossary-floatingselection">
          Floating Selections
        </link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>みわけかた:</emphasis>
        <link linkend="gimp-selection-float">フローティング (浮層) 選択範囲
        </link> があると、 これを固定するまでは実行できない操作がたくさん
        あります。 確認のため、 レイヤーダイアログを見て (作業中の画像を扱って
        いる状態で)、 最前面のレイヤーが<quote>フローティング選択範囲</quote>に
        なっていないか確かめます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>対処法:</emphasis>
        フローティング選択範囲を固定するか、 もしくはそれを通常の
        (浮いていない) レイヤーに転換します。 よくわからない方は
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-anchor">レイヤーを固定</link>
        をご覧ください。
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title lang="en">The selection is hidden</title>
      <title lang="ja">選択範囲が隠されている</title>
      <figure>
        <title lang="en">Unstuck show selection menu</title>
        <title lang="ja">
          <quote>選択範囲の境界線を表示</quote>メニューで対処
        </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/unstuck-show-selection-menu.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="en">
              In the View menu, make sure that "Show Selection" is checked.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <guilabel>表示</guilabel>メニューの
              <guilabel>選択範囲の境界線を表示</guilabel>
              が入りになっていることを確かめます。
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en"><emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
        If this is the problem, merely reading this will already have made
        you realize it, probably, but to explain in any case: sometimes
        the flickering line that outlines the selection is annoying
        because it makes it hard to see important details of the image, so
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> gives you the option of hiding the selection,
        by unchecking
        <guimenuitem>Show Selection</guimenuitem>
        in the <guimenu>View</guimenu>
        menu. It is easy to forget that you have done this, though.
      </para>
      <para lang="en"><emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> If this
        hasn't rung any bells, it isn't the problem, and if it has,
        you probably know how to fix it, because it doesn't happen
        unless you explicitly tell it to; but anyway:  just go to
        the <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu for the image and, if
        <guimenuitem>Show Selection</guimenuitem> is
        unchecked, click on it..
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        これが問題になるそもそもの原因は、 ここを読んでいる時点まではいろいろ
        他の問題は思い付きはしても、 まさかここが関係するとはなかなか察知
        しづらいからではないでしょうか。 選択範囲を示す点滅破線はしばしば
        画像の重要な細部を見えづらくしてしまう難点があるため、
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>では
        <guimenu>表示</guimenu>メニューの
        <guimenuitem>選択範囲の境界線を表示</guimenuitem>
        のチェックを外せば選択範囲の線を隠せるようになっています。
        ところがその後で忘れてしまいやすいのです。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>対処法:</emphasis>
        これが何ら警鐘を鳴らすものではないのなら、 もともと問題でもありません。
        これが問題だと思わなければよいだけの話になります。 その逆の場合も、
        すでにあなたはもうどうすれば良いかご存知です。 でも一応申し上げますが、
        <guimenu>表示</guimenu>メニューを開き、
        <guimenuitem>選択範囲の境界線を表示</guimenuitem>
        のチェックが外れていたらクリックして入れてください。
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title lang="en">You are acting outside of the selection</title>
      <title lang="ja">選択範囲の外で作業している</title>
      <figure>
        <title lang="en">Unstuck select all</title>
        <title lang="ja"><quote>すべて選択</quote>で対処</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/unstuck-select-all.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="en">
              Click <quote>All</quote>
              in the Select menu to make sure that everything is selected.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              選択範囲を全域にするため <guimenu>選択
              </guimenu>メニューの <guimenuitem>すべて選択
              </guimenuitem> をクリックする。
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en"><emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis>
        If doing this has destroyed a selection that you wanted to keep, hit
        <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>
        (undo) a couple of times to restore it, and then we'll figure
        out what the problem is. There are a couple of possibilities. If you
        couldn't see any selection, there may have been a very tiny one, or
        even one that contained no pixels. If this was the case, it surely is
        not a selection that you wanted to keep, so why have you gotten this
        far in the first place? If you can see a selection but thought you
        were inside it, it might be inverted from what you think. The easiest
        way to tell is to hit the Quick Mask button: the selected area will be
        clear and the unselected area will be masked. If this was the problem,
        then you can solve it by toggling Quick Mask off and choosing Invert
        in the <guimenu>Select</guimenu> menu.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>対処法:</emphasis> 全域選択でせっかくできていた選択範囲が
        壊れてしまったのでしたら、 もとに戻るまで
        <keycombo><keycap>CTRL</keycap><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo> (取り消し)
        を数回繰り返してから問題解決に入りましょう。 考えられる原因はいくつか
        あります。 もし選択範囲がどこにも見当たらないときは、 選択範囲が極めて
        小さく、ときには1ピクセルも含んでいないようなものになっている可能性が
        あります。 この場合、残しておきたいようなものではないでしょうから、
        もとに戻す必要はありませんね。 もし選択範囲が見えていて作業もその
        範囲内でしているはずだという場合は、 選択範囲が反転している可能性が
        あります。 クイックマスクボタンを押すのがいちばん簡単なみわけかたです。
        選択範囲は透明ですが非選択範囲にはマスクが掛かっています。
        原因がこのとおりならば、クイックマスクを解除してから
        <guimenu>選択</guimenu> メニューより <guimenuitem>
        選択範囲を反転</guimenuitem> してください。
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title lang="en">The active drawable is not visible</title>
      <title lang="ja">描画中の領域が不可視である</title>
      <figure>
        <title lang="en">Unstuck layer invisibility</title>
        <title lang="ja">不可視レイヤーに対処</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/unstuck-layers-dialog-invislayer.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="en">
              Layers dialog with visibility off for the active layer.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              描画中のレイヤーが不可視になっていることを示すレイヤーダイアログ。
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en"><emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
        The Layers dialog gives you ability to toggle the visibility of
        each layer on or off. Look at the Layers dialog, and see if
        the layer you are trying to act on is active (i.e., darkened) and
        has an eye symbol to the left of it. If not, this is your problem.
      </para>
      <para lang="en"><emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis>
        If your intended target layer is not active, click on it in the Layers
        dialog to activate it. (If none of the layers is active, the
        active drawable might be a channel -- you can look at the Channels tab
        in the Layers dialog to see. This does not change the solution,
        though.) If the eye symbol does not appear, click in the Layers dialog
        at the left edge to toggle it: this should make the layer visible. See
        the Help section for the
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>
        if you need more help.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>みわけかた:</emphasis>
        レイヤーダイアログでは個々のレイヤーの可視/不可視を切り替えることが
        できます。 レイヤーダイアログを見て、 描画されているレイヤー
        (強調されています) がどれかを探し、 その左に目のしるしがあるか
        確かめてください。 なければ、 それが原因です。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>対処法:</emphasis>
        処理対象のレイヤーが無効だった場合は、 レイヤーダイアログでそのレイヤー
        をクリックして有効にしてください。 (有効なレイヤーがまったく無ければ、
        描画領域はチャンネルかもしれませんので チャンネルダイアログを見て
        ください。 解法は同じです。) レイヤーダイアログ上で目のしるしが
        なければ、 左端をクリックして切り替えてください。 これでレイヤーは
        可視化されます。 より詳しい説明が
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">レイヤーダイアログ</link> に
        あります。
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title lang="en">The active drawable is transparent</title>
      <title lang="ja">描画中の領域が透明になっている</title>
      <figure>
        <title lang="en">Unstuck layer transparency</title>
        <title lang="ja">レイヤーの不透明度に対処</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/unstuck-layers-dialog-transparentlayer.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="en">
              Layers dialog with opacity set to zero for the active layer.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              作業中のレイヤーの不透明度がゼロであることを示すレイヤーダイアログ
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en">
        When the opacity is set 0 on the layer, you cannot see anything which
        you draw.  Look the <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> slider,
        and see which side the slider placed at.  If it is at the leftmost side,
        that is your problem.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Move the slider.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>みわけかた:</emphasis>
        不透明度が0のレイヤー上ではどんな描画をしても何も表示されません。
        レイヤーダイアログ上部の <guilabel>不透明度</guilabel> スライダを
        見てください。 もし最左端にあれば、 それが原因です。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>対処法:</emphasis>スライダを動かします。
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title lang="en">You are trying to act outside the layer</title>
      <title lang="ja">レイヤーの領域外で作業している</title>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis>
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, layers don't need to have the same
        dimensions as the
        image: they can be larger or smaller. If you try to paint outside
        the borders of a layer, nothing happens. To see if this is
        happening, look for a black-and-yellow dashed rectangle that does
        not enclose the area you're trying to draw at.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis>
        You need to enlarge the layer. There are two commands at the bottom of
        the Layer menu that will let you do this: Layer to Image Size, which
        sets the layer bounds to match the image borders; and Layer Boundary
        Size, which brings up a dialog that allows you to set the layer
        dimensions to whatever you please.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>みわけかた:</emphasis>
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>ではレイヤーが画像と同じ大きさである必要は
        ありません。 はみ出すような大きいものでも、 一部だけの小さなものでも、
        ずれていてもよいのです。 レイヤーの境界線より外側で作業しても何も
        起きません。 この事態をみわけるには、 黒と黄色の点線で区切られた
        矩形領域をさがしだし、 その内側で作業しているのかどうか確かめるのです。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        レイヤーを大きくします。 <guimenuitem>レイヤー
        </guimenuitem>メニューの下のほうにある2つの操作がどちらもこの問題を解決
        します。 <guimenuitem>レイヤーをキャンバスに合わせる
        </guimenuitem>: レイヤーの範囲を画像の大きさと同じにします。
        <guimenuitem>レイヤーの拡大・縮小...</guimenuitem>:
        ダイアログが開き、 レイヤーの大きさを自由に変えられます。
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title lang="en">The image is in indexed color mode.</title>
      <title lang="ja">画像がインデックスカラーのモードになっている</title>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>How to tell:</emphasis><acronym>GIMP</acronym> can handle
        three different color modes:
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">RGB(A), Indexed and Grayscale</link>.
        The indexed colormode uses a colormap,
        where all used colors on the image are indexed. The
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">color picker</link> in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> however, let you choose RGB colors.
        That means, if you try to paint with a different color than
        it is indexed in the colormap, you end up in very
        undetermined results (e.g. it paints with the wrong color or
        you can't paint).
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>How to fix:</emphasis> Always use the
        RGB Color mode to paint on images. You can verify and select
        another color mode from the
        <link linkend="gimp-image-mode">Mode</link> menuitem in the
        <guimenu>Image</guimenu> menu.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>みわけかた:</emphasis>
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は3つの異なる色のモード
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">RGB(A)とインデックスと
        グレースケール</link> を扱えます。 インデックスカラーのモードは
        カラーマップを使用しており、 画像のすべての色は色目録から
        とられています。 しかし<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">スポイト</link>は
        <acronym>RGB</acronym>カラーのモードを前提にした仕様で色を抽出します。
        要するに、 カラーマップの目録外の色で描こうとすると、
        (変な色がついたり、 何も描けなかったり) おかしな結果になるのです。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>対処法:</emphasis>
        画像を描画するときは常に<acronym>RGB</acronym>モードを使用します。
        <guimenu>画像</guimenu>メニューの
        <link linkend="gimp-image-mode">モード</link> を見れば現在のモードを
        確認でき、 ここで他のモードに変換することもできます。
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
