<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2008-07-20 Mr.Dust : added 'ko'
  2007-01-29 added Spanish content by manuq
  2006-11-01 lexa: made the file docbook compliant
  2008-02-04 Vérification + compléments par jpl in french
-->
<!--2010-12-15-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-folders">
  <title lang="en">Folders</title>
  <title lang="ja">フォルダ</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Folders</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ダイアログ</primary>
    <secondary sortas="カンキョウセッテイ">環境設定</secondary>
    <tertiary>フォルダ</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Basic Folder Preferences</title>
    <title lang="ja">環境設定 基本のフォルダのページ</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/preferences/prefs-folders.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    This page allows you to set the locations for two important folders used
    by GIMP for temporary files. The pages below it allow you to customize the
    locations searched for resources such as brushes etc.; see
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Data Folders</link>
    for a description that applies to them. You can change the folders here by
    editing the entries, or by pressing the buttons on the right to bring up a
    file chooser window.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    このページでは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>が一時的なファイルを置くための 
    2 箇所の重要なフォルダの位置を設定できます。 このページ以降では
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>で扱う例えばブラシのようなファイル資材を探し出す
    位置を、 個別に設定できるようになっています。 それぞれの説明が次項
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">データフォルダ</link> にあります。
    ここに示されたフォルダ以外の位置を指定する場合は、 引き出しメニューから
    選択するか、 その下端にある <guimenuitem>その他...</guimenuitem> をクリック
    しておのおののフォルダ選択ダイアログで指定してください。
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <title lang="en">Folders</title>
    <title lang="ja">フォルダ</title>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Temp folder</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Swap folder</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary>テンポラリフォルダ</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary>スワップフォルダ</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Temp folder</term>
      <term lang="ja">テンポラリフォルダ</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This folder is used for temporary files: files created for temporary
          storage of working data, and then deleted within the same GIMP
          session. It does not require a lot of space or high performance. By
          default, a subdirectory called <filename>tmp</filename>
          in your personal GIMP directory is used, but if that disk is very
          cramped for space, or has serious performance issues, you can change
          it to a different directory. The directory must exist and be
          writable by you, or bad things will happen.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          このフォルダは一時的に発生するファイルを置くためのものです。 これらの
          ファイルは作業用データを暫時保存するために作成され、 その
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>操作の期間内に消去されます。 大きな容量も高い
          性能も必要ありません。 初期設定では個人用<acronym>GIMP</acronym>内の
          <filename class="directory">tmp</filename> というサブディレクトリが
          使われますが、 ディスク残量がたいへん窮屈になっていたり重大な
          性能問題がある場合には、 ここで他のディレクトリに替えましょう。 
          ただしそのディレクトリが存在し、 なおかつそのディレクトリに対する
          読み書きの権限が必要です。 無ければまずいことになるでしょう。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Swap folder</term>
      <term lang="ja">スワップ用フォルダ</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          This is the folder used as a <quote>memory bank</quote> when the
          total size of images and data open in GIMP exceeds the available
          RAM. If you work
          with very large images, or images with many layers, or have many
          images open at once, GIMP can potentially require hundreds of
          megabytes of swap space, so available disk space and performance are
          definitely things to think about for this folder. By default, it is
          set to your personal GIMP directory, but if you have another disk
          with more free space, or substantially better performance, you may
          see a significant benefit from moving your swap folder there. The
          directory must exist and be writable by you.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          このフォルダは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>で開かれたすべての画像とデータの
          容量が使用可能な<acronym>RAM</acronym>の限界を越してしまった場合の
          メモリ貯蔵庫として使われます。 とても大きな画像やレイヤーを多数持つ
          画像を扱ったり、 多数の画像を同時に開いたときに
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は可能性として数百メガバイトものスワップ空間を
          要求することになりうるのですが、 ディスク容量がどこまで利用可能か
          という問題やその性能についてはこのフォルダに明確にかかっています。 
          初期設定ではここは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の個人用ディレクトリ内に
          置かれますが、 もっと大きな容量のディスクや、 実際的に性能がより良い
          ディスクが他にある場合には、 そちらにスワップフォルダを移動すれば
          目に見えて恩恵を得るでしょう。 もちろんそのディレクトリが必ず存在し、
          書き込み権限を持っていなくてはなりません。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect2>
