<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-01-04 ude: replaced calloutlist with orderedlist
  2007-08-24 j.h verified v2.4 : no change in "en".
  2007-05-19 ude: fixed calspair coords
  2006-03-06 lexa: reviewed and made docbook compliant
-->
<!--2010-11-26-->
<!-- This dialog is included from channel-dialog.xml-->
<sect3 id="gimp-qmask">
  <title lang="en">Quick Mask</title>
  <title lang="ja">クイックマスク</title>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Dialog Quick Mask</title>
    <title lang="ja">クイックマスクをかけられた画像</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/channel-quickmask.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    A <guilabel>Quick Mask</guilabel> is a
    <link linkend="gimp-channel-mask">Selection Mask</link>
    intended to be used temporarily to paint a selection. Temporarily means
    that, unlike a normal selection mask, it will be deleted from the
    channel list after its transformation to selection. The
    <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">selection tools</link>
    sometimes show their limits when they have to be used for doing complex
    drawing selection, as progressive. In this case, using the QuickMask is a
    good idea which can give very good results.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <quote>クイックマスク</quote>とは一時的に選択範囲を描画可能にする目的をもつ
    <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">選択マスク</link> だと言えます。
    一時的と断わったのは、 通常の選択マスクとは異なり選択範囲に戻すとチャンネル
    の一覧表から消えるからです。 徐々に変化がつくような複雑な選択範囲を描こうと
    すると、
    <link linkend="gimp-tools-selection">選択ツール</link> はしばしばその限界を
    見せてしまいます。 こんなとき、 クイックマスクを使ってみると非常に良好な
    仕上がりが期待できるでしょう。
  </para>

  <sect4>
    <title lang="en">Activating the dialog</title>
    <title lang="ja">呼び出し方</title>
    <para lang="en">
      The QuickMask can be activated in different ways:
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      クイックマスクを起用する方法はつぎのいずれかです。
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          From the image menu:
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Select</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Toggle QuickMask</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像ウィンドウのメニューより
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>選択</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>クイックマスクに切り替え</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          と辿ってチェックを入れると有効になります。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          by clicking the left-bottom button showed in red on the screenshot.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          スクリーンショットでも見えている画像ウィンドウの
          左下にある小さな正方形のボタンをクリック
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          By using the
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap>
          </keycombo>
          shortcut.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          キーボードショートカット
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect4>

  <sect4>
    <title lang="en">Creating a Quick Mask</title>
    <title lang="ja">クイックマスクの作成</title>
    <para lang="en">
      To initialize a <guilabel>Quick Mask</guilabel>,
      click the bottom-left button in the image window. If a selection was
      active in your image, then its content appears unchanged while the
      border is covered with a translucent red color. If no selection was
      active then all the image is covered with a translucent red color.
      Another click on the bottom-left button will deactivate the quick mask.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      From the channel dialog you can double click on the name or the
      thumbnail to edit the <guilabel>QMask</guilabel> attributes. Then you
      can change the <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> and its filling color.  At
      every moment you can hide the mask by clicking on the eye icon
      <guiicon>
        <inlinegraphic fileref="images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png"/>
      </guiicon>
      in front of the <guilabel>QMask</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The mask is coded in gray tones, so you must use white or gray to
      decrease the area limited by the mask and black to increase it. The area
      painted in light or dark gray will be transition areas for the selection
      like feathering. When your mask is ready, click again on the bottom-left
      button in the image window and the quick mask will be removed from the
      channel list and converted to a selection.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Quick mask's purpose is to paint a selection and its transitions with
      the paint tools without worrying about managing selection masks. It's a
      good way to isolate a subject in a picture because once the selection is
      made you only have to remove its content (or inverse if the subject is
      in the selection).
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <quote>クイックマスク</quote>を使うにはまず画像ウィンドウの左下のボタンを
      クリックしてください。 画像上に何か選択範囲があれば、 その境界線が半透明
      な赤で覆われて選択範囲の内容が変更を受けることなく表示されます。 選択範囲
      が何も無かったときは画像全体が半透明な赤で覆われます。 この左下のボタンを
      またクリックするとクイックマスクは解除されます。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      チャンネルダイアログ上ではクイックマスクの縮小見本画像か名前をダブル
      クリックすれば<quote>チャンネルプロパティの編集</quote>ダイアログが開かれ
      ますので、 ここでクイックマスクの <guilabel>塗り不透明度
      </guilabel> や塗りつぶし色を変更できます。 いつ何時でも一覧表の
      <guilabel>クイックマスク</guilabel> の欄の<quote>目</quote>のアイコン
      <guiicon>
        <inlinegraphic fileref="images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png"/>
      </guiicon>
      をクリックすればマスクを隠せます。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      マスクは灰色陰影の階調で構成されているので、 マスクで塞がれた領域を減らす
      には白か灰色を、 増やすには黒を使わなくてはなりません。 濃淡のついた灰色
      で塗られている領域は選択範囲のぼかされた境界付近のような漸進変化をして
      います。 マスクができあがったら画像ウィンドウの左下のボタンを再びクリック
      すればチャンネルの一覧表からクイックマスクが消え、 その内容は選択範囲に
      変換されます。 
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      クイックマスクの使用目的は選択マスクの管理に煩わされることなく選択範囲を
      描画ツールで描くこと、 しかも必要なら選択になだらかな強弱を加えること
      です。 このような手法は画像内にある物体を孤立させて取り出すのに使うと、
      選択範囲はもうできあがっているのであとはその範囲内の画像を (もし欲しい
      物体が範囲内にあるときは反転してから) 削除すればよいだけになりますから
      便利です。
    </para>
  </sect4>
  <sect4>
    <title lang="en">Using Quick Mask with a gradient</title>
    <title lang="ja">グラデーションとクイックマスクの利用</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
                   fileref="images/dialogs/channel-masks-gradient.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <orderedlist>
      <title lang="en">Description</title>
      <title lang="ja">説明</title>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Screenshot of the image window with activated QuickMask. As long as
          the Quickmask is activated, all operations are done on it. A
          gradient from black (left) to white (right) has been applied to the
          mask.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          クイックマスクを有効にした画像ウィンドウのスクリーンショット。
          クイックマスクが有効な間は全ての操作をクイッマスクが受ける。 マスクに
          対しグラデーションを黒 (左) から白 (右) にかけた。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The QuickMask is now disabled. The selection occupies the right half
          part of the image (marching ants) because the limit of the selection
          is at the middle of the gradient.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          クイックマスクを解除した。 選択範囲の枠 (蟻の行進) が画像の右半分だけ
          にあるのは、 選択範囲の境界線がグラデーションの中央にあるからである。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          A stroke is now added during the enabled selection. Weird! The
          gradient, although not visible, remains active all over the image,
          in selected and non selected areas!
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          選択範囲が活性化したままで描線を加えた。 不思議なことが起こった。 
          もう見えなくなったはずのグラデーションが、 選択範囲の枠内・枠外を
          問わず画像の全域にわたっていまだに残っている。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para lang="en">
      After the QuickMask Button is pressed, the command generates a
      temporary 8-bit (0-255) channel, on which the progressive selection
      work is stored. If a selection is already present the mask is
      initialized with the content of the selection. Once QuickMask has been
      activated, the image is covered by a red semi-transparent veil. This
      one represents the non-selected pixels. Any
      <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">paint tool</link>
      can be used to create the selection on the QuickMask. They should use
      only greyscale color, conforming the channel properties, white enabling
      to define the future selected place. The selection will be displayed as
      soon as the QuickMask will be toggled but its temporary channel will
      not be available anymore.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      クイックマスクボタンをクリックすると発行されるコマンドが 8 ビット (0-255) 
      チャンネルを一時的に作成するので、 ここに漸進的変化のある選択範囲も収め
      られます。 予め選択範囲ができていた場合はクイックマスクは選択範囲の内容を
      もとに初期化されます。 クイックマスクが起用されると画像は赤い半透明な薄膜
      で覆われます。 これは非選択画素を表しています。 クイックマスクを通して
      選択範囲を作成するときは
      <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">描画ツール</link> がどれでも使えます。
      チャンネルの属性を強化するにあたり、 利用できる色は白黒と灰色濃淡に
      限られます。 白い領域があとで選択範囲になります。 選択範囲の境界線は再び
      クイックマスクの切り替えをすれば直ちに表示されますが、 一時的なチャンネル
      はもうその時点から利用できなくなります。
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para lang="en">
        To save in a channel the selection done with the Quickmask select in
        the image menu
        <guimenuitem>Select/Save to Channel</guimenuitem>
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        クイックマスクで作成した選択範囲をチャンネルに保存するには、
        画像ウィンドウのメニューより
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>選択</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>チャンネルに保存</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        してください。
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect4>
  <sect4>
    <title lang="en">Usage</title>
    <title lang="ja">使用の手順</title>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          <link linkend="gimp-file-open">Open</link> an image or begin a
          <link linkend="gimp-file-new">new document</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像を
          <link linkend="gimp-file-open">開く</link> か、 あるいは
          <link linkend="gimp-file-new">新しい画像</link> を用意します。
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Activate the Quickmask using the left-bottom button in the image
          window. If a selection is present the mask is initialized with the
          content of the selection.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像ウィンドウの左下のボタンをクリックしてクイックマスクを有効に
          します。 選択範囲があるとマスクは選択範囲の内容を基に初期化されます。
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Choose a <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">drawing tool</link>
          and use it with greyscale colors on the QuickMask.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <link linkend="gimp-tools-paint">描画ツール</link>
          を呼び出して灰色陰影でクイックマスクを塗ります。
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Deactivate the Quickmask using the left-bottom button in the image
          window.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像ウィンドウの左下のボタンを使ってクイックマスクを解除します。
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect4>
</sect3>
