<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-06-20 Added Spanish translation by AntI
  2007-03-12 Kolbjorn: added no tranlsation
-->
<!--2009-09-12-->
<sect2 id="gimp-menu-filters-introduction">
  <title lang="en">Introduction to the <quote>Filters</quote> Menu</title>
  <title lang="ja"><quote>フィルタ</quote>メニューのあらまし</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Menu</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Common functions</secondary>
    <tertiary>Introduction to filters</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>フィルタ</primary>
    <secondary>メニュー</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>フィルタ</primary>
    <secondary sortas="キョウツウキノウ">共通機能</secondary>
    <tertiary sortas="アラマシ">あらまし</tertiary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">The <quote>Filters</quote> menu</title>
    <title lang="ja"><quote>フィルタ</quote>メニュー</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/menus/filters.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    terminology, a <emphasis>filter</emphasis>
    is a plug-in that modifies the appearance of an image, in most cases just
    the active layer of the image. Not all of the entries in this menu meet
    that definition, however; the word <quote>filter</quote> is often
    mis-used to mean any plug-in, regardless of what it does. Indeed, some
    of the entries in this menu do not modify images at all.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    With the exception of the top three items of the
    <guimenu>Filters</guimenu> menu, all of the entries
    are provided by plug-ins. Each plug-in decides for itself where it would
    like its menu entry to be placed. Therefore, the appearance of this menu
    can be completely different for each user. In practice, though, the
    appearance does not vary very much, because most plug-ins come with
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> when it is installed, and of course
    they are always in the same places in the menu.
  </para>
  <para lang="en"><!-- Must be rewritten for v2.4? -->
    Plug-ins are not restricted to just the <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
    menu: a plug-in can place entries in any menu. Indeed, a number of
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s basic
    functions (for example, <guimenuitem>Semi-flatten</guimenuitem>
    in the <guimenu>Layer</guimenu> menu) are implemented
    by plug-ins. But the <guimenu>Filters</guimenu> menu is the default
    place for a plug-in to place its menu entries.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    For general information on plug-ins and how to use them, see the section
    on <link linkend="gimp-concepts-plugins">Plug-ins</link>. You can find
    information on the filters that are provided with
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in the
    <link linkend="filters">Filters</link> chapter. For filters you install
    yourself, please refer to the information which came with them.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の用語法における <emphasis>フィルタ</emphasis> とは
    画像の見た目を変更するプラグインのことで、 ほとんどの場合活性レイヤーで作動
    します。 でもこのメニュー内の全ての項目がこの定義にあてはまるわけでは
    ありません。 というのも<quote>フィルタ</quote>の用語でプラグインのことを
    その作用と関係なしに呼ぶ誤用がしばしば見受けられるからです。 しかも正にこの
    メニュー内でさえ全然画像を加工しないプラグインが入っています。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <guimenu>フィルタ</guimenu> メニュー内のコマンドは冒頭の
    最上段の3つのコマンドを除き全てがプラグインで提供されています。 プラグイン
    のメニュー項目が置かれる場所はプラグイン自身が意のままに決めています。 こう
    言うとこのメニューの中身はユーザごとに全く異なった構成にもなりそうですが、 
    実際はほとんどのプラグインが<acronym>GIMP</acronym>と一緒にインストール
    された同梱物なのでメニュー上の位置はいつも同じになりますから、 見た目に
    まるきり違うようなことはありません。 [上図は私の構成です。 メニュー下部の
    ぼかしがかけられた項目は<acronym>GIMP</acronym>に同梱されていません。 なお
    この部分と冒頭のコマンドの部分は <guisubmenu>ぼかし
    </guisubmenu> サブメニュー内のフィルタプラグインを利用しました。]
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    プラグインは <guimenu>フィルタ</guimenu> メニュー内に
    あるものが全てではありません。 他のメニューにもプラグインが入っています。 
    実は<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の数々の基本機能 (例えば 
    <guimenu>レイヤー</guimenu> メニューの <guimenuitem>
    半統合</guimenuitem> コマンド) がプラグインで実装されて
    います。 でも初期設定では <guimenu>フィルタ
    </guimenu> メニューがプラグインを呼び出すメニュー項目のありかです。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    プラグインについての総合的な情報や使い方については 
    <link linkend="gimp-concepts-plugins">プラグイン</link> の節で述べて
    います。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>についてくるフィルタの情報は 
    <link linkend="filters">フィルタ</link> の章に網羅されています。 ご自身で
    インストールされたプラグインについては入手された配布物に含まれる案内に
    従ってください。
  </para>
</sect2>
