<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--Section History
  2008-04-09 Mr.Dust : added 'ko'
  2007-09-29 AntI: Added 'es'
  2006-01-02: fixed image scaling and made the file docbook compliant by lexa
  2008-01-28 jpl: update text & images
-->
<!--2012-03-09-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-theme">
  <title lang="en">Theme</title>
  <title lang="ja">テーマ</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Theme</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Theme</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ダイアログ</primary>
    <secondary sortas="カンキョウセッテイ">環境設定</secondary>
    <tertiary>テーマ</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>テーマ</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Theme Preference</title>
    <title lang="ja">環境設定 テーマのページ</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/preferences/prefs-theme.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    This page lets you select a theme, which determines many aspects of
    the appearance of the GIMP user interface, including the set of
    icons used, their sizes, fonts, spacing allowed in dialogs, etc.
    Two themes are supplied with GIMP: <guilabel>Default</guilabel>,
    which is probably best for most people, and
    <guilabel>Small</guilabel>, which may be preferable for those with
    small or low-resolution monitors.  Clicking on a theme in the list
    causes it to be applied immediately, so it is easy to see the result
    and change your mind if you don't like it.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    You can also use custom themes, either by downloading them from the
    net, or by copying one of the supplied themes and modifying it.
    Custom themes should be places in the <filename>themes</filename>
    subdirectory of your personal GIMP directory:  if they are, they
    will appear in the list here.  Each theme is actually a directory
    containing ASCII files that you can edit.  They are pretty
    complicated, and the meaning of the contents goes beyond the scope
    of this documentation, but you should feel free to experiment:  in
    the worst case, if you mess things up completely, you can always
    revert back to one of the supplied themes.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    You cannot edit the supplied themes unless you have administrator
    permissions, and even if you do, you shouldn't:  if you want to
    customize a theme, make a copy in your personal directory and work
    on it.  If you make a change and would like to see the result <quote>on
    the fly</quote>, you can do so by saving the edited theme file and then
    pressing <guilabel>Reload Current Theme</guilabel>.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    このページでは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>で使われるアイコン集とその大きさ、
    書体、 ダイアログ間取り間隙などのユーザーインターフェース外観を定めている
    テーマを選べます。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>同梱のテーマは大多数の人々に
    とって最適な <guilabel>Default</guilabel> と、 ご使用のモニターが小さいか
    低解像度な場合のための <guilabel>Small</guilabel> の 2 つです。 テーマ
    一覧表内の行をクリックすればそのテーマが直ちに適用されますから、 その
    効果を見ながら好みを楽に探れます。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    テーマはネットからダウンロードしたものや同梱のテーマを改造したものなどを
    使って誂えることも可能です。 自分流のテーマは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の
    個人用ディレクトリー内の <filename class="directory">themes</filename> 
    サブディレクトリーに置きましょう。 置かれたものはこの一覧表に現れます。 
    個々のテーマのディレクトリーには編集しやすい<acronym>ASCII</acronym>
    テキストファイルが入ります。 その内容は結構複雑なうえここで述べる限度を
    越えていますので説明しませんが、 気楽に編集をしてみてください。 内容が
    すっかりぐちゃぐちゃになる最悪の事態となっても、 同梱のテーマを選びさえ
    すればいつでも元に戻せるためです。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    同梱のテーマを直に編集できるのはシステムの管理者だけですが、 それでもしない
    でください。 これらのテーマを自分流に改造したい場合は、 その複製を個人用
    ディレクトリーに置いて、 そちらで作業してください。 変更を施す度にその場で
    結果を確かめるには、 まずそのファイルを保存してから
    <guibutton>現在のテーマの再読み込み</guibutton>
    ボタンをクリックしてください。
  </para>
</sect2>
