<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-07-17 Mr.Dust : added 'ko'
  2008-02-04 Vérification + compléments par jpl in french
  2007-09-30 AntI: Added 'es'
  2007-03-25 KoSt: added 'no'
  2006-11-01 lexa: make docbook compliant
  2006-02-25 fixed invalid image reference
-->
<!--revision2803 2009-04-01-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-window-management">
  <title lang="en">Window Management</title>
  <title lang="ja">ウィンドウ・マネジメント</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Window management</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Image Windows</primary>
    <secondary>Basic settings</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ダイアログ</primary>
    <secondary>環境設定</secondary>
    <tertiary>ウィンドウマネジメント</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>画像ウィンドウ</primary>
    <secondary>基本設定</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Window Management Preferences</title>
    <title lang="ja">環境設定 ウィンドウ・マネジメントのページ</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/preferences/ja/prefs-window-management.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    This page lets you customize the way windows are handled in GIMP. You
    should note that GIMP does not manipulate windows directly, instead it
    sends requests to the window manager (i. e., to Windows if you are running
    in Windows; to Metacity if you are running in a standard Gnome setup in
    Linux; etc). Because there are many window managers, and not all of them
    are well behaved, it cannot be guaranteed that the functions described
    here will actually work as described. However, if you are using a modern,
    standards-compliant window manager, they ought to.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    このページでは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>でどのように各ウィンドウを扱うかを
    設定します。 ご理解いただきたいのは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は各ウィンドウを
    直接は操作せず、 ウィンドウマネージャに依頼する方式をとっていることです。
    (ウィンドウマネージャとは <productname>MS Windows</productname> における
    ウィンドウズのシステム、 <productname>X11</productname> ウィンドウシステム
    で標準的に組み上げた <productname>Gnome</productname> 上の <application>
    Metacity</application> などです。) ウィンドウマネージャは数多くの種類があり
    その全てが順当に作動するわけではありませんので、 実際はここに示した機能が
    説明どおりにはたらく保証はありません。 しかし最近の標準に忠実なウィンドウ
    マネージャをお使いならば確実でしょう。
  </para>
  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="ja">オプション</title>
    <variablelist>
      <title lang="en">Window Manager Hints</title>
      <title lang="ja">ウィンドウマネージャのためのヒント</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Window type hints for the toolbox and the docks</term>
        <term lang="ja">
          ツールボックスやドックのウィンドウ形式を示すヒント
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The choices you make here determine how the Toolbox, and the docks
            that hold dialogs, will be treated. If you choose "Normal Window",
            they will be treated like any other windows. If you choose
            "Utility Window", they will be raised into visibility whenever you
            activate an image window, and kept in front of every image window.
            If you choose "Keep above", they will be kept in front of every
            other window at all times. Note that changes you make here will
            not take effect until the next time you start GIMP.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            ここで選択できるのはツールボックスとダイアログ群を纏めるドックの
            扱われ方です。 <guimenuitem>通常のウィンドウ</guimenuitem> を選択
            した場合は他のウィンドウと同じように扱われます。 <guimenuitem>
            ユーティリティウィンドウ</guimenuitem> を選択した場合は、 隠れて
            いても画像ウィンドウを活性化すればいつでも現れ出るようになり、
            全ての画像ウィンドウよりも前に居座ります。 <guimenuitem>常に前面
            </guimenuitem> を選ぶと常時他の全てのウィンドウよりも前面に居座り
            ます。 この設定が有効になるのは次回<acronym>GIMP</acronym>を起動
            して以降になりますことをご承知おきください。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title lang="en">Focus</title>
      <title lang="ja">フォーカス</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Activate the focused image</term>
        <term lang="ja">
          フォーカスされた画像をアクティブに(<accel>F</accel>)
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Normally, when you focus an image window (usually indicated by a
            change in the color of the frame), it becomes the "active image"
            for GIMP, and therefore the target for any image-related actions
            you perform.  Some people, though, prefer to set up their window
            managers such that any window entered by the pointer is
            automatically focused.  If you do this, you may find that it is
            inconvenient for focused images to automatically become active,
            and may be happier if you uncheck this option.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            普通はどれかの画像ウィンドウをフォーカスすると (たいていはその
            ウィンドウ枠の色が変化するのでわかります)、 その画像は<acronym>GIMP
            </acronym>の<quote>活性画像</quote>になり、 画像に関連した操作の
            対象となります。 ところがウィンドウにマウスポインタをかざしただけ
            だけで自動的にフォーカスするようなウィンドウマネージャの設定を好む
            人々もいます。 この設定を適用してみると画像ウィンドウにフォーカス
            しただけでその画像が自動的に活性化するのは不便なことがわかります。
            そういった方はこのオプションのチェックを外すとよいでしょう。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <variablelist>
      <title lang="en">Window Positions</title>
      <title lang="ja">ウィンドウ位置</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Save window positions on exit</term>
        <term lang="ja">終了時にウィンドウの位置を保存(<accel>S</accel>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            If this option is checked, the next time you start GIMP,
            you will see the same set of dialog windows, in the same
            positions they occupied when you last exited.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このオプションにチェックを入れると、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>を起動
            したときに、 ダイアログのウィンドウやツールボックスが前回終了時点
            で置かれた位置と大きさのままに開かれます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Save Window Positions Now</term>
        <term lang="ja">現在のウィンドウ位置を保存(<accel>N</accel>)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This button is only useful if "Save window positions on exit" is
            unchecked. It allows you to set up your windows they way you like,
            click the button, and then have them come up in that arrangement
            each time you start GIMP.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このボタンは
            <guilabel>終了時にウィンドウの位置を保存(<accel>S</accel>)
            </guilabel> にチェックを入れない場合に役立ちます。 あらかじめお好み
            の位置にウィンドウを置いてからこのボタンをクリックすると、
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>を起動する度にその配置でウィンドウが開かれ
            るようになります。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Reset Saved Window Positions to Default Values</term>
        <term lang="ja">
          保存されているウィンドウ位置をリセット(<accel>R</accel>)
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            If you decide that you are unhappy with the arrangement of windows
            you have saved, and would rather go back to the default
            arrangement than spend time moving them around, you can do so by
            pressing this button.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            いったん保存したウィンドウ配置が気に入らなくなったときに、 それらを
            いちいち再配置するよりは初期設定の配置に戻してしまいたいとお考え
            ならばこのボタンをクリックすればよいのです。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
