<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2008-04-08 Mr.Dust : added 'ko'
  2006-11-01 lexa: made the file docbook compliant
  2008-01-28 jpl: update text & images
-->
<!--2012-05-02-->
<sect2 id="gimp-prefs-interface">
  <title lang="en">Interface</title>
  <title lang="ja">ユーザーインターフェース</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
    <tertiary>Interface</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Interface</primary>
    <secondary>Preferences</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Navigation</primary>
    <secondary>Preview size</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Preview</primary>
    <secondary>Navigation preview size</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ダイアログ</primary>
    <secondary sortas="カンキョウセッテイ">設定</secondary>
    <tertiary>インターフェース</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>インターフェース</primary>
    <secondary sortas="カンキョウセッテイ">設定</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ナビゲーション</primary>
    <secondary>プレビューサイズ</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>プレビュー</primary>
    <secondary sortas="ナビゲーションノプレビューサイズ">
      ナビゲーションのプレビューサイズ
    </secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Assorted Interface Preferences</title>
    <title lang="ja">設定 ユーザーインターフェースのページ</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/preferences/prefs-interface.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          This page lets you customize language, layer/channel previews and
          keyboard shortcuts.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          このページでは言語と、 レイヤーとチャンネルのプレビューと
          キーボードショートカットが誂えられる。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <variablelist>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="ja">オプション</title>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Languages</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Previews</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Keyboard Shortcuts</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ゲンゴ(ニホンゴ)">言語(日本語)</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary>プレビュー</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary>キーボードショートカット</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Language</term>
      <term lang="ja">言語の設定</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          The GIMP's default language is that of your system. You can select
          another language in the drop-down list. You have to start GIMP again
          to make this change effective. Please refer to 
          <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-running-language"/>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は初期設定の場合、 お使いのシステムと
          同じ言語を用います。 他の言語へはこの引き出しリストで切り替え
          できます。 ただしこの指定は<acronym>GIMP</acronym>を再起動したあとに
          反映されます。
          <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-running-language"/> を参照してください。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Previews</term>
      <term lang="ja">プレビュー</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          By default, GIMP shows miniature previews of the contents of
          layers and channels in several places, including the Layers
          dialog.  If for some reason you would prefer to disable
          these, you can do it by unchecking <guilabel>Enable layer and
          channel previews</guilabel>.  If you do want previews to be shown,
          you can customize their sizes using the menus for <guilabel>Default
          layer and channel preview size</guilabel> and <guilabel>Navigation
          preview size</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          初期設定では、 レイヤーダイアログなどいろいろな場面で画像の縮小見本が
          表示されます。 何らかの理由でこの機能を無効にする場合には、
          <guilabel>レイヤーとチャンネルのプレビューを表示する</guilabel> 
          のチェックを外してください。 プレビューを表示する場合には
          <guilabel>プレビューサイズの既定値</guilabel> や
          <guilabel>ナビゲーションのプレビューサイズ</guilabel> 
          のメニューでその大きさが 9 段階に調節できます。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry id="prefs-kbd-shortcuts" xreflabel="Keyboard Shortcuts">
      <term lang="en">Keyboard Shortcuts</term>
      <term lang="ja">キーボードショートカット</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Any menu item can be activated by holding down
          <keycap>Alt</keycap> and pressing a sequence of keys.
          Normally, the key associated with each menu entry is shown
          as an underlined letter in the text, called <emphasis>
          accelerator</emphasis>.  If for some reason you
          would prefer the underlines to go away (maybe because you
          think they're ugly and you don't use them anyway), then you
          can make this happen by unchecking <guilabel>Show menu
          mnemonics</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          GIMP can give you the ability to create keyboard shortcuts
          (key combinations that activate a menu entry) dynamically,
          by pressing the keys while the pointer hovers over the
          desired menu entry.  However, this capability is disabled by
          default, because it might lead novice users to accidentally
          overwrite the standard keyboard shortcuts.  If you want to
          enable it, check <guilabel>Use dynamics keyboard shortcuts</guilabel>
          here.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          Pressing the button for <guilabel>Configure Keyboard
          Shortcuts</guilabel> brings up the Shortcut Editor, which gives you
          a graphical interface to select menu items and assign shortcuts
          to them.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          If you change shortcuts, you will probably want your changes
          to continue to apply in future GIMP sessions.  If not,
          uncheck <guilabel>Save keyboard shortcuts on exit</guilabel>. But
          remember that you have done this, or you may be frustrated
          later. If you don't want to save shortcuts on exit every
          session, you can save the current settings at any time using the
          <guilabel>Save Keyboard Shortcuts Now</guilabel> button, and they will
          be applied to future sessions.  If you decide that you have made
          some bad decisions concerning shortcuts, you can reset them to
          their original state by pressing <guilabel>Reset Saved Keyboard
          Shortcuts to Default Values</guilabel>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          メニュー上の項目は <keycap>Alt</keycap> キーと個々の呼応するキーとの
          組み合わせにより活性化できます。 普通はそれぞれのメニュー見出しに
          [(丸括弧)に入った]下線つきの英数字がついていて、 これらを 
          <emphasis>アクセラレーター</emphasis> といいます。 (その表記が煩わしい
          とか使うつもりもないというふうな) 何らかの理由でこの表示が不要な
          場合は、 
          <guilabel>メニューにニーモニック (アクセスキー)を表示</guilabel> の
          チェックを外すとよいでしょう。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>はキーボードショートカット (メニュー項目を
          活性化するキーやキーの組み合わせ) が動的に作成可能です。 対象となる
          メニュー項目上にマウスポインタを合わせ、 キーを押せば登録完了です。
          ただしこの機能は初心者ユーザーが誤って標準のキーボードショートカットを
          上書きする恐れがあるため、 初期設定では無効となっています。 これを
          有効にするには
          <guilabel>動的キーボードショートカットを使用する</guilabel> に
          チェックを入れてください。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <guibutton>キーボードショートカット設定...</guibutton> 
          ボタンをクリックすると<quote>キーボードショートカット設定</quote>
          ダイアログが開かれます。 ここには[あらゆるコマンドと]
          メニュー項目が並んでおり、 ショートカットの登録が視覚的に行えます。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          登録変更したショートカットはおそらくこれからも<acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          でずっと使い続けるのを念頭に置かれている方がほとんどだと思います。
          もしそうでないのなら、 
          <guilabel>終了時にキーボードショートカットを保存する</guilabel>
          のチェックを外しておくとよいでしょう。 でもこのことを覚えておかないと
          あとで困るはめになります。 ショートカットの保存が毎終了時では嫌な方は
          <guilabel>今すぐキーボードショートカットを保存</guilabel> を
          クリックすれば即座に保存できます。 ショートカットまわり
          で何か登録の手違いをしたように思われるときには、 
          <guilabel>キーボードショートカットをリセット</guilabel>
          ボタンをクリックすれば出荷時設定に戻せます。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect2>
