<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--Section History
  2008-03-15 Mr.Dust : added korean contents
  2008-01-14  PP reviewed for fr
  2007-10-07 lexa: reviewed de for GIMP 2.4
  2007-08-27 lexa: replaced table by complex figures
  2007-06-17 kost: added norwegian
  2007-01-13 lexa: enhanced docbook compliance
-->
<!--2009-05-04-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-painting">
  <title lang="en">Painting Tools (Pencil, Paintbrush, Airbrush)</title>
  <title lang="ja">筆触ツール (鉛筆、 絵筆、 エアブラシ)</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Painting</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ツール</primary>
    <secondary sortas="ヒッショク">筆触</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Painting example</title>
    <title lang="ja">描画の例</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/toolbox/painting-examples.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          Three strokes painted with the same round fuzzy brush (outline shown
          in upper left), using the Pencil (left), Paintbrush (middle), and
          Airbrush (right).
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          3つの描線は同じ円形のぼかし入りブラシ(左上の枠内に概形図)を用い、
          左から順に鉛筆、 絵筆、 エアブラシで描画。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The tools in this group are GIMP's basic painting tools, and they have
    enough features in common to be worth discussing together in this section.
    Features common to all brush tools are described in the
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">Common Features</link>
    section. Features specific to an individual tool are described in the
    section devoted to that tool.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The Pencil is the crudest of the tools in this group: it makes hard,
    non-anti-aliased brushstrokes. The Paintbrush is intermediate: it is
    probably the most commonly used of the group. The Airbrush is the most
    flexible and controllable.  This flexibility also makes it a bit more
    difficult to use than the Paintbrush, however.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    All of these tools share the same brushes, and the same options for
    choosing colors, either from the basic palette or from a gradient. All are
    capable of painting in a wide variety of modes.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    ここに挙げたツール群は<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の基本的な描画ツールで、
    このようにまとめて解説するのに見合うほどの機能を共通して持っています。
    描画ツール全般に共通する機能については、
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-brush">共通機能</link> の節をご覧ください。
    それぞれのツール固有の機能については個別に解説した節があります。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    鉛筆はこの一群のツールのなかでも最も無骨であり、 描線はごつごつとして硬く、
    アンチエイリアスがかかっていません。 絵筆はこの一群のなかでは中間的で、
    いちばんよく使われているはずです。 エアブラシは最も柔軟性に富み操縦可能性
    が高いツールです。
    ただしその柔軟性のせいで絵筆よりは扱いがやや難しくなっています。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    これらのツールはともに同じブラシが利用でき、 同じオプションで基本のパターン
    (文様)やグラデーションから色が選べます。 いずれも多彩なモードを描画に
    生かせます。
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers</title>
    <title lang="ja">キー修飾</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Holding down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key changes each of these
            tools to a <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">Color
              Picker</link>: clicking on any pixel of any layer sets the
            foreground color (as displayed in the Toolbox Color Area) to the
            color of the pixel.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            どのツールも <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> キーを押している間は
            <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">スポイト (カラーピッカー)
            </link> に変身し、 レイヤー上をクリックすればその画素 (ピクセル) の
            色が描画色 (ツールボックスの色領域で表示されています) になります。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
