<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-11-23 ciampix: added Italian translation
  2007-10-26 ude: added German translation
  2007-10-15 j.h : created (inspired from the GIMP Developers site)
-->
<!--2012-03-07-->
<sect2 id="gimp-edit-fade">
  <title lang="en">Fade</title>
  <title lang="ja">&hellip; をフェード...</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Fade</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>フェード</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    This command is usually grayed out. It becomes active if you use the Fill
    function or the Blend tool, or if you apply some filters.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    It allows you to modify the paint mode and opacity of the
    <emphasis>last</emphasis> drawable operation (Fill, Blend, Filter) by
    creating a blend between the current state of the layer and the previous
    state. It performs the following operations: copy the active drawable,
    undo the last action, paste the copy as a new layer, set its
    <quote>Opacity</quote>, and merge both new layer and previously active
    drawable.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    普段 <guimenuitem>フェード...</guimenuitem> コマンドは
    灰色無効になっています。 これが利用可能になるのは塗りつぶしツールやブレンド
    ツール、 あるいはある種のフィルターを使用した後です。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    描画対象に対し <emphasis>最後に</emphasis> 加えられた操作が塗りつぶしツール
    やブレンド (グラデーション) ツールやフィルターを用いたものであるとき、 その
    操作前の状態と操作後の状態の両者間の融合方法に関わる描画モードと不透明度を
    このコマンドで変更できます。 具体的には操作後の活性描画対象の複製をとって
    からその操作前の状態に戻し、 新たなレイヤーとして複製を貼り付けてその
    レイヤーモードや不透明度が調節できるようにします。 
    <guibutton>フェード</guibutton> ボタンをクリックすると複製レイヤーと
    元の活性描画対象が統合されます。
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Activate the command</title>
    <title lang="ja">コマンドの呼び出し方</title>

    <para lang="en">
      You can get to this command from the image Menu bar through:
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fade...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      画像ウィンドウのメニューより
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>編集</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>&hellip; をフェード...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="ja">オプション</title>

    <para lang="en">
      This command brings up a dialog window:
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">このコマンドは下図のようなダイアログを開きます。</para>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">The <quote>Fade</quote> dialog</title>
      <title lang="ja"><quote>&hellip; をフェード</quote>ダイアログ</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/edit/fade-options.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Mode</term>
        <term lang="ja">モード</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This drop-down list allows you to choose a
            <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Layer merge mode</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            この引き出しリストから
            <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">レイヤー統合のモード
            </link> が選べます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Opacity</term>
        <term lang="ja">不透明度</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This slider value is initially set to the opacity of the color
            you used with the Fill or Blend tool, which corresponds to
            the current state. Lowering the opacity to 0 changes the drawable
            to its previous state. Intermediate values produce a mixture of
            the two according to the mode you have chosen. The effect of
            this setting is visible in real time in the image, but you have
            to click on the <guibutton>Fade</guibutton> button to validate
            it.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このスライダーの初期値は直前の操作に用いた塗りつぶしツールや
            ブレンドツールの塗色の不透明度に設定されています。 不透明度を 0 に
            近づけると描画対象は操作前の状態に戻ります。 中間的な値を与えると
            操作の前後の状態の間をとった描画になります。 ここで行なった調節は
            即座に画像に反映されますが、 確定させるには 
            <guibutton>フェード</guibutton> ボタンをクリックしてください。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
