<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-05-26 j.h: no change for v2.8
  2007-09-30 j.h : updated to v2.4. Channel option added
  2007-06-15 j.h : some improvement in Add Layer Mask explanations
  2006-03-09 lexa: reviewed and made docbook compliant
-->
<!--2012-03-25-->
<sect3 id="gimp-layer-mask">
  <title lang="en">Layer masks</title>
  <title lang="ja">レイヤーマスク</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layer mask</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Masks</primary>
    <secondary>Layer mask</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>レイヤーマスク</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>マスク</primary>
    <secondary>レイヤーマスク</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en"><quote>Add mask</quote> dialog</title>
    <title lang="ja"><quote>レイヤーマスクを追加</quote>ダイアログ</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/layer-mask-add.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Overview</term>
      <term lang="ja">概観</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          A transparency mask can be added to each layer, it's called Layer
          mask. A layer mask has the same size and same number of pixels as
          the layer to which it is attached. Every pixel of the mask can then
          be coupled with a pixel at the same location in the layer. The mask
          is a set of pixels in gray-tone on a value scale from 0 to 255. The
          pixels with a value 0 are black and give a full transparency to the
          coupled pixel in the layer. The pixels with a value 255 are white
          and give a full opacity to the coupled pixel in the layer.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          To create a layer mask start with a right click on the layer to call
          the context menu and select <guilabel>Add layer mask</guilabel>
          in the menu. A dialog appears where you can initialize the content of
          the mask:
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          レイヤーには各層ごとにレイヤーマスクと呼ばれる透過効果マスクが加え
          られます。 レイヤーマスクはレイヤーと同じ大きさがあり、 属する
          レイヤーの各画素に対応する同数の画素をもっています。 つまりマスクの
          各画素はレイヤーと同位置の画素と対をなしています。 マスクは 0 から
          255 の値をもつ陰影画素の集合です。 値が 0 の画素は黒くなりレイヤーの
          同位置の画素を完全透過にします。 値が 255 の画素は白になり、 
          レイヤーの同位置の画素を完全不透明にします。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          レイヤーマスクを加えるにはまずそのレイヤーをマウスの 
          <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> でクリックすると出てくる脈絡
          メニューで <guimenuitem>レイヤーマスクの追加...</guimenuitem>
          を選んでください。 すると
          ダイアログが開かれ、 つぎのようなマスクの内容で初期化できます。
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              <guilabel>White (full opacity)</guilabel>: the mask is white
              in the Layer Dialog. So, all pixels of the layer are visible
              in the image window since painting the mask with white makes
              layer pixels fully visible. You will paint with black to make
              layer pixels transparent.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <guilabel>完全不透明(白)</guilabel>: ダイアログ
              上ではマスクが白くなります。 マスクを白く塗るとレイヤーの画素が
              完全に可視化することから、 この場合、 画像ウィンドウの全ての画素
              が見えます。 黒でマスクを塗るとレイヤーのその位置は透明に
              なります。
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              <guilabel>Black (full transparency)</guilabel>: the mask is
              black in the Layer Dialog. So, the layer is fully transparent
              since painting the mask with black makes layer pixels
              transparent. Painting with white will remove the mask and make
              layer pixels visible.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <guilabel>完全透明(黒)</guilabel>: ダイアログ上
              ではマスクが黒くなります。 マスクを黒く塗るとレイヤーの画素が透明
              になりますから、 この場合レイヤーは完全透過です。 白でマスクを
              塗るとマスクは剥がれ、 レイヤーの画素が見えるようになります。
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              <guilabel>Layer's alpha channel</guilabel>: the mask is
              initialized according to the content of layer Alpha
              channel.  If the layer still contains transparency it's
              copied in the mask.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <guilabel>レイヤーのアルファチャンネル</guilabel>: マスクは
              レイヤーのアルファチャンネルの内容どおりに初期化されます。 
              既にレイヤーに透過効果があればそれがマスクに
              複写されますが、 もしなければ<quote>完全透明(黒)</quote>と同じ
              ように初期化されます。
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              <guilabel>Transfer layer's alpha channel</guilabel>:
              Does the same thing as the previous option, except that it
              also resets the layer's alpha channel to full opacity.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <guilabel>レイヤーのアルファチャンネルを移転</guilabel>: 
              マスクの初期化は前のオプションと同じですが、
              レイヤーのアルファチャンネルが全面的に完全不透明に戻されます。
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              <guilabel>Selection</guilabel> : the mask is initialized
              according to pixel values found in the selection.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <guilabel>選択範囲</guilabel>: マスクは各画素の
              選択の値をもとに初期化されます。
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              <guilabel>Grayscale copy of layer</guilabel>: the mask
              is initialized according to pixel values of the layer.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <guilabel>レイヤーのグレースケールのコピー</guilabel>: 
              マスクはレイヤーの画素の値をもとに初期化されます。
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              <guilabel>Channel</guilabel>: The layer mask is initialized
              with a selection mask you have created before, stored in the
              Channel dialog.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <guilabel>チャンネル</guilabel>: 
              <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">選択マスク</link> を作成
              しチャンネルダイアログに保管してあれば、 それをレイヤーマスクの
              初期化に利用できます。
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              <guilabel>Invert mask</guilabel> : This checkbox allows you to
              invert : black turns to white and white turns to black.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <guilabel>マスク反転</guilabel>: このチェック
              ボックスで白黒が反転します。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para lang="en">
          When the mask is created it appears as a thumbnail right to the
          layer thumbnail. By clicking alternatively on the layer and mask
          thumbnail you can enable one or other. The active item has a white
          border (which is not well visible around a white mask). That's an
          important point. Always keep the Layers Dialog prominently when
          working with masks, because you can't see, looking at the canvas,
          which of the layer or the mask is active.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          Pressing <keycap>Alt</keycap> (or
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo>  and
          click on the layer mask thumbnail) is equivalent to the
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask-show">Show Layer Mask</link>
          command : the layer mask border turns to green. If you press
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> the border is red and the result is
          equivalent to the
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask-disable">Disable Layer Mask</link>
          command. To return to normal view redo last operation. These
          options are for greater convenience in your work.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          マスクを作成すると、 その縮小画像がレイヤーの縮小画像の右隣に
          現れます。 レイヤーとレイヤーマスクはその縮小見本画像のどちらか一方を
          クリックすればそれが描画対象になります。 活性化された方に白の枠線
          (マスクが白くなっていると見えづらい) がつきます。 これが肝心な点で、 
          キャンバスを見たところで描画対象がレイヤーなのかマスクなのかは
          一切判りませんので、 マスクを扱う際には常にレイヤーダイアログが
          見えるようにしておきましょう。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <keycap>Alt</keycap> キーを押しながら (システムによっては
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> の
          組み合わせを押しながら) レイヤーダイアログ上のレイヤーマスクの縮小
          見本画像をクリックすると、
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask-show">レイヤーマスクを表示</link>
          のコマンドがはたらき、 マスク縮小見本の枠線が緑色に変わります。
          代わりに <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> キーを押しながらのクリックだと
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask-disable">レイヤーマスクを無効化</link>
          のコマンドがはたらき、 枠線は赤色に変わります。 通常表示に戻すには
          直前のコマンドを再度実行してください。 これらのオプションは作業を容易
          にするためにあります。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Layer Mask example</term>
      <term lang="ja">レイヤーマスクの例</term>
      <listitem>
        <figure>
          <title lang="en">A layer with layer mask</title>
          <title lang="ja">レイヤーマスク付きのレイヤー</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="images/dialogs/examples/layer-mask-1.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para lang="en">
                This image has a background layer with a flower and another
                blue one, fully opaque. A white layer mask has been added to
                the blue layer. In the image window, the blue layer remains
                visible because a white mask makes layer pixels visible.
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                画像には花が写っている背景レイヤーと、 その上に完全不透明な青い
                レイヤーがある。 白いレイヤーマスクが青のレイヤーに加えられた。
                白いマスクはレイヤーの画素を完全可視化するので、 画像ウィンドウ
                では依然として青いレイヤーが見えている。
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <title lang="en">Painting the layer mask</title>
          <title lang="ja">レイヤーマスクに描くと</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                         fileref="images/dialogs/examples/layer-mask-2.png" />
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para lang="en">
                The layer mask is active. You paint with black color, which
                makes the layer transparent: the underlying layer becomes
                visible.
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                レイヤーマスクを活性化した。 黒で描くとレイヤーが透過する。 
                背後のレイヤーが見えるようになる。
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect3>
