<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-09-25 AntI: Added 'es'
  2007-02-04 added 'no' by KoSt
  2006-08-26 lexa: fixed docbook errors
  yyyy-mm-tt n.n.: added section for context menu
-->

<!--2009-05-10-->
<sect1 id="gimp-menus-introduction">
  <title lang="en">Introduction to Menus</title>
  <title lang="ja">メニューのあらまし</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Menus</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>メニュー</primary>
    <secondary sortas="アラマシ">あらまし</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <!--TODO: add image menubar screenshot (?)-->

  <para lang="en">
    There are many places in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> where you can
    find menus. The aim of this chapter is to explain all the commands that
    are accessible from the image menu bar and the image menu you can get by
    right clicking in the canvas. All the context menus and the menu entries
    for the other dialogs are described elsewhere in the chapters that
    describe the dialogs themselves.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>にはいたるところにメニューがあります。 この章の目的
    は、 画像ウィンドウのメニューで呼び出せるコマンドの解説です。 画像メニュー
    は画像ウィンドウのメニューバーをクリックするか、 キャンバスを <mousebutton>
    第2ボタン</mousebutton> でクリックすると開きます。 そのほかダイアログに
    付属する脈絡メニューやそのメニュー項目は、
    <link linkend="dialogs">個々のダイアログの説明</link> のなかで解説して
    います。
  </para>

  <sect2 id="context-menus">
    <title lang="en">Context Menus</title>
    <title lang="ja">脈絡メニュー</title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Context menus</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ミャクラクメニュー">脈絡メニュー</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      If you right-click on certain parts of the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> interface, a
      <quote>context menu</quote> opens, which leads to a variety of
      functions. Some places where you can access context menus are:
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のインタフェースはその特定部位をマウスの
      <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> でクリックするといろいろな機能が
      入っている脈絡メニューが開きます。 脈絡メニューが出てくる部分はつぎの
      とおりです。
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Clicking on an image window displays the Image menu. This is useful
          when you are working in full-screen mode, without a menubar.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像ウィンドウのキャンバス内を <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton>
          でクリックすると画像ウィンドウのメニューが呼び出せます。 メニューバー
          を隠して全画面モードで作業しているときはこの方法が便利です。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Clicking on a layer in the Layers Dialog or on a channel in the
          Channels Dialog displays functions for the selected layer or
          channel.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          レイヤーダイアログのレイヤーやチャンネルダイアログのチャンネルなどは
          <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> でクリックするとそのダイアログの
          脈絡メニューが呼び出せます。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Right-clicking on the image menubar has the same effect as
          left-clicking.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像ウィンドウの左上のメニューボタンをクリックしてもメニューが
          呼び出せます。<!--原文破棄-->
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Right-clicking on the title bar displays functions which do not
          belong to <acronym>GIMP</acronym>,
          but to the window manager program on your computer.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          タイトルバーを <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> でクリックすると
          メニューか何かの機能が呼び出されますが、 これは<acronym>GIMP
          </acronym>に属したものではなく、 お使いのコンピュータのウィンドウ
          マネージャの機能です。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="tear-off-menus">
    <title lang="en">Tear-off menus</title>
    <title lang="ja">切り取り可能なメニュー</title>

    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Tear-off menus</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Tear-off line</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="キリトリカノウナメニュー">
        切り取り可能なメニュー
    </primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="キリトリセン">切り取り線</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para lang="en">
      There is an interesting property associated with some of the menus in
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      These are any of the menus from the Image context menu you get by
      right-clicking on the canvas and any of its submenus. (You can tell
      that a menu item leads to a submenu because there is an
      <guiicon>
        <inlinegraphic fileref="images/menus/icon-submenu.png" format="PNG"/>
      </guiicon>
      icon next to it.) When you bring up any of these menus, there is a
      dotted line at the top of it (tear-off line). By clicking on this
      dotted line, you detach the menu under it and it becomes a separate
      window.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の一部のメニューには面白い特徴が備わっています。
      各ダイアログの脈絡メニューや画像ウィンドウメニューのサブメニュー (
      <guiicon>
        <inlinegraphic fileref="images/menus/icon-submenu.png" format="PNG"/>
      </guiicon>
      の印がサブメニューのあるメニュー項目の右端についていることで分かります。)
      はもちろん、 キャンバスを <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> でクリック
      すると出てくる親メニューは、 呼び出すとその上辺に破線 (切り取り線) が
      つきます。 この破線をクリックするとこのメニューは切り離され補助ウィンドウ
      になります。
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">
        The <quote>windows</quote> submenu and its tear-off submenu
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/ja/local-windows-submenu.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/menus/ja/detached-submenu.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">
      Tear-off menus are actually independent. They are always visible, their
      functions always apply to the current image, and they persist when all
      of the images are closed. You can close a tear-off submenu by clicking
      on the dotted line again or closing the window from the window manager
      on your computer (often by clicking on an X icon in the upper right
      corner of the window).
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      切り取られたメニューは実質的に独立しています。 これは常設になり、 現在
      活性化している画像にその機能が適用されます。 画像が全て閉じられてもその
      メニューは残ります。 このウィンドウ化したメニューを閉じるには再び破線を
      クリックするか、 お使いのコンピュータのウィンドウマネージャのウィンドウを
      閉じる機能 (よくある例はタイトルバーの端の×印をクリック) を利用します。
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
