<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--Section History
  2009-02-21 j.h: revised v2.6
  2008-04-05 Mr.Dust : reviewed and added 'ko'
  2008-01-14 alex falappa: fixed outstanding TODOs for 'it'
  2008-01-05 jpl: added lock-alpha image 'en;fr'
  2007-08-18: alex falappa: translated example for Alpha Channel
  2007-07-11: Added example for Alpha Channel by j.h
  2007-06-14: alex falappa: updated italian Alpha channel section
  2007-02-04: rebuilt Alpha channel section en;fr by j.h
  2006-09-06: added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-02-17: added italian translation by ciampix
  2005-12-26: added german translation and made the file docbook compliant by lexa
-->
<!--revision2806 2009-04-07-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-layers">
  <title lang="en">Introduction to Layers</title>
  <title lang="ja">レイヤーのあらまし</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Layers</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>レイヤー</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para lang="en">
    A good way to visualize a GIMP image is as a stack of transparencies: in
    GIMP terminology, each individual transparency is called a
    <emphasis>layer</emphasis>. There is no limit, in principle, to the number
    of layers an image can have: only the amount of memory available on the
    system. It is not uncommon for advanced users to work with images
    containing dozens of layers.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The organization of layers in an image is shown by the Layers dialog,
    which is the second most important type of dialog window in GIMP, after
    the Main Toolbox. The appearance of the Layers dialog is shown in the
    adjoining illustration. How it works is described in detail in the
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers Dialog</link>
    section, but we will touch on some aspects of it here, in relation to the
    layer properties that they display.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    <indexterm><primary>Drawable</primary></indexterm>
    Each open image has at any time a single
    <emphasis>active drawable</emphasis>. A <quote>drawable</quote>
    is a GIMP concept that includes layers, but also several other types of
    things, such as channels, layer masks, and the selection mask. (Basically,
    a <quote>drawable</quote>
    is anything that can be drawn on with painting tools). If a layer is
    currently active, it is shown highlighted in the Layers dialog, and its
    name is shown in the status area of the image window. If not, you can
    activate it by clicking on it. If none of the layers are highlighted, it
    means the active drawable is something other than a layer.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    In the menubar above an image window, you can find a menu called
    <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>, containing a number of commands that
    affect the active layer of the image.  The same menu can be
    accessed by right-clicking in the Layers dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の画像はあたかも透明なシートを重ね合わせるようにした
    うまい見せ方ができます。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の用語ではそれぞれの透明
    シートのことを <emphasis>レイヤー</emphasis> と呼びます。 システムのメモリ
    容量が許せば、 画像に使うレイヤーは根本的に何層にも増やせます。 しかし上級
    ユーザでも普通は何十層もレイヤーがある画像を扱うようなことはしません。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    レイヤーが画像上で重ね合わされている様子はレイヤーダイアログで見られます。
    レイヤーダイアログは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>にとってはツールボックスに次いで
    重要なダイアログです。 そのはたらきは
    <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">レイヤーダイアログ</link> の節で詳しく
    説明してありますが、 レイヤーの属性表示の機能についてはここでも触れることに
    します。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <indexterm>
      <primary>描画対象</primary>
    </indexterm>
    画像は開かれるとそれぞれに <emphasis>活性描画対象</emphasis> をひとつ
    持ちます。 レイヤーは<quote>描画対象</quote>のひとつですが、 他にも
    チャンネルやレイヤーマスク、 選択マスクもこれに含まれます。 (基本的には、
    <quote>描画対象</quote>とは描画ツールで書き込めるもの全般を表しています。)
    現在活性化しているレイヤーはレイヤーダイアログで強調表示され、 画像
    ウィンドウ下部の状態情報の区画でその名前が表示されます。 不活性レイヤーは
    レイヤーダイアログ上でクリックすると活性化します。 いずれのレイヤーも
    強調表示されていない場合は、 レイヤー以外の描画対象が活性化していることに
    なります。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    画像ウィンドウ上部のメニューバーに、 <guimenu>レイヤー(<accel>L</accel>)
    </guimenu> と書かれたメニューがあります。 主に現在活性化しているレイヤーを
    処理する様々なコマンドがここから呼びだせます。 同じ目的のメニューが
    レイヤーダイアログにもあります。 こちらはレイヤーダイアログ上を
    <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> でクリックすると出てきます。
  </para>

  <sect2 id="gimp-layer-properties">
    <title lang="en">Layer Properties</title>
    <title lang="ja">レイヤーの諸特性</title>
    <para lang="en">
      Each layer in an image has a number of important attributes:
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      画像上のレイヤーはそれぞれが数々の重要な属性を有しています:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Name</term>
        <term lang="ja">レイヤー名</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Every layer has a name. This is assigned automatically when the
            layer is created, but you can change it. You can change the name
            of a layer either by double-clicking on it in the Layers dialog,
            or by right-clicking there and then selecting the top entry in the
            menu that appears,
            <guimenuitem>Edit Layer Attributes</guimenuitem>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            全てのレイヤーは名前がつけられます。 レイヤーが作られるときに自動的
            に名付けられることもありますが、 変更もできます。 レイヤー名は
            レイヤーダイアログ上で名前を変えたいレイヤーの名前をダブルクリック
            すればその場で書き換えられます。 あるいはレイヤーダイアログ上を
            マウスの <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> でクリックして出て
            くるメニューの最上部にある <guimenuitem>
            レイヤー名の変更(<accel>E</accel>)... </guimenuitem> をクリック
            すると、 ダイアログが現れますのでここで
            現在活性化しているレイヤーの名前を変更できます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Presence or absence of an alpha channel</term>
        <term lang="ja">アルファチャンネルの追加と削除</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Background layer</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Transparency</primary>
            <secondary>Background layer transparency</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>背景レイヤー</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>透過効果</primary>
            <secondary>背景レイヤーの透明化</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            An alpha channel encodes information about how transparent a layer
            is at each pixel. It is visible in the Channel Dialog: white is
            complete opacity, black is complete transparency and grey levels
            are partial transparencies.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            The background layer is particular. If you have just created a
            new image, it has still only one layer which is a background
            layer. If the image has been created with an opaque Fill type,
            this one layer has no Alpha channel. If you add a new layer,
            even with an opaque Fill type, an Alpha channel is automatically
            created, which applies to all layers apart from the background
            layer. To get a background layer with transparency, either you
            create your new image with a transparent Fill type, or you use
            the
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-add">Add an Alpha Channel</link>.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Every layer other than the bottom layer of an image has
            automatically an Alpha channel, but you can't see a grayscale
            representation of the alpha values. See
            <link linkend="glossary-alpha">Alpha</link> in Glossary for
            more information.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            アルファチャンネルは各レイヤーの画素ごとの透過程度の情報を符号化
            します。 チャンネルダイアログ上で可視化されています。 白は完全
            不透明、 黒は完全透過を表し、 灰色は各段階の不完全透過を表して
            います。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            背景レイヤーはこの件で独特です。 新しい画像を作成した直後の段階
            では、 画像のレイヤーは背景レイヤーの一層だけです。 作成の際に塗り
            つぶし色に透明以外を指定した場合はその画像にアルファチャンネルは
            ありません。 しかし新しくレイヤーを追加すれば、 不透明な塗りつぶし
            色で作成された画像であっても自動的にアルファチャンネルがつくられ、
            背景レイヤーを別として新たなレイヤーには全て適用されます。 背景
            レイヤーにも透過効果が欲しいときは、 新しい画像の作成の際に塗り
            つぶし色に透明を選ぶか、 既にある画像の背景レイヤーに対し
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-add">アルファチャンネルを追加
            </link> します。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            レイヤーは最背面のレイヤーを除きいずれも自動的にアルファチャンネル
            がある状態になりますが、 アルファ値をグレイスケール化して見ることは
            できません。 詳しい説明が用語集の
            <link linkend="glossary-alpha">アルファ</link> の項目にあります。
          </para>
          <formalpara id="alpha-channel-example">
            <title lang="en">Example for Alpha channel</title>
            <title lang="ja">アルファチャンネルの例</title>
            <indexterm lang="en">
              <primary>Alpha Channel</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm lang="ja">
              <primary>アルファチャンネル</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>
              <figure>
                <title lang="en">Alpha channel example: Basic image</title>
                <title lang="ja">アルファチャンネルの例: 基本の画像</title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/glossary/alpha-channel-0.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">
                      This image has three layers painted with pure 100% opaque
                      Red, Green, and Blue. In the Channel Dialog, you can see
                      that an alpha Channel has been added. It is white because
                      the image is not transparent since there is at least one
                      100% opaque layer. The current layer is the red one : since
                      it is painted with pure red, there is no green and no blue
                      and the corresponding channels are black.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="ja">
                      この画像では3層のレイヤーがそれぞれ純赤、 純緑、 純青で
                      100%不透明に塗られている。 チャンネルダイアログではこの
                      画像にアルファチャンネルが加わっていることがわかる。 白く
                      描かれているのは、 100%不透明なレイヤーしかないので画像が
                      全く透過しないためである。 いま赤のレイヤーを活性化
                      している。 純赤で塗られているので緑や青は片鱗もなく、
                      それぞれのチャンネルは黒くなっている。
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
              <figure>
                <title lang="en">
                  Alpha channel example: One transparent layer
                </title>
                <title lang="ja">
                  アルファチャンネルの例: 透過レイヤーが1層
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/glossary/alpha-channel-1.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">
                      The left part of the first layer has been made transparent
                      (Rectangular selection, Edit/Clear). The second layer,
                      green, is visible. The Alpha channel is still white, since
                      there is an opaque layer in this part of the image.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="ja">
                      最前面のレイヤーの左半分が透明になった (矩形選択してから
                      <menuchoice>
                        <shortcut>
                          <keycap>Delete</keycap>
                        </shortcut>
                        <guimenu>編集(<accel>E</accel>)</guimenu>
                        <guimenuitem>消去(<accel>E</accel>)</guimenuitem>
                      </menuchoice>)。
                      第2のレイヤーの緑が透けて見える。 アルファチャンネルが
                      まだ白いままなのは、 画像にはこの区画で不透明なレイヤーが
                      あるためである。
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
              <figure>
                <title lang="en">
                  Alpha channel example: Two transparent layers
                </title>
                <title lang="ja">
                  アルファチャンネルの例: 透過レイヤーが2層
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/glossary/alpha-channel-2.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">
                      The left part of the second layer has been made
                      transparent. The third layer, blue, is visible through the
                      first and second layers. The Alpha channel is still white,
                      since there is an opaque layer in this part of the image.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="ja">
                      第2のレイヤーの左側を透過させた。 第3のレイヤーの青が
                      第1と第2のレイヤーを通して見えている。 アルファチャンネル
                      がいまだ白いのは、 画像にはこの区画で不透明なレイヤーが
                      あるためである。
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
              <figure>
                <title lang="en">
                  Alpha channel example: Three transparent layers
                </title>
                <title lang="ja">
                  アルファチャンネルの例: 透過レイヤーが3層
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/glossary/alpha-channel-3a.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">
                      The left part of the third layer has been made transparent.
                      The Alpha channel is still white and the left part of the
                      layer is white, opaque! The background layer has
                      no Alpha channel. In this case, the Clear command works
                      like the Eraser and uses the Background color of Toolbox.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="ja">
                      第3のレイヤーの左半分を透過させ[ようとし]た。 アルファ
                      チャンネルは白いままで、 このレイヤーの左半分も白く不透明
                      だ。 背景レイヤーにアルファチャンネルがない。
                      つまりこれは、 消去コマンドが消しゴムツールのように動作
                      するため、 ツールボックスの色の区画にある背景色が塗られた
                      ことになる。
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
              <figure>
                <title lang="en">
                  Alpha channel example: Alpha channel added to the Background
                </title>
                <title lang="ja">
                  アルファチャンネルの例: 背景レイヤーにアルファチャンネルを追加
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="PNG"
                      fileref="images/glossary/alpha-channel-3b.png"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <caption>
                    <para lang="en">
                      We used the
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
                        <guimenuitem>Transparency</guimenuitem>
                        <guisubmenu>Add Alpha Channel</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>
                      command, on the Background layer.
                      Now, the left part of the image is fully transparent and
                      has the color of the page the image is lying on. The left
                      part of the Alpha Channel thumbnail is black (transparent)
                      in the Channel Dialog.
                    </para>
                    <para lang="ja">
                      <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>レイヤー(<accel>L</accel>)</guimenu>
                        <guimenuitem>透明部分(<accel>A</accel>)</guimenuitem>
                        <guisubmenu>アルファチャンネルを追加(<accel>H</accel>)</guisubmenu>
                      </menuchoice>
                      コマンドを背景レイヤーに対して使った。 とうとうこの画像の
                      左半分は完全に透過し、 画像が置かれたページの色が
                      出ている。<!-- ?? --> アルファチャンネルの左部分は透明に
                      なり、 チャンネルダイアログ上では黒く表示された。
                    </para>
                  </caption>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Layer type</term>
        <term lang="ja">レイヤーの種類</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Layer</primary>
            <secondary>Type</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>レイヤー</primary>
            <secondary>種類</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            The layer type is determined by the image type (see previous
            section) and the presence or absence of an alpha channel. These
            are the possible layer types:
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>RGB</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>RGBA</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">Gray</para>
              <para lang="ja">グレイスケール</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">GrayA</para>
              <para lang="ja">アルファつきグレイスケール</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">Indexed</para>
              <para lang="ja">インデックス化カラー</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">IndexedA</para>
              <para lang="ja">アルファつきインデックス化カラー</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para lang="en">
            The main reason this matters is that most filters (in the
            <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
            menu) only accept a subset of layer types, and appear grayed out
            in the menu if the active layer does not have an acceptable type.
            Often you can rectify this either by changing the mode of the
            image or by adding or removing an alpha channel.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            レイヤーの種類を問うものの代表がフィルタ
            (<guimenu>フィルタ<accel>R</accel>)</guimenu> メニューにあります)
            です。 その多くが扱える種類を一部に限定していて、 使えないフィルタ
            はメニュー上で灰色無効になっています。 この問題への対処は、
            画像のモードを変更したりアルファチャンネルを追加もしくは削除すると
            できます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/dialogs/stock-eye-20.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          <phrase lang="en">Visibility</phrase>
          <phrase lang="ja">可視性</phrase>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Visibility</primary>
            <secondary>Icon</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>可視性</primary>
            <secondary>アイコン</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            It is possible to temporarily remove a layer from an image,
            without destroying it, by clicking on the symbol in the Layers
            dialog. This is called <quote>toggling the visibility</quote>
            of the layer. Most operations on an image treat toggled-off layers
            as if they did not exist. When you work with images containing
            many layers, with varying opacity, you often can get a better
            picture of the contents of the layer you want to work on by hiding
            some of the other layers.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            レイヤーを破棄せずに画像から一時的に除外したいとき、 レイヤー
            ダイアログ上で<quote>目</quote>のしるしをクリックします。 これを
            レイヤーの<quote>可視性の切り替え</quote>といいます。 画像に対する
            操作のほとんどは不可視にされたレイヤーをまるで存在しないかのように
            扱います。 不透明度が一様でない複数のレイヤーを有する画像を扱うとき、
            他のレイヤーをいくつか隠せば作業対象のレイヤーの内容がよく見えます。
          </para>
          <tip>
            <para lang="en">
              If you <emphasis>Shift</emphasis>-click on the eye symbol, this
              will cause all layers <emphasis>except</emphasis>
              the one you click on to be hidden.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <keycap>Shift</keycap> キーを押しながら目のしるしをクリックすると
              クリックしたレイヤー <emphasis>以外の</emphasis> 全てのレイヤーが
              不可視になります。 再び同じ操作をすると全てのレイヤーが可視性有りに
              切り替わります。
            </para>
          </tip>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/dialogs/stock-vchain-24.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </guiicon>
          <phrase lang="en">Linkage to other layers</phrase>
          <phrase lang="ja">レイヤーの連結</phrase>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Layer</primary>
            <secondary>Link layers together</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Chain icon</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>レイヤー</primary>
            <secondary>連結</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>鎖アイコン</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            If you click between the eye icon and the layer thumbnail, you get
            a chain icon, which enables you to group layers for operations on
            multiple layers (for example with the Move tool or a transform
            tool).
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            レイヤーの見本と目のしるしの間をクリックすると、 複数のレイヤーを
            纏める鎖のアイコンが表示されます。 こうして連結されたレイヤーは例え
            ば移動ツールをはじめとする変換ツールで一斉に操作できます。 連結は
            <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog-using">パスダイアログ</link> にも
            あって、 連結されたレイヤーとともに操作できます。
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title lang="en">Layer Dialog</title>
            <title lang="ja">レイヤーダイアログ</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/dialogs/link-visibility.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <caption>
                <para lang="en">
                    Red: Linkage to others layers. Green: Visibility.
                  </para>
                <para lang="ja">黄: 可視性。 赤: レイヤー同士の連結。</para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Size and boundaries</term>
        <term lang="ja">大きさと境界線</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Layer</primary>
            <secondary>Size</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Layer</primary>
            <secondary>Boundaries</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            In GIMP, the boundaries of a layer do not necessarily match the
            boundaries of the image that contains it. When you create text,
            for example, each text item goes into its own separate layer, and
            the layer is precisely sized to contain the text and nothing more.
            Also, when you create a new layer using cut-and-paste, the new
            layer is sized just large enough to contain the pasted item. In
            the image window, the boundaries of the currently active layer are
            shown outlined with a black-and-yellow dashed line.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            The main reason why this matters is that you cannot do anything to
            a layer outside of its boundaries: you can't act on what doesn't
            exist. If this causes you problems, you can alter the dimensions
            of the layer using any of several commands that you can find near
            the bottom of the <guimenu>Layer</guimenu> menu.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>ではレイヤーの境界線がその画像の境界線と一致
            する必要がありません。 例えばテキストを置く場合、 それぞれの
            テキストは別個のレイヤーとなって画像に重なり、 その大きさはぴったり
            文字の大きさが収まるだけの幅と高さになります。 また、 切り取って
            貼り付けられた新たなレイヤーは、 貼り付けられた形象が収まるちょうど
            の大きさになります。 画像ウィンドウ上では、 活性レイヤーの境界線は
            黒と黄の点滅破線で縁取られて表示されます。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            この境界線に関して気を付けなければならないことは、 その領域外では
            何も操作できないということです。 何もないところでは作業できません。
            これが問題を引き起こす場合にレイヤーの大きさを変更する手があります。
            <guimenu>レイヤー(<accel>L</accel></guimenu> メニューの下のほうに
            いくつか関係するコマンドがあります。
          </para>
          <note>
            <para lang="en">
              The amount of memory that a layer consumes is determined by its
              dimensions, not its contents. So, if you are working with large
              images or images that contain many layers, it might pay off to
              trim layers to the minimum possible size.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              レイヤーが消費するメモリ量はそこに描かれた内容を問わずただその
              大きさで決まります。 ですから多数のレイヤーを有する画像や巨大な
              画像を扱うときには、 それぞれのレイヤーの大きさをできるだけ小さく
              するとメモリの消費を節約できます。
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Opacity</term>
        <term lang="ja">不透明度</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The opacity of a layer determines the extent to which it lets
            colors from layers beneath it in the stack show through. Opacity
            ranges from 0 to 100, with 0 meaning complete transparency, and
            100 meaning complete opacity.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            レイヤーの不透明度は積み重なったレイヤーを通して下層のレイヤーの色が
            どの程度見えるかを定めます。 不透明度の範囲は 0 から 100 にあり、
            0 は完全透過を、 100 は完全不透明を表します。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Mode</term>
        <term lang="ja">モード</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The Mode of a layer determines how colors from the layer are
            combined with colors from the underlying layers to produce a
            visible result. This is a sufficiently complex, and sufficiently
            important, concept to deserve a section of its own, which follows.
            See <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes"/>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            レイヤーのモードはこのレイヤーの色が背面側のレイヤーの色とどのように合成
            され視覚的効果を及ぼすかを定めます。 とても複雑ですがとても重要です
            ので、 その件だけの節を設けるのに十分な内容があります。 次節
            <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes"/> をお読みください。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Layer mask</term>
        <term lang="ja">レイヤーマスク</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Masks</primary>
            <secondary>Layer mask</secondary>
            <tertiary>Overview</tertiary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>マスク</primary>
            <secondary>レイヤーマスク</secondary>
            <tertiary>あらまし</tertiary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            In addition to the alpha channel, there is another way to control
            the transparency of a layer: by adding a
            <emphasis>layer mask</emphasis>,
            which is an extra grayscale drawable associated with the layer.
            A layer does not have a layer mask by default: it must be added
            specifically. Layer masks, and how to work with them, are
            described much more extensively in the
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask">Layer Mask</link> section.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            アルファチャンネルとは別に、 レイヤーに透過効果をかけるもう一つの
            方法があります。 <emphasis>レイヤーマスク</emphasis> はレイヤーに
            追加するとそのレイヤーに対してグレイスケールの描画対象が付加
            されます。 レイヤーは作られた当初はレイヤーマスクがありませんので、
            必要なときに追加することになります。
            レイヤーマスクとその操作方法については
            <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask">レイヤーマスク</link>
            でさらに踏み込んで説明しています。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en"><quote>Lock alpha channel</quote> setting</term>
        <term lang="ja"><quote>アルファチャンネルをロック</quote></term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            In the upper left corner of the Layers dialog appears a small
            checkbox that controls the <quote>Lock</quote>
            setting for the transparency of the layer (see the figure below).
            If this is checked, then the alpha channel for the layer is
            locked, and no manipulation has any effect on it. In particular,
            nothing that you do to a transparent part of the layer will have
            any effect.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            レイヤーダイアログの左上隅に小さなチェックボックスがあって、
            各レイヤーの透過部分に対し<quote>透明保護</quote>できるように
            なっています (下図参照)。 ここにチェックを入れるとそのレイヤーの
            アルファチャンネルは保護され、 それに対するどんな操作も受けつけ
            なくなります。とりわけレイヤーの透過部分に対して行なった操作は
            何の効果もありません。
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title lang="en">Lock Alpha channel</title>
            <title lang="ja">アルファチャンネルをロック</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/dialogs/ja/lock-alpha.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
