<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
     2009-03-16 j.h: reviewed for v2.6
     2008-04-07 JPL reviewed fr
     2008-02-13 j.h: added tip
     2008-01-26  PP updating to v2.4
     2007-10-07 lexa: reviewed de for GIMP 2.4
     2007-06-18 kost: added norwegian
     2007-02-10 lexA: fixed bug #396404 for en and de
     2006-06-04 changed first para, added para in anti-erase, en;fr by j.h
     2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
     2005-12-01 informalfigure replaced by figure by lexa
     050521 de reviewed by axel.wernicke
-->
<!--2009-04-27-->
<sect2 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-tool-eraser">
  <title lang="en">Eraser</title>
  <title lang="ja">消しゴム</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Eraser</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Eraser</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Transparency</primary>
    <secondary>Eraser tool</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ツール</primary>
    <secondary sortas="ケシゴム">消しゴム</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="ケシゴム">消しゴム</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="トウカコウカ">透過効果</primary>
    <secondary sortas="ケシゴムツール">消しゴムツール</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Eraser tool icon in the Toolbox</title>
    <title lang="ja">
        ツールボックス上の<quote>消しゴム</quote>ツールアイコン
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/toolbox/ja/toolbox-eraser.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Eraser is used to remove areas of color from the current layer or from
    a selection of this layer. If the Eraser is used on something that does
    not support transparency (a selection mask channel, a layer mask, or the
    Background layer if it lacks an alpha channel), then erasing will show the
    background color, as displayed in the Color Area of the Toolbox (in case
    of a mask, the selection will be modified). Otherwise, erasing will
    produce either partial or full transparency, depending on the settings for
    the tool options. You can learn more on how to add an alpha channel to a
    layer in <xref linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-add"/>.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    消しゴムツールは現在の活性レイヤーから部分的に色を取り除いたり、 そのレイヤーの
    選択範囲から色を消したりするためのものです。 透過効果のないもの (選択マスク
    チャンネルやレイヤーマスク、 あるいはアルファチャンネルのない背景レイヤー) に
    対して消しゴムをかけると、 そこには背景色 (ツールボックスの色領域で表示
    されています) が甦ります。 マスクの場合は選択領域が変更されます。 透過効果
    ありの場合は、 ツールオプションの設定によって不完全もしくは完全な透過の
    いずれかが起こります。 レイヤーにアルファチャンネルを追加する方法については
    <xref linkend="gimp-layer-alpha-add"/> で具体的に述べています。
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Eraser and Alpha channel</title>
    <title lang="ja">消しゴムとアルファチャンネル</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/eraser-ex1.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          The Background Color is White. The image has no Alpha channel. The
          Eraser (Opacity 100%) shows the BG color.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          背景色は白。 画像にアルファチャンネルはない。 消しゴム (不透明度100%)
          でなぞると背景色が現れる。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/eraser-ex2.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          The image has an Alpha channel. The Eraser shows transparency.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像にはアルファチャンネルがある。 消しゴムでなぞると透過する。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    If you need to erase some group of pixels completely, leaving no trace
    behind of their previous contents, you should check the "Hard edge" box in
    the Tool Options. Otherwise, sub-pixel brush placement will cause partial
    erasure at the edges of the brush-stroke, even if you use a hard-edged
    brush.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    画像の一部分のいくつかのまとまった画素 (ピクセル) だけ、 今までそこにあった
    痕跡を残さず完全に消したいときは、 ツールオプションで <guilabel>
    ハードエッジ</guilabel> (強い輪郭) にチェックを入れます。 これを忘れると、
    たとえブラシがハードエッジだったとしても副画素的に (サブピクセル) ブラシが
    入ってしまい描線の縁で不完全消去をひきおこしてしまいます。
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para lang="en">
      If you use GIMP with a tablet, you may find it convenient to treat the
      reverse end of the stylus as an eraser. To make this work, all you need
      to do is click the reverse end on the Eraser tool in the Toolbox.
      Because each end of the stylus is treated as a separate input device,
      and each input device has its own separate tool assignment, the reverse
      end will then continue to function as an Eraser as long as you don't
      select a different tool with it.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      タブレットを使われる方は、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>でも尖筆の逆端部に
      ついている消しゴムが使えれば便利だと思われることでしょう。 設定方法は、
      ツールボックスの消しゴムアイコンを尖筆の逆端部でクリックするだけです。
      尖筆の両端はそれぞれ別の入力デバイスとして扱われているので、 それぞれの
      入力デバイスに別々のツールを関連づけることができますから、 あとで
      消しゴム以外のツールと結びつけない限りはずっと消しゴムの機能が使えます。
    </para>
  </tip>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">How to Activate</title>
    <title lang="ja">呼び出し方</title>
    <para lang="en">You can activate the Eraser tool in several ways :</para>
    <para lang="ja">消しゴムツールを起用する方法はつぎのいずれかです:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          From the image menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Paint Tools</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Eraser</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>;
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像ウィンドウのメニューより
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>ツール(<accel>T</accel>)</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>描画ツール(<accel>P</accel>)</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>消しゴム(<accel>E</accel>)</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          from the Toolbox by clicking on the tool icon
          <guiicon><inlinegraphic
            fileref="images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png"/>
          </guiicon>;
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          ツールボックスのツールアイコン
          <guiicon><inlinegraphic
            fileref="images/toolbox/stock-tool-eraser-22.png"/>
          </guiicon>;
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          or from the keyboard using the shortcut
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          キーボードショートカット
          <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Key modifiers</title>
    <title lang="ja">キー修飾</title>
    <para lang="en">
      See the <xref linkend="gimp-tool-brush"/> for a description of key
      modifiers that have the same effect on all brush tools.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ブラシツールに共通する修飾キーについては
      <xref linkend="gimp-tool-brush"/> をご覧ください。
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            For the Eraser, holding down the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key puts it
            into <quote>color picker</quote> mode, so that it selects the
            color of any pixel it is clicked on. Unlike other brush tools,
            however, the Eraser sets the <emphasis>background</emphasis>
            color rather than the foreground color. This is more useful,
            because on drawables that don't support transparency, erasing
            replaces the erased areas with the current background color.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            消しゴムツールは <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> キーを押している間は
            <quote>スポイト</quote>ツールに変身しますので、 クリックした場所の
            画素の色が取り込まれます。 ただし他のブラシツールが描画色と
            するのに対し、 消しゴムの場合は <emphasis>背景色</emphasis> として
            取り込みます。 透過しない描画対象に対し消しゴムをかけると
            その領域には背景色が塗られるため、 この方が都合がよいのです。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycap>Alt</keycap>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            For the Eraser, holding down the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key switches
            it into <quote>anti-erase</quote> mode, as described below in the
            Tool Options section. Note that on some systems, the
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> key is trapped by the Window Manager. If this
            happens to you, you may be able to use
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
            instead.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            消しゴムツールは <keycap>Alt</keycap> キーを押している間は
            <quote>逆消ゴム</quote>モードになります。 逆消しゴムについては
            ツールオプションの節で説明があります。 システムによっては
            <keycap>Alt</keycap> キーがウィンドウマネージャに奪われることが
            あります。 この場合はかわりに
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
            の組み合わせを使ってみてください。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Tool Options</title>
    <title lang="ja">ツールオプション</title>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Tool Options for the Eraser tool</title>
      <title lang="ja">
          <quote>消しゴム</quote>ツールのツールオプション
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/ja/tool-options-eraser.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <xi:include href="about-common-options-display.xml"/>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">
          Mode; Opacity; Brush; Scale; Brush Dynamics; Fade Out; Apply
          Jitter; Incremental
        </term>
        <term lang="ja">
          モード; 不透明度; ブラシ; 拡大・縮小; ブラシ感度の調整;
          フェードアウト; 揺らぎ; 重ね塗り
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <xi:include href="about-common-brush-options.xml"/>
          <!--<para lang="ja">
            ブラシツール共通もしくは広く通用しているオプションです。
          </para>-->
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Opacity</term>
        <term lang="ja">不透明度</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The <guilabel>Opacity</guilabel> slider, in spite of its name,
            determines the <quote>strength</quote> of the tool. Thus, when
            you erase on a layer with an alpha channel, the higher the
            opacity you use, the more transparency you get!
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このツールでの <guilabel>不透明度</guilabel> スライダは、
            名前とは裏腹にツールの<quote>強度</quote>を示しています。
            つまりアルファチャンネルのあるレイヤーに消しゴムをかけると、
            不透明度を高く設定すればするほど透明度が増すことになります。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Hard Edge</term>
        <term lang="ja">ハードエッジ</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This option avoids partial erasure at the edges of the
            brush-stroke. See above.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このオプションは描線の縁が不完全消去されるのを防ぎます。 上記参照。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Anti Erase</term>
        <term lang="ja">逆消ゴム</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The Anti Erase option of the Erase tool can un-erase areas of an
            image, even if they are completely transparent. This feature only
            works when used on layers with an alpha channel. In addition to
            the check-button in the Tool Options, it can also be activated
            on-the-fly by holding down the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key (or, if
            the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key is trapped by the Window Manager, by
            holding down
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>).
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            逆消ゴムオプションは消しゴムツールで画像を部分的に反消去するための
            もので、 完全透過な領域にも作用します。 この機能は
            アルファチャンネルのあるレイヤーにのみ作用します。 ツールオプション上
            のチェックボタンに加え、 作業中には <keycap>Alt</keycap> キーを
            使ってもこのオプションを起用できます (もしも <keycap>Alt</keycap>
            キーがウィンドウマネージャに囚われるのでしたら、
            <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>
            を使ってください)。
          </para>
          <note>
            <para lang="en">
              To understand how anti-erasing is possible, you should realize
              that erasing (or cutting, for that matter) only affects the
              alpha channel, not the RGB channels that contain the image data.
              Even if the result is completely transparent, the RGB data is
              still there, you simply can't see it. Anti-erasing increases the
              alpha value so that you can see the RGB data once again.
            </para>
            <para lang="en">
              An annoying feature: on a layer you have created with a
              transparent background, using anti-erasing on non-painted areas
              paints with black!
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              逆消ゴムがいかにして効くのかを知るには、 消去の作用 (もしくは
              同じ意味での切り取り) が、 画像を含む <acronym>RGB</acronym>
              チャンネルのいずれでもなくアルファチャンネルにのみはたらくことを
              理解せねばなりません。 たとえ結果的に全く透明になってしまっても、
              単に見えなくなっただけで、 <acronym>RGB</acronym>データは依然と
              して残っています。 逆消ゴムの作用はアルファ値を増やすものなので、
              <acronym>RGB</acronym>データは[見ようと思えば]再び見られます。
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              困った機能: 背景色を透明にしたレイヤー上で逆消ゴムをかけると、
              何も描かれていない領域では黒く着色されてしまいます。
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <tip id="change-selection-shape">
      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Selection</primary>
        <secondary>Change shape</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="ja">
        <primary sortas="センタクハンイ">選択範囲</primary>
        <secondary sortas="ケイジョウヘンコウ">形状変更</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para lang="en">
        You can use the Eraser tool to change the shape of a floating
        selection. By erasing, you can trim the edges of the selection.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        消しゴムツールはフローティング選択範囲の形状を変更するのにも使えます。
        選択範囲の輪郭を消して刈り込むのです。
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
