<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-08-20 AntI: added 'es'
  2007-04-15 KoSt: added 'no'
  2007-02-10 lexa: translated new section to de
  2007-01-24 translated new sect3 to it by alessandro falappa
  2006-12-17 Added a sect3 to explain Unsharp Mask by j.h
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  050901 de added by axel.wernicke
  050716 en added sect "more information"
-->
<!--2012-06-15-->
<sect2 id="plug-in-unsharp-mask">
  <title lang="en">Unsharp Mask</title>
  <title lang="ja">アンシャープマスク...</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Filters</primary>
    <secondary>Enhance</secondary>
    <tertiary>Unsharp Mask</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Unsharp Mask</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>フィルター</primary>
    <secondary sortas="キョウチョウ">強調</secondary>
    <tertiary>アンシャープマスク</tertiary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>アンシャープマスク</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Overview</title>
    <title lang="ja">概観</title>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Applying example for the Unsharp Mask filter</title>
      <title lang="ja">アンシャープマスクの適用例</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/taj_orig.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">元画像</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="JPG"
            fileref="images/filters/examples/enhance-taj-unsharp-mask.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">Filter <quote>Unsharp mask</quote> applied</para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <quote>アンシャープマスク</quote>フィルター適用後
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para lang="en">
      Out-of-focus photographs and most digitized images often need a
      sharpness correction. This is due to the digitizing process that must
      chop a color continuum up in points with slightly different colors:
      elements thinner than sampling frequency will be averaged into an
      uniform color. So sharp borders are rendered a little blurred. The same
      phenomenon appears when printing color dots on paper.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The Unsharp Mask filter (what an odd name!) sharpens edges of the
      elements without increasing noise or blemish. It is the king of the
      sharpen filters.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ピントのぼけた写真やディジタル化したほとんどの写真はしばしば明晰化の修正が
      必要になります。 これはディジタル化処理の過程で抽出用振幅よりも細かく
      描かれた物体の色を平均化し単色に変えてしまう癖があり、 元は少し違う色の
      混じった点の集まりだった部分が単色の塊にまとめられてしまうからです。 
      そのため輪郭が僅かにぼやけて描画されるのです。 同様の現象は色のドットで
      紙に印刷するときにも発生します。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <guimenuitem>アンシャープマスク...</guimenuitem> (直訳
      は非明晰化マスクですからまぎらわしいですね) は物体の輪郭を明晰化します。 
      ノイズや汚れが増えることはありません。 シャープ化フィルターの王者です。
    </para>
    <tip>
      <para lang="en">
        Some imaging devices like digital cameras or scanners offer to sharpen
        the created images for you. We strongly recommend you disable the
        sharpening in this devices and use the GIMP filters instead. This way
        you regain the full control over the sharpening of your images.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        ディジタルカメラやスキャナーのような画像化デバイスには取り込んだ画像を
        シャープ化する機能が付いているものがあります。 でもデバイス付属のこの
        ようなシャープ化機能のスイッチは切っておき、 代わりに
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> のフィルターを利用されることを強く
        お勧めします。 そうすれば
        あなたの手で画像の明晰化処理にかかる全面的な制御が可能になるからです。
      </para>
    </tip>
    <para lang="en">
      To prevent color distortion while sharpening, Decompose your image to
      HSV and work only on Value. Then Compose the image to HSV. Go to
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Components</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Decompose...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      Make sure the <guilabel>Decompose to Layers</guilabel>
      box is checked. Choose HSV and click OK. You will get a new grey-level
      image with three layers, one for Hue, one for Saturation, and one for
      Value. (Close the original image so you won't get confused). Select
      the Value layer and apply your sharpening to it. When you are done,
      with that same layer selected, reverse the process. Go to
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Colors</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Components</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Compose...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Again choose HSV and click OK. You will get back your original image
      except that it will have been sharpened in the Value component.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      シャープ化の際に色の歪みが起こるのを防ぐため、 画像を
      <acronym>HSV</acronym> にチャンネル分解して明度 V チャンネル上にだけ
      フィルターをかけるとよいでしょう。 そのあとまた <acronym>HSV</acronym>
      画像に合成するのです。 まずは画像ウィンドウのメニューより 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>色</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>色要素</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>チャンネル分解...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      コマンドでダイアログを開きます。 必ず 
      <guilabel>分解したチャンネルをレイヤーに展開</guilabel> に
      チェックを入れてください。 <guilabel>取り出すチャンネル</guilabel> に
      <acronym>HSV</acronym> を選択して <guibutton>OK</guibutton> をクリック
      します。 これで 3 層の灰色濃淡で描かれたレイヤーからなる画像が
      生成されます。 レイヤーはそれぞれ色相、 彩度、 明度を表しています。 
      (混乱しないために元画像は閉じておきましょう。) 明度レイヤーを選択したら
      ここでシャープ化フィルターを適用します。 そのあとは同じレイヤーを
      選んでから処理を逆に辿ります。 画像ウィンドウのメニューより 
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>色</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>色要素</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>チャンネル合成...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      と進み、 再び <acronym>HSV</acronym> を選択してから 
      <guibutton>OK</guibutton> ボタンをクリックします。 これで
      元の画像から明度の要素でシャープ化されたものが手に入ります。
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Activating the filter</title>
    <title lang="ja">フィルターの呼び出し方</title>
    <para lang="en">
      You can find this filter through
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Enhance</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Unsharp Mask</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      画像ウィンドウのメニューより
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>フィルター</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>強調</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>アンシャープマスク...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="ja">オプション</title>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en"><quote>Unsharp Mask</quote> filter options</title>
      <title lang="ja">
        <quote>アンシャープマスク</quote>フィルターのオプション
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/filters/enhance/unsharp-mask.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Preview</term>
        <term lang="ja">プレビュー</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Parameter setting results are interactively displayed in preview.
            Scroll bars allow you to move around the image.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <guilabel>プレビュー</guilabel> オプションを有効
            にしておれば画像に実際にフィルターをかける前からダイアログ上で調節
            したとおりに即座に効果のようすが見て判るようになっています。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Radius</term>
        <term lang="ja">半径</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            The slider and input boxes (0.1-120) allow you to set how many
            pixels on either side of an edge will be affected by sharpening.
            High resolution images allow higher radius. It is better to always
            sharpen an image at its final resolution.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            スライダーや数値記入欄で、 シャープ化される輪郭周辺の画素数を決める
            ことになる値を 0.1 から 120.0 の範囲で設定します。 高解像度の画像
            なら半径に大きな値がとれます。 画像のシャープ化はいつもその最終
            解像度で行なう方が良いでしょう。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Amount</term>
        <term lang="ja">量</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This slider and input boxes (0.00-5.00) allow you to set
            strength of sharpening.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このスライダーや数値記入欄でシャープ化の強度が設定できます。 値の
            範囲は 0.00 から 5.00 です。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Threshold</term>
        <term lang="ja">しきい値</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This slider and input boxes (0-255) allow you to set the minimum
            difference in pixel values that indicates an edge where sharpen
            must be applied. So you can protect areas of smooth tonal
            transition from sharpening, and avoid creation of blemishes in
            face, sky or water surface.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このスライダーや数値記入欄で、 輪郭がシャープ化を受けるかどうかを
            示す画素の値の最小差異を設定できます。 値の範囲は 0 から 255 です。 
            これを用いてシャープ化を受けたくない滑らかな色変化の部分を守れます
            ので、 天空や水面のような被写体に汚点を作らずに済みます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">How does an unsharp mask work?</title>
    <title lang="ja">アンシャープマスクが効くわけ</title>
    <para lang="en">
      Using an unsharp mask to sharpen an image can seem rather weird. Here is
      the explanation:
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Think of an image with a contrast in some place. The intensity curve of
      the pixels on a line going through this contrast will show an abrupt
      increase of intensity: like a stair if contrast is perfectly sharp, like
      an S if there is some blur.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      アンシャープマスクを用いて画像をシャープ化するというのも何だかおかしな
      話です。 説明しましょう。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      コントラストがひとつある画像について考えます。 コントラストがある線上の
      画素の強度曲線は急激な変化を見せます。 コントラストが完璧に鋭ければ階段状
      に、 ぼかしが入れば S 字を描きます。
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/unsharp-mask-1.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para lang="en">
      Now, we have an image with some blur we want to sharpen (black curve).
      We apply some more blur: the intensity variation will be more gradual
      (green curve).
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Let us subtract the blurredness intensity from the intensity of the
      image. We get the red curve, which is more abrupt : contrast and
      sharpness are increased. QED.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      さてここにぼやけた画像があり、 これをシャープ化 (黒で示したグラフの
      ように) したいと考えているとします。 この画像にさらにぼかしをかけます。
      強度の変化が (緑の曲線のように) もっとなだらかになるでしょう。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ぼかしが現れている強度をこの画像の強度から除算しましょう。 その結果赤い
      曲線ができました。 険しさが増していますから、 コントラストや明晰さが
      増しました。 証明完了。
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/unsharp-mask-2.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para lang="en">
      Unsharp mask has first been used in silver photography. The photograph
      first creates a copy of the original negative by contact, on a film,
      placing a thin glass plate between both; that will produce a blurred
      copy because of light diffusion. Then he places both films, exactly
      corresponding, in a photo enlarger, to reproduce them on paper. The dark
      areas of the positive blurred film, opposed to the clear areas of the
      original negative will prevent light to go through and so will be
      subtracted from the light going through the original film.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      アンシャープマスクは銀塩写真で使われたのが最初です。 この写真ははじめに、
      元のネガフィルムと[ポジ]フィルムの間に薄いガラス板をはさみ貼り合わせて
      画像を写しとります。 この方法は光の拡散が起こるためぼやけた複写が
      できます。 そのつぎに紙に印画するためその対になった両方のフィルムを
      写真引き伸ばし装置に置きます。 元のネガフィルムのクリアな部分を通る光は
      対照的なぼやけたポジフィルムの暗い部分で通過が遮られることから、 元の
      フィルムを通る光からの減算となるのです。
    </para>

    <procedure>
      <para lang="en">
        In digital photography, with GIMP, you will go through the following
        steps:
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        ディジタル化写真では <acronym>GIMP</acronym> だとつぎのような工程を
        経ます。
      </para>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Open your image and duplicate it
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Image</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Duplicate</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像を開いたら複製をとります。 
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>画像</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>複製</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          In the copy, duplicate the layer
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Duplicate layer</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>, then drop the Filters menu down and apply
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Blur</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Gaussian Blur</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          to the duplicated layer with the default IIR option and radius 5.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          複製側でレイヤーのコピーをとります。
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>レイヤー</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>レイヤーの複製</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          つぎに
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>フィルター</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>ぼかし</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>ガウスぼかし...</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          を初期設定の <acronym>IIR</acronym> オプションと
          半径が 5 の設定でコピーのレイヤーにかけます。
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          In the layer dialog of the duplicated image, change Mode to
          <quote>Subtract</quote>, and in the right-clic menu, select
          <quote>Merge down</quote>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          複製側の画像においてレイヤーダイアログでぼかしのかかったレイヤーの
          モードを <guimenuitem>減算</guimenuitem> に設定し、 下のレイヤーと
          統合させます。
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Click and drag the only layer you got into the original image, where
          it appears as a new layer.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          こうしてできたレイヤーをレイヤーダイアログでクリックして元の画像の
          ウィンドウ上まで曳いて放つと、 新しいレイヤーになります。
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para lang="en">
          Change the Mode in this layer dialog to <quote>Addition</quote>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          この新たなレイヤーのモードをレイヤーダイアログで 
          <guimenuitem>加算</guimenuitem> に設定します。
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <para lang="en">
      Voilà. The <quote>Unsharp Mask</quote> plug-in does the same for you.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      At the beginning of the curve, you can see a dip. If blurring is
      important, this dip is very deep; the result of the subtraction can be
      negative, and a complementary color stripe will appear along the
      contrast, or a black halo around a star on the light background of a
      nebula (black eye effect).
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ほらこのとおり、 <quote>アンシャープマスク</quote>プラグインと同じ処理の
      できあがりです。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      グラフ上で曲線のはじまりがくぼんでいますね。 ぼかし処理が重くなると、 
      このくぼみがとても深くなります。 結果的に減算が負の値を生み、 
      コントラストのある部分に沿って補色のすじができたり、 明るめの星雲を背景に
      見える星のまわりに黒い暈 (ハロー) ができるのです (黒目効果)。
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Black eye effect</title>
      <title lang="ja">黒目効果</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/filters/examples/unsharp-mask-3.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
