<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossary PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--2009-05-06-->
<glossary id="glossary">
  <title lang="en">Glossary</title>
  <title lang="ja">用語集</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Glossary</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>用語集</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <glossentry id="glossary-alpha">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Alpha</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">アルファ</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Alpha</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>アルファ</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        An Alpha value indicates the transparency of a pixel. Besides its
        Red, Green and Blue values, a pixel has an alpha value. The smaller
        the alpha value of a pixel, the more visible the colors below it. A
        pixel with an alpha value of 0 is completely transparent. A pixel
        with an alpha value of 255 is fully opaque.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        There is no grayscale representation of the alpha of a layer. The
        Alpha Channel you can see in the Channel Dialog is that of the
        whole composite image. If a pixel is opaque only in a layer and
        transparent in all other layers, it will be white in the Alpha
        Channel.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        With some image
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file formats</link>,
        you can only specify that a pixel is completely transparent or
        completely opaque. Other file formats allow a variable level of
        transparency.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
アルファ値は画素の透明度を示します。 赤、 緑、 青の各値とは別に画素には
アルファ値があります。 アルファ値が低くなるにつれその画素の色の可視度が
強くなります。 アルファ値が 0 の画素は完全透過します。 アルファ値が 
255 の画素は完全不透明です。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
アルファだけをレイヤーごとにグレースケールとして表示するしくみは
ありません。 チャンネルダイアログで見られるアルファチャンネルは[可視
レイヤー]全部を合成した画像です。 仮にどこかの画素で1層のレイヤーだけが
完全不透明で他のレイヤーは皆透明だったとすると、 アルファチャンネルは
白で表わされます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
いくつかの画像用 
<link linkend="glossary-fileformat">ファイル形式</link> は画素の透明度
を表すのに完全透過か完全不透明のどちらかしか選べないものがあります。 
それ以外のファイル形式では透明度が何段階にも表せます。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-alpha-channel">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Alpha Channel</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">アルファチャンネル</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
        <primary>Transparency</primary>
        <secondary>Alpha channel</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
        <primary>Alpha Channel</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
        <primary sortas="トウカコウカ">透過効果</primary>
        <secondary>アルファチャンネル</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
        <primary>アルファチャンネル</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para lang="en">
        An Alpha Channel represents the transparency of the image. Imagine
        you can see through the image. This Alpha Channel is automatically
        added to the image as soon as you add a second layer. You can see it
        in the Channels Dialog. It gives the possibility to be transparent to
        layers. But this possibility is not given to the background layer :
        for this, you must use the <quote>Add an Alpha Channel</quote>
        command.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        You can also consider that an Alpha channel, although not visible, is
        added to every layer, except to the background layer. The image
        Alpha channel is the sum of the Alpha channels of layers.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        See also <link linkend="alpha-channel-example">Alpha channel example
        </link>. <!--In concepts/layers.xml-->
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
アルファチャンネルは画像の透明度を表します。 透けて見える画像を思い浮か
べていただければ十分です。 アルファテャンネルは画像に2枚目のレイヤーを
追加すると自動的に追加されます。 チャンネルダイアログでそれが分かり
ます。 これでレイヤーが透過もできるようになります。 しかし背景レイヤー
にだけはこの能力が自動付加されません。 可能にするには<quote>
アルファチャンネルを追加</quote>コマンドを実行しなければなりません。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
アルファチャンネルは目に見えませんが背景レイヤーを除く全てのレイヤーに
付加されています。 アルファチャンネルを可視化しているものがチャンネル
ダイアログにありますが、 これは全てのレイヤーのアルファ値を合成して
表示しています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<link linkend="alpha-channel-example">アルファチャンネルの例</link> 
もご覧ください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-antialiasing">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Antialiasing</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">アンチエイリアス</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Antialiasing</primary>
      <secondary>Explanation</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>アンチエイリアス</primary>
      <secondary sortas="セツメイ">説明</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Antialiasing is the process of reversing an alias, that is,
        reducing the <quote>jaggies</quote>. Antialiasing
        produces smoother curves by adjusting the boundary between the
        background and the pixel region that is being antialiased. Generally,
        pixel intensities or opacities are changed so that a smoother
        transition to the background is achieved. With selections, the
        opacity of the edge of the selection is appropriately reduced.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
アンチエイリアス化とは近似 (エイリアス) されたところを元に戻す工程を
指しており、 つまりは<quote>ギザギザ現象</quote>を減らすしくみと
いえます。 アンチエイリアスが掛けられた領域の画素と背景との境目は、 
滑らかな曲線になるよう調整されます。 一般的には画素の発色や不透明度に
変化をつけることによって背景と滑らかにつながったように見せています。 
選択をとると、 選択範囲の境界線付近では選択の強度が適切に弱められます。
      </para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/glossary/alias.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/glossary/antialias.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-bezier-curve">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Bezier curve</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">ベジエ曲線</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A spline is a curve which is defined mathematically and has a set
        of control points. A Bezier spline is a cubic spline which has
        four control points, where the first and last control points
        (knots or anchors) are the endpoints of the curve and the inner
        two control points (handles) determine the direction of the curve
        at the endpoints.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In the non-mathematical sense, a spline is a flexible strip of
        wood or metal used for drawing curves. Using this type of spline
        for drawing curves dates back to shipbuilding, where weights were
        hung on splines to bend them. The outer control points of a
        Bezier spline are similar to the places where the splines are
        fastened down and the inner control points are where weights are
        attached to modify the curve.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Bezier splines are only one way of mathematically representing
        curves. They were developed in the 1960s by Pierre Bezier, who
        worked for Renault.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Bezier curves are used in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> as component
        parts of <link linkend="glossary-path">Paths</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
スプラインとは数式により定義された曲線のことで、 なおかつコントロール
ポイントが数カ所ついています。 ベジエスプラインは4つのコントロール
ポイントからなる立方スプラインであり、 始めと終わりのコントロール
ポイント (ノットとかアンカーともいいます) が曲線の終端になっており、 
内側にある2つのコントロールポイント (ハンドルともいいます) が終端から
発する曲線の方向を決めています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
数式とは別の観点から言えば、 曲線を形作る金属製もしくは木製のしなやかな
部材がスプラインです。 この種類のスプラインによって曲線を描くさまは、 
かつての造船の時代を思い起こさせます。 当時はスプラインを曲げるために
おもりがつり下げられていました。 ベジエスプラインの端点のコントロール
ポイントはスプラインに縄を括り付けて引く位置に似ており、 内側にある2つ
のコントロールポイントは曲線を調整するためのおもりにあたります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
ベジエスプラインは曲線を数式で表現する唯一の方法です。 この技法はルノー
社で働いていた技術者 Pierre Bézier 氏が1960年代に考案しました。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>はベジエ曲線を 
<link linkend="glossary-path">パス</link> 成分を描くのに用いています。
      </para>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/glossary/bezier-curve.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The image above shows a Bezier curve. Points P0 and P3 are points
        on the Path, which are created by clicking with the mouse. Points
        P1 and P2 are handles, which are automatically created by
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> when you click on the line between P0 and
        P3 and stretch it. They change position when you stretch the
        curve in different ways.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
上図はベジエ曲線を描く様子を示しています。 点 P0 と P3 はパス上にあり、 
それぞれマウスでクリックして置かれました。 点 P1 と P4 がハンドルで、 
P0 と P3 の間のパス分節をクリックして曳き延ばすと<acronym>GIMP
</acronym>は自動的にこれらを生成します。 この曲線をいろいろな方法を用いて
曳き延ばすとハンドルの位置が変化します。
      </para>
      <para>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/path-with-anchors.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The image above shows a path which consists of two components,
        having both straight and curved segments, being worked on with the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Path tool</link>. Here, the open
        circle indicates the selected anchor and the two open squares are
        the two handles which are associated with this anchor from the
        curves on either side of it.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
上図には2つの成分からなるパスが描かれており、 両方とも直線や曲線の分節
が含まれています。 この作業は
<link linkend="gimp-tool-path">パスツール</link> で行ないました。 
ひとつだけある白丸は選択されたアンカーを表していて、 2つの白い正方形は
そのアンカーから延びる2本の曲線のこの端点でのハンドルを表しています。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-bitmap">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Bitmap</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">ビットマップ</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        From
        <emphasis>
          The Free Online Dictionary of Computing (13 Mar 01)
        </emphasis>:
        <blockquote><para>
            bitmap &mdash; A data file or structure which corresponds bit for
            bit with an image displayed on a screen, probably in the same
            format as it would be stored in the display's video memory or
            maybe as a device independent bitmap. A bitmap is characterised by
            the width and height of the image in pixels and the number of bits
            per pixel which determines the number of shades of grey or colours
            it can represent. A bitmap representing a coloured image (a
            <quote>pixmap</quote>) will usually have pixels with between one
            and eight bits for each of the red, green, and blue components,
            though other colour encodings are also used. The green component
            sometimes has more bits than the other two to cater for the human
            eye's greater discrimination in this component.
          </para></blockquote>
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<ulink url="http://foldoc.org/index.cgi?bitmap">
<citetitle>The Free Online Dictionary of Computing (1996-09-21)
</citetitle></ulink> によると
        <blockquote>
          <para>
bitmap &mdash; 画面上に表示される画像の画素と1対1で対応するデータ
ファイルもしくは構造のことをいい、 ディスプレイ用ビデオメモリ上に
展開される形式とおそらくは同一であり、 機種非依存のビットマップ形式
を指すこともある。 ビットマップの特性は画像の幅と高さの画素数と各
画素のビット深度によって決まる。 画素のビット深度は灰色陰影の階調
あるいは表現可能な色の数を決定づけている。 カラー画像のビットマップ
 (<quote>ピクスマップ</quote>) はふつう赤、 緑、 青の成分それぞれに
1乃至8ビットを割り当てているが、 他の色エンコーディングも利用されて
いる。 ヒトの視力は緑成分に対する識別能力が高いので、 この成分には
しばしば他の2つの成分よりも多くのビットを割り当てることがある。
          </para>
        </blockquote>
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-bmp">
    <glossterm>
      <anchor id="file-bmp-load" xreflabel="BMP"/>
      <anchor id="file-bmp-save" xreflabel="BMP"/>
      <phrase>BMP</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>BMP</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>BMP</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ケイシキ">形式</primary>
      <secondary>BMP</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        BMP is an uncompressed image
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link>
        designed by Microsoft and mainly used in Windows. Colors are
        typically represented in 1, 4 or 8 bits, although the format also
        supports more. Because it is not compressed and the files are large,
        it is not very well suited for use in the internet.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
BMPはマイクロソフト社が発案した非圧縮の画像 
<link linkend="glossary-fileformat">ファイル形式</link> のひとつで、 
主に <productname>Windows</productname> で使われています。 色は主に
1、 4、 8ビットのいずれかで表現されていますが、 このファイル形式
自体はさらに多様な方法が可能です。 非圧縮なためファイルが大きくなって
しまうので、 インターネット上での使用には向いていません。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-bumpmapping">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Bump mapping</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">バンプマッピング</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Bump mapping is a technique for displaying extremely detailed objects
        without increasing the geometrical complexity of the objects. It is
        especially used in 3-dimensional visualization programs. The trick is
        to put all the necessary information into a texture, with which
        shadowing is shown on the surface of the object.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Bump mapping is only one (very effective) way of simulating surface
        irregularities which are not actually contained in the geometry of the
        model.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
バンプマッピングとは幾何学計算をあまり複雑にせずに非常に緻密な物体を
描出する技法です。 3次元の視覚化プログラムでよく使われています。 
この手品は必要な情報の表現を、 物体の表面の質感や陰影を描いておいた
テクスチャに全て委ねています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
バンプマッピングは表面のでこぼこした様子を実際には模型の構造に含めずに
模倣する唯一の (たいへん効果的な) 方法です。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-channelmask">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Channel Mask</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">チャンネルマスク</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A channel masks is a special type of mask which determines the
        transparency of a selection. See <xref linkend="glossary-masks"/> for
        a detailed description.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
チャンネルマスクとは選択範囲の透明度や強度を示せる特別な種類のマスク
です。 詳しい説明は用語集の
<xref linkend="glossary-masks"/> の項をご覧ください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-channels">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Channels</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">チャンネル</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Channel</primary>
      <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>チャンネル</primary>
      <secondary sortas="アラマシ">あらまし</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A Channel is a single component of a pixel's color. For a colored
        pixel in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, these components are usually Red,
        Green, Blue and sometimes transparency (Alpha). For a
        <link linkend="glossary-graylevel">Grayscale</link> image, they are
        Gray and Alpha and for an
        <link linkend="glossary-indexedcolors">Indexed</link> color image,
        they are Indexed and Alpha.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The entire rectangular array of any one of the color components for
        all of the pixels in an image is also referred to as a Channel. You
        can see these color channels with the Channels dialog.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        When the image is displayed, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> puts these
        components together to form the pixel colors for the screen, printer,
        or other output device. Some output devices may use different
        channels from Red, Green and Blue. If they do,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s channels are converted into the
        appropriate ones for the device when the image is displayed.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Channels can be useful when you are working on an image which needs
        adjustment in one particular color. For example, if you want to
        remove <quote>red eye</quote> from a photograph, you might work on
        the Red channel.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        You can look at channels as masks which allow or restrict the output
        of the color that the channel represents. By using Filters on the
        channel information, you can create many varied and subtle effects
        on an image. A simple example of using a Filter on the color
        channels is the
        <link linkend="plug-in-colors-channel-mixer">Channel Mixer</link>
        filter.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In addition to these channels, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> also allows
        you to create other channels (or more correctly, Channel Masks),
        which are displayed in the lower part of the Channels dialog. You
        can convert a selection to a channel mask by using the
        <link linkend="gimp-selection-to-channel">Save to Channel</link>
        command. You can also create a channel by right-clicking in the
        Channels dialog and using the
        <link linkend="gimp-channel-new">New channel</link> command.
        See the glossary entry on
        <link linkend="glossary-masks">Masks</link> for more information about
        Channel Masks.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
チャンネルとは画素の色成分ひとつを示すことばです。 <acronym>GIMP
</acronym>で扱う色つき画素は、 通常は赤、 緑、 青の色成分と、 必須では
ありませんが透過効果 (アルファ) 成分によって構成されます。 
<link linkend="glossary-graylevel">グレースケール</link> 画像は灰色
陰影のチャンネルとアルファチャンネルで、
<link linkend="glossary-indexedcolors">インデックス化</link> カラー画像
はインデックス化カラーマップとアルファチャンネルで構成されています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
いずれかの色成分を画像から抜き出せば、 全ての画素に対する行列式の全体像
もまたチャンネルとして参照できます。 このような色チャンネルのようすは
チャンネルダイアログ上で見られます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
画像を表示するとき、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は色成分を画面やプリンタを
はじめとする出力デバイスに合わせて再編成します。 一部の出力デバイスは
赤緑青とは異なる色チャンネル構成を使用しています。 このようなデバイスに
で画像が表示されるとき、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のチャンネルはそれらに
最適なものに変換されます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
ある特定の画像の色を調節したいとき、 チャンネルを利用すると便利です。 
たとえば写真から<quote>赤目</quote>を除去したいときは、 赤チャンネルで
作業するとよいでしょう。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
チャンネルがもつ色だけに着目できることから、 チャンネルはその色の出力
マスクとしても活用できます。 チャンネルの情報にフィルタをかければ、 
多種多様で繊細な効果を画像にかけられます。 色チャンネルにフィルタを
かける単純な例として
<link linkend="plug-in-colors-channel-mixer">チャンネルミキサー</link>
フィルタがあります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
3つの色チャンネルに加え、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>では他にもチャンネル
 (正確にはチャンネルマスク) を作成できます。 これらはチャンネル
ダイアログの下側に表示されます。 
<link linkend="gimp-selection-to-channel">チャンネルに保存</link> 
コマンドを使えば選択範囲を変換してチャンネルマスクが作成できます。 
チャンネルダイアログの脈絡メニューには新たにチャンネルを作成する 
<link linkend="gimp-channel-new">チャンネルを追加...</link> コマンド
もあります。 より詳しい情報は用語集の 
<xref linkend="glossary-masks"/> の項をご覧ください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-clipboard">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Clipboard</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">クリップボード</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        The Clipboard is a temporary area of memory which is used to
        transfer data between applications or documents. It is used when you
        Cut, Copy or Paste data in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The clipboard is implemented slightly differently under different
        operating systems. Under Linux/XFree, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses
        the XFree clipboard for text and the <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        internal image clipboard for transferring images between image
        documents. Under other operating systems, the clipboard may work
        somewhat differently. See the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> documentation
        for your operating system for further information.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The basic operations provided by the clipboard are
        <quote>Cut</quote>, <quote>Copy</quote>, and <quote>Paste</quote>.
        Cut means that the item is removed from the document and copied to
        the clipboard. Copy leaves the item in the document and copies it to
        the clipboard. Paste copies the contents of the clipboard to the
        document. The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> makes an intelligent decision
        about what to paste depending upon the target. If the target is a
        canvas, the Paste operation uses the image clipboard. If the target
        is a text entry box, the paste operation uses the text clipboard.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
クリップボードとは、 別のアプリケーションや別の文書・作品との間で
データをやりとりするときに使える一時的な記憶領域のことです。 <acronym>
GIMP</acronym>ではデータを<quote>切り取り</quote>、 <quote>写し取り
</quote>、 <quote>貼り付け</quote>するときに利用しています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
クリップボードはオペレーティングシステムが異なると少しずつ実装に違いが
あります。 <productname>Linux</productname> などのUNIX系システムと
<productname>Xorg</productname>の環境では、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は
Xの提供するテキスト用クリップボードを使いますが、 画像作品同士の画像
データのやりとりには<acronym>GIMP</acronym>内部の画像用クリップボード
を使います。 このあたりは他のオペレーティングシステムでのクリップ
ボードのはたらきがいくぶん異なっていることでしょう。 この詳細について
はお使いのオペレーティングシステムに関する<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の
文書を[探して]お読みください。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
クリップボードを使ってできる基本的な操作は<quote>切り取り</quote>、 
<quote>写し取り</quote>、 <quote>貼り付け</quote>です。 切り取りとは
対象を文書や作品から削除し、 その部分の写しをクリップボードに取り込む
ことです。 写し取り (コピー) とは文書や作品にその対象部分を残しつつ
写しをクリップボードに取り込むことです。 貼り付け (ペースト) とは
クリップボードの内容を文書や作品に写し取ることです。 <acronym>GIMP
</acronym>は貼り付け操作のときその対象文書によって扱うものを知能的に
判断します。 対象がキャンバスならば貼り付け操作は画像用クリップボード
を使用します。 対象がテキスト入力欄ならば、 貼り付け操作はテキスト用
クリップボードを使用します。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-cmyk">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>CMY, CMYK</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>CMYK</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Subtractive color synthesis</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="イロ">色</primary>
      <secondary sortas="ゲンポウコンショク">減法混色</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        CMYK is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which has components for Cyan, Magenta, Yellow and Black. It is a
        subtractive color model, and that fact is important when an image
        is printed. It is complementary to the
        <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB</link> color model.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The values of the individual colors vary between 0% and 100%, where 0%
        corresponds to an unprinted color, and 100% corresponds to a
        completely printed area of color. Colors are formed by mixing the
        three basic colors.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The last of these values, K (Black), doesn't contribute to
        the color, but merely serves to darken the other colors.  The
        letter K is used for Black to prevent confusion, since B usually
        stands for Blue.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>CMYK</acronym>はシアン、 マゼンタ、 イエローと黒の成分からなる
<link linkend="glossary-colormodel">色モデル</link> です。 減算色モデル
であることが、 画像を印刷するさいに重要になります。 
<link linkend="glossary-rgb"><acronym>RGB</acronym></link> 色モデルの
補色にあたります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
それぞれの色成分の値は 0% から 100% の範囲を推移します。 0% は印刷にその
色を全く使わないことを示し、 100% はその印刷位置で完全発色させることを
意味します。 どの色も先の3つの基本色の合成より成りたちます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
4つめに挙げた K (黒) の値は色彩表現には使われませんが、 まれに他の色を
暗くするのに使われることがあります。 K の文字は印刷枠を示すキー色に
由来していますが、 青を示す B との混同を避けるためそのまま黒の意味でも
使われています。
      </para>
      <figure float="0">
        <title lang="en">Subtractive color model</title>
        <title lang="ja">減算色モデル</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/glossary/color-model-subtractive.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> does not currently support the CMYK model.
        (An experimental plug-in providing rudimentary CMYK support can be
        found <xref linkend="bibliography-online-plugin-separate"/>.)
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        This is the mode used in printing. These are the colors in the ink
        cartridges in your printer. It is the mode used in painting and in all
        the objects around us, where light is reflected, not emmitted. Objects
        absorb part of the light waves and we see only the reflected part.
        Note that the cones in our eyes see this reflected light in RGB mode.
        An object appears Red because Green and Blue have been absorbed. Since
        the combination of Green and Blue is Cyan, Cyan is absorbed when you
        add Red. Conversely, if you add Cyan, its complementary color, Red, is
        absorbed. This system is <emphasis>subtractive</emphasis>.
        If you add Yellow, you decrease Blue, and if you add Magenta, you
        decrease Green.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        It would be logical to think that by mixing Cyan, Magenta and Yellow,
        you would subtract Red, Green and Blue, and the eye would see no light
        at all, that is, Black. But the question is more complex. In fact, you
        would see a dark brown. That is why this mode also has a Black value,
        and why your printer has a Black cartridge. It is less expensive that
        way. The printer doesn't have to mix the other three colors to create
        an imperfect Black, it just has to add Black.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は現時点で<acronym>CMYK</acronym>色モデルを
サポートしていません。 (<acronym>CMYK</acronym>を基本的にサポートする
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>用実験的プラグインが 
<xref linkend="bibliography-online-plugin-separate"/> にあります。)
<!--Perhaps it has been already included on the official GIMP supplies.-->
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
このモードは印刷に利用されています。 これら4色のインクカートリッジが
お使いのプリンタに入っているはずです。 絵画や、 私たちの身の回りにある
発光物体を除く光を反射するあらゆる物が、 このモードによって発色して
います。 物体は光波を浴びるとその一部だけを吸収し、 私たちはその残りの
反射光だけを見ています。 ちなみにヒトの目の角膜はこの反射光を<acronym>
RGB</acronym>モードで見ています。 赤く見える物体はその物体が緑と青の
光を吸収しているからそう見えるのです。 緑と青を合成色はシアンですが、 
[物体に]赤を加えるとシアンは吸収されます。 逆にシアンを加えると、 その
補色の赤が吸収されます。 このしくみを <emphasis>減法混色</emphasis> 
といいます。 イエローを加えると青が弱まり、 マゼンタを加えると緑が
弱まります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
シアンとマゼンタとイエローの混色は、 論理的に考えると赤、 緑、 青を減法
混色することになりますから、 目に見える光は何も残らなくなり、 つまりは
黒く見えるはずです。 しかし実際の問題はもっと複雑です。 上図では濃い
茶色に見えますでしょう。 そういうわけでこのモードには黒の値が加えられ
ており、 プリンタにも黒のカートリッジが付いているのです。 こうした方が
安価で済みます。 プリンタは[黒く塗るのに]3つの色を混ぜてこのような
不完全な黒を作ることはなく、 黒のインクを使用します。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-colordepth">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Color depth</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">色深度</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Color depth</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="イロシンド">色深度</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>bpp</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Color depth is simply the number of bits used to represent a color
        (bits per pixel : bpp). There are 3 channels for a pixel (for Red,
        Green and Blue). <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can support 8 bits per
        channel, referred as <emphasis>eight-bit color</emphasis>. So,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> color depth is 8&nbsp;*&nbsp;3&nbsp;=&nbsp;24,
        which allows
        256&nbsp;*&nbsp;256&nbsp;*&nbsp;256&nbsp;=&nbsp;16,777,216 possible
        colors (8 bits allow 256 colors).
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
色深度とは簡単に言えば色を表現するのに使われるビット数のことです。 
<foreignphrase>bits per pixel</foreignphrase>(bpp) とも表現されます。 
ひとつの画素に赤緑青の3つのチャンネルがあります。 <acronym>GIMP
</acronym>は1チャンネルあたり8ビットをサポートしており、 <emphasis>
8ビットカラー</emphasis> と呼ばれます。 つまり<acronym>GIMP</acronym>
の色深度は 8&#xd7;3&nbsp;=&nbsp;24 となり、 8ビットで256色できる
ことから、 256&#xd7;256&#xd7;256&nbsp;=&nbsp;1677万7216色が表現可能
となります。 <!--GEGL offers 32bpp.-->
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-colormodel">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Color model</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">色モデル</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Color model</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="イロモデル">色モデル</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        <!-- Reorganised "color models" to be more like de. There's no need
             to repeat the information again.  scb -->
        A color model is a way of describing and specifying a color. The term
        is often used loosely to refer to both a color space system and the
        color space on which it is based.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        A color space is a set of colors which can be displayed or
        recognized by an input or output device (such as a scanner, monitor,
        printer, etc.). The colors of a color space are specified as values
        in a color space system, which is a coordinate system in which the
        individual colors are described by coordinate values on various axes.
        Because of the structure of the human eye, there are three axes in
        color spaces which are intended for human observers. The practical
        application of that is that colors are specified with three
        components (with a few exceptions). There are about 30 to 40 color
        space systems in use. Some important examples are:
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
色モデル (カラーモデル) とは色の記述法ならびに表現法の一種です。 この
用語は色空間の座標系を指す場合とその色空間そのものを指す場合があり、 
しばしば区別が曖昧になっています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
色空間は入力デバイスと出力デバイス (スキャナ、 モニタ、 プリンタなど) 
が認識もしくは描出できる範囲の色のまとまりです。 色空間にある色は色空間
の座標系で数値化できます。 ヒトの目の構造上、 ヒトが認識できる色空間
には3色の基軸があります。 このことから実用的なアプリケーションは色を
3つの成分で表しています (僅かに例外もあります)。 現在利用できる色空間
座標系は30から40種類あります。 重要なものは用語集にあります。
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="glossary-hsv">HSV</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="glossary-cmyk">CMY(K)</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="glossary-yuv">YUV</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="glossary-ycbcr">YCbCr</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-dithering">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Dithering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">ディザリング</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Dithering</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Dithering</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>ディザリング</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="イロ">色</primary>
      <secondary>ディザリング</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Dithering is a technique used in computer graphics to create the
        illusion of more colors when displaying an image which has a low
        <link linkend="glossary-colordepth">color depth</link>. In a
        dithered image, the missing colors are reproduced by a certain
        arrangement of pixels in the available colors. The human eye
        perceives this as a mixture of the individual colors.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The <link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">Gradient</link> tool uses
        dithering. You may also choose to use dithering when you convert an
        image to <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">Indexed</link>
        format. If you are working on an image with indexed colors, some
        tools (such as the pattern fill tool) may also use dithering, if the
        correct color is not available in the colormap.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The <link linkend="plug-in-newsprint">Newsprint</link> filter
        uses dithering as well. You can use the
        <link linkend="plug-in-nlfilt">NL Filter</link> (Non Linear filter)
        to remove unwanted dithering noise from your image.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Also note that although <acronym>GIMP</acronym> itself uses 24-bit
        colors, your system may not actually be able to display that many
        colors. If it doesn't, then the software in between
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> and your system may also dither colors while
        displaying them.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        See also the glossary entry on
        <link linkend="glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering">Floyd-Steinberg
        dithering</link>, which is used in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
ディザリングとはコンピュータグラフィックの技法のひとつで、 少ない
<link linkend="glossary-colordepth">色深度</link> の画像でより多くの
色数を表現できます。 ディザリングを利用した画像では、 本来無い色を再現
するとき、 利用できるいくつかの他の色の画素を一定の規則で配置します。
ヒトの目はそれらの別々の色をひとつの混ざった色として認識します。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">グラデーション</link> ツールは
ディザリングを使用しています。 そのほかにも画像を 
<link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">インデックス化</link> 画像に
変換するときディザリングを利用するオプションがあります。 インデックス化
カラー画像を塗りつぶしツールなどを用いてパターンで埋め尽すとき、 カラー
マップに使いたい色がないときにもディザリングが利用されます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<link linkend="plug-in-newsprint">新聞印刷</link> フィルタもまた
ディザリングを利用しています。 ディザリングで画像にできた乱れは 
<link linkend="plug-in-nlfilt">非線形フィルタ</link> で除去できます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
ちなみに<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は24ビットカラーで動作してはいますが、 
必ずしもお使いのシステムがそんなに多くの色数で表示できているとは限り
ません。 実際に不足している場合は<acronym>GIMP</acronym>と描画システム
との間のソフトウェアがディザリング処理を行なって色を再現します。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
この用語集には<acronym>GIMP</acronym>が利用している
<link linkend="glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering">Floyd-Steinberg
ディザリング</link> の項もあります。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-exif">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>EXIF</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>EXIF</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Exchangeable image file format (official abbreviation Exif, not
        EXIF) is a specification for the image file format used by digital
        cameras. It was created by the Japan Electronic Industry Development
        Association (JEIDA). The specification uses the existing JPEG, TIFF
        Rev. 6.0, and RIFF WAVE file formats, with the addition of specific
        metadata tags. It is not supported in JPEG 2000 or PNG. Version 2.1 of
        the specification is dated June 12, 1998 and version 2.2 is dated
        April 2002. The Exif tag structure is taken from that of TIFF files.
        There is a large overlap between the tags defined in the TIFF, Exif,
        TIFF/EP and DCF standards
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-exif"/>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
Exchangeable image file format (略すとExif、 <acronym>EXIF</acronym>
ではない) はデジタルカメラが利用する画像ファイル形式のための規格です。 
これを規定したのは日本電子工業振興協会 (<acronym>JEIDA</acronym>、 
現在の社団法人電子情報技術産業協会 (<acronym>JEITA</acronym>)) です。 
この規格は現行の<acronym>JPEG</acronym>、 <acronym>TIFF</acronym>改訂第
6.0版、 <acronym>RIFF</acronym> WAVEファイル形式に対しある種のメタ
データタグを埋め込みます。 <acronym>JPEG</acronym> 2000と<acronym>PNG
</acronym>には対応しておりません。 この規格の第2.1版は1998年6月12日に、 
第2.2版は2002年4月に仕様制定されました。 Exifのタグ構造は
<xref linkend="glossary-tiff"/> 形式のタグをもとにしています。 
<acronym>TIFF</acronym>、 Exif、 <acronym>TIFF/EP</acronym>、 <acronym>
DCF</acronym>の各標準規格のタグの間には大きな共通点があります。 
<xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-exif"/> を参考にしてください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-feathering">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Feathering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">フェザリング</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Feathering selection border</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="センタクハンイノキョウカイセンヲボカス">
        選択範囲の境界線をぼかす
      </primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses the process of Feathering to make a
        smooth transition between a region and the background by softly
        blending the edges of the region.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は画像上にある領域と背景との境界部分がなだらかに
変化するようにその境界線を淡柔に背景へ調和させるためにフェザリング処理
を利用しています。
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/glossary/feather.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, you can feather the edges of a
        selection. Brushes can also have feathered edges.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>では選択範囲の境界線をぼかせます。 ブラシの
穂先の縁にもフェザリングがかかっています。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-fileformat">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">File Format</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">ファイル形式</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>File format</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ファイルケイシキ">ファイル形式</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A file format or file type is the form in which computer data is
        stored. Since a file is stored by an operating system as a linear
        series of bytes, which cannot describe many kinds of real data in
        an obvious way, conventions have been developed for interpreting
        the information as representations of complex data. All of the
        conventions for a particular <quote>kind</quote> of file constitute
        a file format.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Some typical file formats for saving images are JPEG, TIFF, PNG and
        GIF. The best file format for saving an image depends upon how the
        image is intended to be used. For example, if the image is intended
        for the internet, file size is a very important factor, and if the
        image is intended to be printed, high resolution and quality have
        greater significance. See
        <link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">Format types</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
ファイル形式とはコンピュータで扱うデータを保存するための規格です。 
オペレーティングシステムはファイルを何バイトから数千億バイトまである
一定の長さのひと連なりのバイト列として保存しますが、 その実際の中身の
データの種類がはっきり分かるような記述をするしくみがありません。 そこで
複雑なデータの代わりになる情報を読み解くための約束事が開発されました。 
ファイルの <emphasis>種類</emphasis> を特定する約束事はいずれもその
ためのファイル形式を制定します。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
画像を保存する主なファイル形式には<acronym>JPEG</acronym>、 <acronym>
TIFF</acronym>、 <acronym>PNG</acronym>、 <acronym>GIF</acronym>が
あります。 画像を保存するのに最適なファイル形式は、 画像を何に利用する
かによって異なります。 例えば、 インターネット上に公開するための画像
ならばファイルの大きさが非常に重要な要素となります。 またもし画像が
印刷されることを念頭に置くならば、 解像度と品質の高さがより重視される
ことでしょう。 
<link linkend="gimp-using-fileformats">ファイル</link> の形式とその
保存方法の説明もご覧ください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-floatingselection">
    <glossterm lang="en">Floating Selection</glossterm>
    <glossterm lang="ja">フローティング選択範囲</glossterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Selection</primary>
      <secondary>Floating selection</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="センタクハンイ">選択範囲</primary>
      <secondary sortas="フローティングセンタクハンイ">
        フローティング選択範囲
      </secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A floating selection (sometimes called a <quote>floating
        layer</quote>) is a type of temporary layer which is similar in
        function to a normal layer, except that a floating selection must be
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-anchor">anchored</link> before you can
        resume working on any other layers in the image.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In early versions of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, when
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> did not use layers, floating selections were
        used for performing operations on a limited part of an image (you can
        do that more easily now with layers). Now floating selections have no
        practical use, but you must know what you have to do with them.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
フローティング[浮層]選択範囲 (<quote>フローティングレイヤー</quote>
と呼ばれることもあります) は通常のレイヤーと同じ機能をもつ一時的な種類
のレイヤーですが、 画像上の他のレイヤーでの作業を再開するにはその前に
フローティング選択範囲を
<link linkend="gimp-layer-anchor">固定</link> する必要があります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
初期の版の<acronym>GIMP</acronym>にはレイヤーがなかったため、 画像の
一部に限定した操作をするときにはフローティング選択範囲が使われました
(今ならレイヤーを使えば簡単に同じことができます)。 今となっては
フローティング選択範囲に実益は無いのですが、 その扱い方は知っておく
べきです。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-floyd-steinberg-dithering">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Floyd-Steinberg Dithering</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">Floyd-Steinbergディザリング</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>Floyd-Steinberg</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Floyd-Steinberg dithering is a method of
        <link linkend="glossary-dithering">dithering</link> which was first
        published in 1976 by Robert W. Floyd and Louis Steinberg. The
        dithering process begins in the upper left corner of the image. For
        each pixel, the closest available color in the palette is chosen and
        the difference between that color and the original color is computed
        in each RGB channel. Then specific fractions of these differences
        are dispersed among several adjacent pixels which haven't yet been
        visited (below and to the right of the original pixel). Because of
        the order of processing, the procedure can be done in a single pass
        over the image.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        When you convert an image to
        <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">Indexed</link>
        mode, you can choose between two variants of Floyd-Steinberg
        dithering.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
フロイド-スタインバーグ・ディザリングとは Robert W. Floyd 氏と 
Louis Steinberg 氏による 
<link linkend="glossary-dithering">ディザリング</link> 技法のひとつで、
 その初版は1976年に発表されました。 ディザリングの処理は画像の左上隅の
画素から開始されます。 個々の画素ではパレットから使える最も近い色が選び
出され、 その色と元の色との差が<acronym>RGB</acronym>の各チャンネルごと
に算出されます。 その次にこれらの差の値からなる特別な分数が、 近接する
未訪問の画素 (元の画素の下側と右側) に拡散されます。 処理には順序がある
のでその進行は画像全体に対し1過程です。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>で画像を
<link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">インデックスつき</link> の
モードにするときのオプションには、 Floyd-Steinberg のアルゴリズムの
2変種が選択肢にあります。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-gamma">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Gamma</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">ガンマ</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Gamma</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>ガンマ</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Gamma or gamma correction is a non-linear operation which is used to
        encode and decode luminance or color values in video or still image
        systems. It is used in many types of imaging systems to straighten out
        a curved signal-to-light or intensity-to-signal response. For example,
        the light emitted by a CRT is not linear with regard to its input
        voltage, and the voltage from an electric camera is not linear with
        regard to the intensity (power) of the light in the scene. Gamma
        encoding helps to map the data into a perceptually linear domain, so
        that the limited signal range (the limited number of bits in each RGB
        signal) is better optimized perceptually.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Gamma is used as an exponent (power) in the correction equation. Gamma
        compression (where gamma &lt; 1) is used to encode linear luminance or
        RGB values into color signals or digital file values, and gamma
        expansion (where gamma &gt; 1) is the decoding process, and usually
        occurs where the current-to-voltage function for a CRT is non-linear.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        For PC video, images are encoded with a gamma of about 0.45 and
        decoded with a gamma of 2.2. For Mac systems, images are typically
        encoded with a gamma of about 0.55 and decoded with a gamma of 1.8.
        The sRGB color space standard used for most cameras, PCs and printers
        does not use a simple exponential equation, but has a decoding gamma
        value near 2.2 over much of its range.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, gamma is an option used in the brush tab
        of the <link linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link>
        filter and in the <link linkend="plug-in-flame">Flame</link> filter.
        The <link linkend="gimp-display-filter-dialog">display filters</link>
        also include a Gamma filter. Also see the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">Levels Tool</link>, where you can
        use the middle slider to change the gamma value.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
ガンマもしくはガンマ補正とは、 ビデオ映像や静止画像のシステムにおいて
輝度や色の値を符号化および復号化するのに使われる一種の非線形操作です。 
画像や映像を扱うさまざまな種類の機器で、 グラフ上で信号-光線曲線や強度-
信号曲線の直線的でないところを真っ直ぐに正すために利用されます。 例えば
<acronym>CRT</acronym>が発する光は入力側の電圧に対し比例しませんし、 
電子カメラの電圧は撮影場面の光の強度対数に対し直線的ではありません。 
ガンマによる符号化は、 信号の限定的な範囲 (つまり<acronym>RGB</acronym>
の各信号にある限られたビット数) の知覚的な最適化がより良く行なわれる
ようにするため、 データを知覚的な直線上に分布させるのに役立ちます。
<!--訳者はperceptuallyの意味がわかりませんでした-->
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
ガンマ値は指数として補正の数式に登場します。 ガンマ圧縮 (つまりガンマ値
 &lt; 1) は直線的に分布する輝度や<acronym>RGB</acronym>値を色信号や
デジタルファイル値に符号化するときに使います。 一方ガンマ展開 (つまり
ガンマ値 &gt; 1) は復号処理であり、 たいていは<acronym>CRT</acronym>
への電流-電圧関数が非線形であるとき使われます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
[ウィンドウズ系の]パソコンの画面ではガンマ値がおよそ 0.45 で画像を
符号化し、 2.2 で復号しています。 <productname>Mac</productname> の
システムでは画像の符号化におよそ 0.55 のガンマ値を、 復号に 1.8 の
ガンマ値を使うのが典型的です。 大多数のカメラやパソコンやプリンタが
利用しているs<acronym>RGB</acronym>色空間の標準が用いる数式は単純な
指数関数ではなく、 復号に使うガンマ値はその値の範囲を大きく越えた2.2
近くになっています。<!--FIX訳文-->
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
ガンマ補正をオプションにもつ<acronym>GIMP</acronym>のプラグインには、 
<link linkend="plug-in-gimpressionist">GIMPressionist</link> フィルタの
<guilabel>ブラシ(<accel>B</accel>)</guilabel> タブや、 
<link linkend="plug-in-flame">炎</link> フィルタがあります。 また、 
<link linkend="gimp-display-filter-dialog">ディスプレイフィルタ</link>
もガンマフィルタを含んでいます。 そのほか
<link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">レベルツール</link> のダイアログを
見ていただくと、 ここでは中央のスライダを使ってガンマ値が変更できます。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-gamut">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Gamut</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">ガモット</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Gamut</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>ガモット</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        In color reproduction, including computer graphics and photography,
        the gamut, or color gamut (pronounced /ˈgæmət/), is a certain complete
        subset of colors. The most common usage refers to the subset of colors
        which can be accurately represented in a given circumstance, such as
        within a given color space or by a certain output device. Another
        sense, less frequently used but not less correct, refers to the
        complete set of colors found within an image at a given time. In this
        context, digitizing a photograph, converting a digitized image to a
        different color space, or outputting it to a given medium using a
        certain output device generally alters its gamut, in the sense that
        some of the colors in the original are lost in the process.
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-gamut"/>
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
コンピュータグラフィックスやコンピュータ上の写真での色再現の場面で
言われるガモット (<foreignphrase>gamut</foreignphrase>&mdash;英語) 
とは、 確固たる色[空間]の部分集合のことです。 最も一般的な利用法は、 
この色の部分集合は所与の色空間の範囲内でもあるいは何かしらの出力
デバイスで決められる環境に合わせても正確に再現されるものとして扱う
ことです。 別の言い方をすれば、 あまり使われなくとも正確さを失わず、 
そのとき画像で得られる完全な色集合を参照します。 そうしたとき写真を
デジタル化してそのデジタル画像を他の色空間に転換もしくは何かしらの
出力デバイスを使って所与のメディアに出力すると、 普通はそのガモットが
変化し、 その処理の過程で元々あった色がいくつか失われます。 
<link linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-gamut">ウィキペディア</link>
を参照してください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-gif">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>GIF</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>GIF</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        <trademark class="trade">GIF</trademark> stands for Graphics
        Interchange Format.  It is a
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link>
        with good, lossless compression for images with low
        <link linkend="glossary-colordepth">color depth</link> (up to 256
        different colors per image). Since GIF was developed, a new format called
        <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">Portable Network Graphics (PNG)
        </link> has been developed, which is better than GIF in all respects,
        with the exception of animations and some rarely-used features.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        GIF was introduced by CompuServe in 1987. It became popular mostly
        because of its efficient, LZW compression. The size of the image files
        required clearly less disk space than other usual graphics formats of
        the time, such as PCX or MacPaint. Even large images could be
        transmitted in a reasonable time, even with slow modems. In addition,
        the open licensing policy of CompuServe made it possible for any
        programmer to implement the GIF format for his own applications free
        of charge, as long as the CompuServe copyright notice was attached to
        them.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Colors in GIF are stored in a color table which can hold up to 256
        different entries, chosen from 16.7 million different color values.
        When the image format was introduced, this was not a much of a
        limitation, since only a few people had hardware which could display
        more colors than that. For typical drawings, cartoons, black-and-white
        photographs and similar uses, 256 colors are quite sufficient as a
        rule, even today. For more complex images, such as color photographs,
        however, a huge loss of quality is apparent, which is why the format
        is not considered to be suitable for those purposes.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        One color entry in the palette can be defined to be transparent.
        With transparency, the GIF image can look like it is non-rectangular
        in shape. However, semi-transparency, as in
        <link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link>, is not possible.
        A pixel can only be either entirely visible or completely
        transparent.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The first version of GIF was 87a. In 1989, CompuServe published an
        expanded version, called 89a. Among other things, this made it
        possible to save several images in one GIF file, which is especially
        used for simple animation. The version number can be distinguished
        from the first six bytes of a GIF file. Interpreted as ASCII symbols,
        they are <quote>GIF87a</quote> or <quote>GIF89a</quote>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIF</acronym>は<foreignphrase>Graphics Interchange Format
</foreignphrase>の略です。 低い
<link linkend="glossary-colordepth">色深度</link> (画像ひとつにつき
256色まで) ながら画像は良質で、 損失のない圧縮がかけられる
<link linkend="glossary-fileformat">ファイル形式</link> です。 
<acronym>GIF</acronym>が開発されたのを受け、 アニメーション機能と
めったに使われない機能を除く全ての点で<acronym>GIF</acronym>より優れた
<link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">Portable Network Graphics 
(<acronym>PNG</acronym>)</link> 形式が新たに開発されました。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIF</acronym>は1987年にCompuServeにより発表されました。 有能な
<acronym>LZW</acronym>圧縮法を採用していることから大人気を博しました。 
この画像ファイルを収めるのに必要なディスク容量は、 当時使われていた
<acronym>PCX</acronym>形式や <application>MacPaint</application>用の形式
など他のいずれの画像形式よりも断然小さくて済みました。 通信速度の遅い
モデムを通して大きな画像を送る場合でさえも、 転送時間は妥当なもの
でした。 しかもCompuServe社が公開ライセンスの方針をとったため、 
CompuServe社の著作権表示を添付しさえすれば方々のプログラマが誰でも無料で
自身のアプリケーションに<acronym>GIF</acronym>を扱うコードを組み込める
ようになっていました。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIF</acronym>で使われている色は1677万色あまりから選ばれ、
最大で256色の項目がある色索引表に記録されています。 この画像形式が
登場した当時は256色を越す発色ができる装置を持つ人は僅かであったため、 
この制限はさほど問題になりませんでした。 今日でも作図や漫画、 白黒写真
のような一部の利用形態なら256色で十分通用します。 しかしカラー写真など
のもっと複雑な画像に対しては大きな画質の低下を招くことは明らかなので、 
この形式はこのような用途には向いていないと考えられています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
パレットの色項目のひとつは透過効果に割り当て可能です。 透過効果つきの
<acronym>GIF</acronym>画像は長方形以外の形にも見せられます。 しかし 
<link linkend="file-png-save-defaults">PNG</link> のような半透明の効果
はありません。 画素は全部見えるか完全透明になるかのどちらかです。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIF</acronym>の最初の版は87aです。 1989年にCompuServe社は89aと
名付けた拡張版を公開しました。 とりわけ注目すべきはひとつの<acronym>GIF
</acronym>ファイルに複数の画像を保管できるようにしたことで、 これは特に
アニメーション機能として使えます。 版の番号は<acronym>GIF</acronym>
ファイルの最初の6バイトで見分けられるようになっています。 <acronym>ASCII
</acronym>文字に置き換えると<quote>GIF87a</quote>と<quote>GIF89a</quote>
です。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-gnu">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>GNU</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        The GNU project was started in 1983 by Richard Stallman with the
        goal of developing a completely free operating system. It is
        especially well-known from the GNU General Public License (GPL) and
        GNU/Linux, a GNU-variant with a Linux kernel.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The name came about from the naming conventions which were in
        practice at MIT, where Stallman worked at the time.
        For programs which were similar to other programs, recursive
        acronyms were chosen as names. Since the new system was to be based
        on the widespread operating system, Unix, Stallman looked for that
        kind of name and came up with GNU, which stands for
        <quote>GNU is not Unix</quote>. In order to avoid confusion, the
        name should be pronounced with the <quote>G</quote>, not like
        <quote>new</quote>. There were several reasons for making GNU
        Unix-compatible. For one thing, Stallman was convinced that most
        companies would refuse a completely new operating system, if the
        programs they used wouldn't run on it. In addition, the architecture
        of Unix made quick, easy and distributed development possible,
        since Unix consists of many small programs that can be developed
        independently of each other, for the most part. Also, many parts of
        a Unix system were freely available to anyone and could therefore
        be directly integrated into GNU, for example, the typesetting
        system, TeX, or the X Window System. The missing parts were newly
        written from the ground up.
      </para>
      <para lang="en"><acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        (GNU Image Manipulation Program) is an official GNU application
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-gnu"/>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GNU</acronym>とは1983年よりRichard Stallman氏により始められた
プロジェクトのことで、 完全にフリーなオペーレーティングシステムの開発
を目指しています。 特に<foreignphrase><acronym>GNU</acronym>一般公衆
利用許諾契約書</foreignphrase> (<acronym>GPL</acronym>) や、 <acronym>
GNU</acronym>/<productname>Linux</productname> などで耳にした方も多い
と思います。 ちなみに後者は<acronym>GNU</acronym>ソフトウェアなどと 
<productname>Linux</productname> カーネルの組み合わせになるシステム
を指す言葉として<acronym>GNU</acronym>プロジェクトが主張する呼称です。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
この名称はストールマン氏が当時勤務していた<acronym>MIT</acronym>で運営
されていた命名協議のなかで生まれました。 他のプログラムに似ていた
プログラムのために<!--???-->、 再帰的命名がとり入れられました。 この
新しいシステムは <productname>Unix</productname> という広く普及していた
オペレーティングシステムをもとにしていたため、 ストールマン氏はそれに
似た名前を探して<acronym>GNU</acronym>を思い立ちました。 これは
<quote>GNU's Not Unix</quote>の略であるとされています。 野生動物ヌーと
の混同を避けるためこの名前を発音するときは頭に子音<quote>G</quote>が
付きます。 いろいろな理由があって<acronym>GNU</acronym>は <productname>
Unix</productname>互換の内容が盛り込まれています。 ひとつには全く新しい
オペレーティングシステムを作ったところで、 もしもその上でプログラムが
動作しなかったらそのプログラムのメーカーがそっぽを向いてしまうだろうと
いう確信をストールマン氏が持っていたからです。 さらには、 <productname>
Unix</productname>は小さなプログラムの寄り集まりにより成り立っていて、 
それらのプログラムは大部分が各自で開発できるようになっていたため、 
<productname>Unix</productname>の構造に倣えば素早く簡便に開発し発布
できることがあげられます。 また、 <productname>Unix</productname>
システムの数多くの部分が誰でも自由に扱えるようになっていたため、 
<acronym>GNU</acronym>に直に統合できたからです。 例えば文書製版システム
<application>TeX</application> や X ウィンドウシステムです。 足りない
ものは新たに始めから書き起こされました。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIMP</acronym> (<acronym>GNU</acronym> Image Manipulation 
Program) は<acronym>GNU</acronym>の正式なアプリケーションです。
<link linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-gnu">ウィキペディア</link> も
ご覧ください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-grayscale">
    <glossterm>
      <anchor id="glossary-graylevel" xreflabel="Grayscale"/>
      <phrase lang="en">Grayscale</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">グレースケール</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Grayscale</primary>
      <secondary>Overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>グレースケール</primary>
      <secondary sortas="ガイカン">概観</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Grayscale is a mode for encoding the colors of an image which
        contains only black, white and shades of gray.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        When you create a new image, you can choose to create it in
        Grayscale mode (which you can colorize later, by changing it to RGB
        mode). You can also change an existing image to grayscale by using
        the <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-grayscale">Grayscale</link>,
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-desaturate">Desaturate</link>,
        <link linkend="plug-in-decompose-registered">Decompose</link>,
        <link linkend="plug-in-colors-channel-mixer">Channel
        Mixer</link>, although not all formats will accept these changes.
        Although you can create images in Grayscale mode and convert images
        to it, it is not a color model, in the true sense of the word.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        As explained in <link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB mode</link>, 24-bit
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> images can have up to 256 levels of gray. If
        you change from Grayscale to RGB mode, your image will have an RGB
        structure with three color channels, but of course, it will still be
        gray.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Grayscale image files (8-bit) are smaller than RGB files.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
グレースケールとは画像の色を黒と白と灰色陰影のみで符号化するモードの
ことです。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
新しい画像を作成するときにグレースケールモードで作成するオプションが
選べます (あとからでも<acronym>RGB</acronym>モードに切り替えれば
彩色可能になります)。 あるいは既存の画像を
<link linkend="gimp-image-convert-grayscale">グレースケール</link> 
モードに変換したり、 その画像から
<link linkend="plug-in-decompose-registered">チャンネル分解</link> や
<link linkend="plug-in-colors-channel-mixer">チャンネルミキサー</link>
のモノクロームモードでグレースケール画像を生成したり、
<link linkend="gimp-tool-desaturate">脱色ツール</link> で灰色陰影画像
に変換する方法がありますが、 どんなモードの画像でもこれらのコマンド類
が利用できるわけではありません。 グレースケールモードで画像を作成したり
既存の画像をグレースケールモードに変換できても、 その名前が示すとおり
色付きにはなりえません。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<link linkend="glossary-rgb">RGB</link> モードで説明したように、 24
ビットの<acronym>GIMP</acronym>画像は最高で256階調の白黒陰影を[各
チャンネルに]持つことになります。 グレースケールから<acronym>RGB
</acronym>モードに変換すると、 画像は3つの色チャンネルを備えた<acronym>
RGB</acronym>構造に変わりますが、 もちろん画像の見た目は依然として
白黒陰影のままです。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
グレースケール画像のファイルは一種の8ビット画像ですから、 <acronym>
RGB</acronym>モードにするよりもファイル容量が小さくなります。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-guides">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Guides</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">ガイド (見当線)</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Guides</primary>
      <secondary>Using</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ケントウセン">見当線</primary>
      <secondary sortas="リヨウホウ">利用法</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Guides are lines you can temporarily display on an image while you are
        working on it. You can display as many guides as you would like, in
        either the horizontal or the vertical direction. These lines help you
        position a selection or a layer on the image. They do not appear when
        the image is printed.
      </para>
      <!--TODO: a glossary entry should tell what a guide *is*, how to create
                or use a guide should be described somewhere else!
      -->
      <para lang="en">
        To create a guide, simply click on one of the rulers in the image
        window and pull out a guide, while holding the
        <mousebutton moreinfo="none">mouse button</mousebutton> pressed. The guide is then
        displayed as a blue, dashed line, which follows the pointer. As soon
        as you create a guide, the <quote>Move</quote> tool is activated and
        the mouse pointer changes to the Move icon.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        You can also create a guide with the <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-add">New Guide</link> command, which
        allows you to precisely place the guide on the image, the <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-percent">New Guide (by Percent)</link>
        command, or the <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-selection">New
        Guides from Selection</link> command.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The behavior of the guides depends upon the
        <guilabel moreinfo="none">Affect</guilabel> mode of the <quote>Move</quote> tool.
        When <emphasis>Transform Layer</emphasis> mode is selected, the
        mouse pointer turns into a small hand as soon as it gets close to a
        guide. Then the guide is activated and it turns red, and you can
        move the guide or delete it by moving it back into the ruler. If
        <emphasis>Transform Selection</emphasis> mode is selected, you can
        position a guide, but you cannot move it after that.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        To make it easier for you to position image elements, you can
        <quote>magnetize</quote> the guides with the
        <link linkend="gimp-view-snap-to-guides">Snap to Guides</link>
        command. You can remove the guides with the
        <link linkend="gimp-image-guides-remove">Remove all guides</link>
        command. You can enable and disable displaying the guides without
        removing them by using the
        <link linkend="gimp-view-show-guides">Show Guides</link> command.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        For more information about guides, see the
        <link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-grid">Grids and Guides</link>
        section.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
見当線 (ガイド) とは操作途中で画像上に一時的に表示できる線のことです。
縦や横に好きなだけ何本でも見当線を表示できます。 これらは画像上に
レイヤーや選択範囲を配置するときに威力を発揮します。 画像の印刷物には
この線は現れません。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja"><!--to be removed-->
見当線を置くには、 画像ウィンドウの縦もしくは横の定規をクリックして
画像内に曳き込みます。 現れた見当線は青色の破線で表示され、 曳いていく
マウスポインタと連動しますのでどこかでマウスボタンを放してください。
見当線を作成すると直ちに
<xref linkend="gimp-tool-move"/> ツールが起用されます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja"><!--to be removed-->
<link linkend="gimp-image-guides-add">新規ガイド...</link> コマンドを
使っても見当線が置けます。 しかも画像上に精密に見当線を置くための
<link linkend="gimp-image-guides-percent">新規ガイド 
(パーセントで)...</link> や、
<link linkend="gimp-image-guides-selection">選択範囲から新規ガイド
</link> コマンドもあります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
見当線の扱い方は
<xref linkend="gimp-tool-move"/> ツールの <guilabel>移動対象
</guilabel> モードに依存します。 <quote>レイヤー</quote> を移動対象に
選んだときは、 マウスポインタを見当線にかざすとその姿が小さな掌の形に
なります。 さらに見当線が活性化されて赤くなりますので、 クリックして
曳くと移動でき、 定規の上まで曳けば消去できます。 <quote>選択範囲
</quote>を移動対象に選んでいる場合は、 新たに見当線を作成できても
いったん置くと移動ができません。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
画像上の部品を一直線に配置するのなら、 
<link linkend="gimp-view-snap-to-guides">ガイドにスナップ</link> 
を有効にしておくとそれらの部品が見当線に吸い付くようになるので便利
です。 全ての見当線を消去するには
<link linkend="gimp-image-guides-remove">すべてのガイドを削除</link> 
をご利用ください。 見当線を消去せずに見えなくするには
<link linkend="gimp-view-show-guides">ガイドを表示</link> コマンドを
お使いください。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
見当線についてのさらなる情報は、
<link linkend="gimp-concepts-image-grid">グリッドとガイド</link> を
参考にしてください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-histogram">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Histogram</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">ヒストグラム</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Histogram</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>ヒストグラム</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        In digital image processing, a histogram is a graph representing the
        statistical frequency of the gray values or the color values in an
        image. The histogram of an image tells you about the occurrence of
        gray values or color values, as well as the contrast range and the
        brightness of the image. In a color image, you can create one
        histogram with information about all possible colors, or three
        histograms for the individual color channels. The latter makes the
        most sense, since most procedures are based on grayscale images and
        therefore further processing is immediately possible.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
ヒストグラムとはデジタル画像処理において画像の陰影の値あるいは色の値の
統計的頻度をグラフ化したものです。 画像のヒストグラムは陰影の値もしくは
色の値ごとの出現の程度と、 コントラストの幅や画像の明るさも示します。 
カラー画像の場合ひとつのヒストグラムで出現する全ての色についての情報を
示したり3つのヒストグラムで各色チャンネルごとの情報を示せます。 後者は
ほとんどの処理過程がグレースケール画像上で行なわれるため大きな意義が
あり、  より深い処理が直ちに可能になります。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-hsv">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>HSV</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        HSV is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which has components for Hue (the color, such as blue or red),
        Saturation (how strong the color is) and Value (the brightness).
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The RGB mode is very well suited to computer screens, but it doesn't
        let us describe what we see in everyday life; a light green, a
        pale pink, a dazzling red, etc. The HSV model takes these
        characteristics into account. HSV and RGB are not completely
        independent of each other. You can see that with the Color Picker
        tool; when you change a color in one of the color models, the other
        one also changes. Brave souls can read
        <emphasis>Grokking the GIMP</emphasis>, which explains their
        interrelationship.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>HSV</acronym>とは色相 (青や赤などの色) と彩度 (色の強さ) と
明度 (明るさ) を成分とする 
<link linkend="glossary-colormodel">色モデル</link> のことです。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>RGB</acronym>モードはコンピュータ画面には非常によく適応し
ますが、 明るい緑色や薄紅色、 眩しい赤など日常見るもの全てを容易に描出
できるわけではありません。 <acronym>HSV</acronym>モデルはこのような特徴
を考慮に入れています。 <acronym>HSV</acronym>と<acronym>RGB</acronym>
は完全無関係ではありません。 このことは 
<link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">スポイトツール</link> で
いずれかの色モデルで色を変更すると、 他でも変化することから確認できます。 
これらの相互関連についての説明を読む勇気のある方は、 
<xref linkend="bibliography-online-grokking-gimp"/> をご覧ください。
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <para lang="en">Brief description of the HSV components:</para>
        <para lang="ja"><acronym>HSV</acronym>の各成分についての概説</para>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">Hue</term>
          <term lang="ja">色相</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              This is the color itself, which results from the combination of
              primary colors. All shades (except for the gray levels) are
              represented in a <emphasis>chromatic circle</emphasis>: yellow,
              blue, and also purple, orange, etc. The chromatic circle (or
              <quote>color wheel</quote>) values range between 0° and 360°.
              (The term <quote>color</quote> is often used instead of
              <quote>Hue</quote>. The RGB colors are <quote>primary
              colors</quote>.)
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
これは色そのもので、 基本色の合成から成っています。 灰色階調を除く全て
の陰影<!--???-->がイエローや青やさらには紫やオレンジなど、 <quote>
色相環</quote>で表現されます。 色相環は0°から360°の範囲の値があります。 
(<quote>色</quote>はしばしば<quote>色相</quote>の代わりに使われます。 
<acronym>RGB</acronym>の各色は<quote>基本色</quote>です。)
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">Saturation</term>
          <term lang="ja">彩度</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              This value describes how pale the color is. A completely
              unsaturated color is a shade of gray. As the saturation
              increases, the color becomes a pastel shade. A completely
              saturated color is pure. Saturation values go from 0 to 100,
              from white to the purest color.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
この値はその色がどの程度薄まっているかを示します。 完全に彩度を失った
色は灰色になります。 彩度が増すと、 色はパステル調に近づきます。 彩度が
完全な色は純色です。 彩度は0から100の間の値をとり、 つまり白から純粋色
の幅があります。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">Value</term>
          <term lang="ja">明度</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              This value describes the luminosity, the luminous intensity. It
              is the amount of light emitted by a color. You can see a change
              of luminosity when a colored object is moved from being in the
              shadow to being in the sun, or when you increase the luminosity
              of your screen. Values go from 0 to 100. Pixel values in the
              three channels are also luminosities: <quote>Value</quote> in
              the HSV color model is the maximum of these elementary values in
              the RGB space (scaled to 0-100).
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
この値は明度、 つまり明るさの強さを示します。 色が発する光の量です。
明度の変化は例えば日陰から日向に移動した物体の色や、 コンピュータ画面
の明度を増したときにわかります。 0から100の範囲の値を持ちます。 3つの
チャンネルそれぞれの画素の値も明度です。 <acronym>HSV</acronym>色モデル
の明度とは<acronym>RGB</acronym>色空間の3つの基本の値 (0から100の範囲)
の最大値から得られます。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-html-notation">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">HTML notation</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja"><acronym>HTML</acronym>表記法</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>HTML notation</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>HTML notation</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary><acronym>HTML</acronym>表記法</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="イロ">色</primary>
      <secondary sortas="HTMLヒョウキホウ">
        <acronym>HTML</acronym>表記法
      </secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A hex triplet is a way of encoding a color for a computer. The
        <quote>#</quote> symbol indicates that the numbers which follow it
        are encoded in hexadecimal. Each color is specified in two
        hexadecimal digits which make up a triplet (three pairs) of
        hexadecimal values in the form <quote>#rrggbb</quote>, where
        <quote>rr</quote> represents red, <quote>gg</quote> represents green
        and <quote>bb</quote> represents blue.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
6桁の16進数はコンピュータで扱う色を符号化する方法になります。 最初の
<quote>#</quote>記号はそのあとにつづく英数字が16進数であることを示して
います。 3つの基本色はそれぞれが2けたで表され、 3つ合わさって<quote>
#rrggbb</quote>の形になります。 この<quote>rr</quote>は赤を、 
<quote>gg</quote>は緑を、 <quote>bb</quote>は青を表します。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-imagehose">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Image Hose</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">散播式ブラシ</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Image Hose</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="サンパシキブラシ">散播式ブラシ</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        An image hose in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is a special type of brush
        which consists of several images. For example, you could have a
        brush with footprints, which consists of two images, one for the
        left footprint and one for the right. While painting with this
        brush, a left footprint would appear first, then a right footprint,
        then a left one, etc. This type of brush is very powerful.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        An image hose is also sometimes called an <quote>image pipe</quote>
        or <quote>animated brush</quote>. An image hose is indicated in the
        Brushes dialog by a small red triangle in the lower right corner of
        the brush's symbol.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        For information concerning creating an image hose, please see the
        <link linkend="gimp-using-animated-brushes">Using Animated
        Brushes</link> and <link linkend="gimp-using-brushes">Using
        Brushes</link> sections.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の散播式ブラシは複数の刻印をもつ特別な形式の
ブラシです。 例えば左足と右足の2枚の画像でできている足跡のブラシも
作れます。 このブラシでなぞるとはじめに左足が刻印され、 その隣に右足が
刻印され、 再び左足&hellip;というふうになるでしょう。 このようなブラシ
形式はとても強力です。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
散播式ブラシは<quote>イメージパイプブラシ</quote>や<quote>アニメーション
するブラシ</quote>とも呼ばれます。 ブラシダイアログ上ではブラシ見本の
右下に小さな赤い三角形がついたものが散播式ブラシです。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
散播式ブラシの作り方と使い方については
<link linkend="gimp-using-animated-brushes">GIHダイアログ</link> と
<link linkend="gimp-using-brushes">ブラシの追加</link> をご覧ください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-incremental">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Incremental, paint mode</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">描画ツールの重ね塗りモード</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Incremental</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="カサネヌリ">重ね塗り</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Incremental mode is a paint mode where each brush stroke is drawn
        directly on the active layer. When it is set, each additional stroke
        of the brush increases the effect of the brush, up to the maximum
        opacity for the brush.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        If incremental mode is not set, brush strokes are drawn on a canvas
        buffer, which is then combined with the active layer. The maximum
        effect of a brush is then determined by the opacity, and stroking with
        the brush repeatedly does not increase the effect beyond this limit.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
重ね塗りモードとは描画モードのひとつです。 ブラシの刻印が活性レイヤー
に直接描画されます。 このモードを有効にすると、 ブラシの刻印が重なった
部分はブラシの最大不透明度を越えない範囲でブラシの効果が増します。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
重ね塗りモードが無効の場合、 ブラシの刻印はキャンバスのバッファ上に
描画され、 そのつぎに活性レイヤーと合成されます。 ブラシの最大効果は
そのとき不透明度で決定されるため、 ブラシの刻印が重なってもその効果は
この限界を越えません。
      </para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/glossary/tool-opt-increment.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/glossary/tool-opt-nonincrement.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The two images above were created using a brush with spacing set to
        60 percent. The image on the left shows non-incremental painting and
        the image on the right shows the difference with incremental painting.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Incremental mode is a tool option that is shared by several brush
        tools, except those which have a <quote>rate</quote> control, which
        automatically implies an incremental effect. You can set it by
        checking the <guilabel moreinfo="none">Incremental</guilabel> checkbox
        in the tool option dialog for the tool (Paintbrush, Pencil and Eraser).
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
上に示した2つの図はブラシ感覚を60パーセントにした描線です。 左図は
<quote>重ね塗り</quote>なしで描いたもので、 右図の<quote>重ね塗り
</quote>ありの描線との違いがわかります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
重ね塗りモードは<quote>割合</quote>オプションがないブラシツールの
ツールオプションにあります。 割合オプションは重ね塗り効果を自動化
します。 <quote>ブラシで描画</quote>ツール、 <quote>鉛筆で描画</quote>
ツール、 <quote>消しゴム</quote>ツールのツールオプションにある
<guilabel>重ね塗り</guilabel> チェックボックスで有効になります。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-indexedcolors">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Indexed Colors</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">インデックス化カラー</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Indexed Colors</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Indexed colors</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="インデックスカカラー">インデックス化カラー</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="イロ">色</primary>
      <secondary sortas="インデックスカカラー">インデックス化カラー</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Indexed color mode is a mode for encoding colors in an image where
        each pixel in the image is assigned an 8-bit color number. The color
        which corresponds to this number is then put in a table (the palette).
        Changing a color in the palette changes all the pixels which refer
        to this palette color. Although you can create images in
        <emphasis>Indexed Color</emphasis> mode and can transform images to
        it, it is, strictly speaking, not a
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        See also the
        <link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">Indexed Palette</link>
        section and the
        <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">Convert Image to Indexed
        Colors</link> command.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
インデックス化カラーモードとは画像の画素に8ビットの色番号が付与される
方式の色の符号化モードのことです。 それらの番号に対応する色はパレット
と呼ばれる対照表だけに記録されます。 パレットの色を変更するとその番号を
もつ全ての画素の色が換わります。 <quote>インデックス化カラー</quote>
モードで画像を作成したり他の色モードに転換できるようになっていますが、 
厳密に言えばこのモードは 
<link linkend="glossary-colormodel">色モデル</link> ではありません。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">カラーマップダイアログ
</link> と 
<link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">インデックス化モードに変換
</link> コマンドについてもご覧ください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-interpolation">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Interpolation</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">補間</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Interpolation means calculating intermediate values. When you
        enlarge (<quote>digitally zoom</quote>) or otherwise transform
        (rotate, shear or give perspective to) a digital image,
        interpolation procedures are used to compute the colors of the
        pixels in the transformed image. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> offers
        three interpolation methods, which differ in quality and speed. In
        general, the better the quality, the more time the interpolation
        takes. The methods are:
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
補間とは中間値の算出を意味します。 デジタル画像を拡大 (<quote>デジタル
的に引き延ば</quote>) したり変換 (回転や剪断変形あるいは遠近法変換) 
すると、 変換を受けた画像の画素の色を算出するために補間処理が
行われます。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は処理速度と品質に違いがある3つの
補間方法からいずれかを選べるようになっています。 概して言えば品質が
高いものほど補間処理に時間がかかります。 選べる方法はつぎのとおりです。
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <emphasis>None</emphasis> (sometimes called <quote>Nearest
            Neighbor</quote>): The color of each pixel is copied from its
            closest neighboring pixel in the original image. This often
            results in aliasing (the <quote>stair-step</quote> effect) and a
            coarse image, but it is the fastest method.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
<quote>最近傍補間</quote>とも言います。 各画素の色は元画像で最も
近くにある画素の色が使われます。 この方法はしばしばエイリアス化 
(境界が<quote>ギザギザ</quote>になること) して画像が粗悪になり
ますが、 処理時間は最短です。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en"><emphasis>Linear</emphasis> (sometimes called
            <quote>Bilinear</quote>): The color of each pixel is computed as
            the average color of the four closest pixels in the original
            image. This gives a satisfactory result for most images and is a
            good compromise between speed and quality.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
<quote>双線形補間</quote>とも言います。 各画素の色は元画像において
最近傍の4つの画素の色を平均したものです。 ほとんどの画像でこの方法
は満足のいく仕上がりになりますから、 処理速度と品質の両面に折り
合いをつける良い方法です。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en"><emphasis>Cubic</emphasis> (sometimes called
            <quote>Bicubic</quote>): The color of each pixel is computed as
            the average color of the eight closest pixels in the original
            image. This usually gives the best result, but it naturally takes
            more time.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
<quote>双三次補間</quote>とも言います。 各画素の色は元画像において
最近傍の8つの画素の色を平均したものです。 大抵の画像で最高の仕上
がりが得られますが、 当然もっと処理に時間がかかります。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para lang="en"><acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses interpolation when you
        <link linkend="gimp-image-scale">Scale</link> an image,
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-scale">Scale</link> a layer, and when you
        <link linkend="gimp-tools-transform">Transform</link> an image. You
        can also set the default interpolation method in the
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">Tools Options Preferences
        </link> dialog.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>が補間処理を実行するのは、 レイヤーや画像を
<link linkend="gimp-image-scale">拡大・縮小</link> するときと、 画像を
<link linkend="gimp-tools-transform">変換</link> するときです。 
補間方法はそのつど指定できますが、 既定値を変更するには 
<link linkend="gimp-prefs-tool-options">環境設定</link> ダイアログの
<quote>ツールオプション</quote>のページで指定してください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-jpeg">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>JPEG</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>JPEG</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        JPEG is a <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link>
        which supports compression and works at all color depths. The
        image compression is adjustable, but beware: Too high a compression
        could severely reduce image quality, since JPEG compression is lossy.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Use JPEG to create web graphics or if you don't want your
        image to take up a lot of space. JPEG is a good format for
        photographs and for computer-generated images (CGI). It is not well
        suited for:
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>JPEG</acronym>はどんな色深度でも動作する圧縮に優れた
<link linkend="glossary-fileformat">ファイル形式</link> です。 画像の
圧縮率は調整できますが、 <acronym>JPEG</acronym>は不可逆圧縮法をとる
のであまりに高く圧縮すると画像の品質は極端に劣ります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
Web用の画像を省量化したいときは<acronym>JPEG</acronym>にしましょう。 
<acronym>JPEG</acronym>は写真や<acronym>CG</acronym>画像の扱いに優れた
形式です。 逆につぎのような用途にはあまり向いていません。
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            digital line drawings (for example, screenshots or vector
            graphics), in which there are many neighboring pixels with the
            same color values, few colors and hard edges,
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
デジタル的な線画。 例えばスクリーンショットやベクター画像など、 同じ色
がずっと続いていて、 使われている色が少なく、 描かれている線の境界が
明確なもの。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Black and white images (only black and white, one bit per pixel)
            or
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
黒と白だけの画像、 つまり1つの画素の色が1ビットで済むもの。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">half-toned images (newsprint).</para>
          <para lang="ja">新聞用画像に使われるハーフトーン画像。</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para lang="en">
        Other formats, such as GIF, PNG or JBIG, are far better for these
        kinds of images.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In general, JPEG transformations are not reversible. Opening and
        then saving a JPEG file causes a new, lossy compression. Increasing
        the quality factor later will not bring back the image information
        which was lost.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
以上のような用途には<acronym>GIF</acronym>や<acronym>JBIG</acronym>
形式が断然優れています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
ほぼ間違いなく<acronym>JPEG</acronym>への変換は不可逆的です。 <acronym>
JPEG</acronym>画像を開いてそれを保存するだけで圧縮による劣化が
起こります。 あとから品質オプションの値を上げても失われた画像の情報は
取り戻せません。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-lab">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>L*a*b*</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        The Lab color space (also called the L*a*b* color space) is a
        <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        developed in the beginning of the 1930s by the Commission
        Internationale d`Eclairage (CIE). It includes all the colors that
        the human eye can perceive. That contains the colors of the
        RGB and the CMYK color spaces, among others. In Lab, a color is
        indicated by three values: L, a and b. Here, the L stands for the
        luminance component — corresponding to the gray value — and a and b
        represent the red-green and blue-yellow parts of the color,
        respectively.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In contrast to RGB or CMYK, Lab is not dependent upon the
        various input and output devices. For that reason, it is used as an
        exchange format between devices. Lab is also the internal color
        model of PostScript Level II.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
Lab色空間、 あるいは L*a*b* (エルスターエイスタービースター) 表色系は
1930年代初頭に<foreignphrase>Commission Internationale d`Eclairage
</foreignphrase> (<acronym>CIE</acronym>) によって開発された
<link linkend="glossary-colormodel">色モデル</link> です。 ヒトの目で
認識できる全ての色を含みます。 <acronym>RGB</acronym>や<acronym>CMYK
</acronym>をはじめいろいろな色空間にある色を包括します。 Lab色空間は
Lとaとbの3つの値で色を表現します。 Lは明度成分&mdash;灰色の値に相当
します&mdash;を、 aとbは色の<quote>赤-緑</quote>と<quote>青-イエロー
</quote>の各部分にそれぞれ相当します。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>RGB</acronym>や<acronym>CMYK</acronym>とは対照的に、 Labは
入力側と出力側双方の様々なデバイスに依存しません。 そこでこの色空間は
デバイス間の情報交換に用いられます。 Postscript Level II の内部色モデル
としてLabが利用されています。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-layer">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Layer</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">レイヤー</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Layer</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>レイヤー</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        You can think of layers as being a stack of slides which are more or
        less transparent. Each layer represents an aspect of the image and
        the image is the sum of all of these aspects. The layer at the bottom
        of the stack is the background layer. The layers above it are the
        components of the foreground.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        You can view and manage the layers of the image through the
        <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layers dialog</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
レイヤーが集まった様子は、 多かれ少なかれ透過している映写用スライドの
重なりにも例えられます。 それぞれのレイヤーが画像に見えるものを請け
負い、 それらおのおのの見えるものたちが合わさって画像ができています。
レイヤーのスタック (積み重ね) の底にあるの背景レイヤーです。 それより
前面にあるレイヤーは前景の部品です。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">レイヤーダイアログ</link> では画像
のレイヤーの様子が見られ、 管理できます。
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title lang="en">Example image with layers</title>
        <title lang="ja">レイヤーのある画像の例</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/dialogs/layers_overview.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="en">Representation of an image with layers</para>
            <para lang="ja">画像がレイヤーに分解できることを示した図</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/dialogs/layers_example.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption><para lang="en">The final image</para></caption>
          <caption><para lang="ja">最終図</para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-marching-ants">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Marching Ants</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">蟻の行進</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Marching ants is a term which describes the dotted line which
        surrounds a selection. The line is animated, so it looks as if
        little ants are running around behind each other.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        You can disable the marching ants by unchecking the
        <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
          <guimenu moreinfo="none"><accel>V</accel>iew</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Show <accel>S</accel>election</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
        option or by using the keyboard shortcut
        <keycombo moreinfo="none"><keycap moreinfo="none">Ctrl</keycap><keycap moreinfo="none">T</keycap></keycombo>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
蟻の行進とは選択範囲をとり囲む点滅破線をいい表した言葉です。 この線は
まるで小さな蟻がぞろぞろと線上を廻る様子に似たアニメーションをします。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
蟻の行進を表示させないようにするには画像ウィンドウのメニューで
<menuchoice>
  <guimenu>表示(<accel>V</accel>)</guimenu>
  <guimenuitem>選択範囲の境界線を表示(<accel>S</accel>)</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice>
を無効にするか、 キーボードショートカット
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>T</keycap></keycombo>
で切り替えてください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-masks">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Masks</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">マスク</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Masks</primary>
      <secondary>Overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>マスク</primary>
      <secondary sortas="ガイカン">概観</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A mask is like a veil put over a layer (layer mask) or all the layers
        of an image (selection mask). You can remove this mask by painting
        with white color, and you can complete it by painting with black
        color. When the mask is <quote>applied</quote>, non masked pixels
        will remain visible (the others will be transparent) or will be
        selected, according to the type of mask.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
マスクとはレイヤーマスクならば1層のレイヤーに対して、 選択マスクならば
画像の全てのレイヤーに対してのベールのようなものです。 マスクの効果は
白く塗ると消え、 黒く塗ると最大限の効果が出ます。 マスクがかけ
られると、 レイヤーマスクの効果がない画素は可視に (それ以外は透過や
半透明に) なり、 選択マスクの効果がない画素が完全選択されます。
      </para>
      <para lang="en">There are two types of masks:</para>
      <para lang="ja">2つの型のマスクについて詳しくみてゆきましょう。</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en"><emphasis>Layer Mask</emphasis>
            : Every layer can have its own mask. The layer mask represents the
            Alpha channel of the layer and allows you to manage its
            transparency. By painting on the layer mask, you can make parts of
            the layer opaque or transparent: painting with black makes the
            layer transparent, painting with white makes the layer opaque and
            painting with shades of gray makes the layer semi-transparent. You
            can use all paint tools to paint on the mask. You can also apply a
            filter or copy-paste. You can use the Layer mask for transition
            effects, volume effects, merging elements from another image, etc.
            See the <link linkend="gimp-layer-mask">Layer Mask</link>
            section for more details.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
<emphasis>レイヤーマスク</emphasis>:
いずれのレイヤーもマスクが付属しています。 レイヤーマスクはその
レイヤーのアルファチャンネルの代わりに透過効果を操れます。 レイヤー
マスクに描画するとレイヤーを部分的に透過させたり不透明にできます。 
黒く塗るとレイヤーが透過し、 白く塗るとレイヤーは不透明になり、 
様々な階調の灰色で塗れば半透明になります。 マスクはどんな描画ツール
を使っても塗れます。 さらにフィルタの適用や他の画像の貼り付けも可能
です。 レイヤーマスクを使えば段々と薄くなるトランジション効果や
塵や霧で立体感を表現するボリューム効果、 他からとってきた画像を
貼り付けなじませることなどいろいろ可能です。 詳しくは
<xref linkend="gimp-layer-mask"/> もご覧ください。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en"><emphasis>Channel Mask</emphasis>, also called
            <emphasis>Selection Mask</emphasis>:
            Channel Masks determine the transparency of a selection. By
            painting on a Channel Mask with white, you remove the mask and
            increase the selection; with black, you reduce the selection.
            This procedure lets you create a selection very precisely. You
            can also save your selections to a Channel Mask with the
            <link linkend="gimp-selection-to-channel">Save to Channel</link>
             command. You can retrieve it later by using the
             <quote>Channel to selection</quote> command from the
             <link linkend="gimp-channel-menu">Channel menu</link>. Channel
             masks are so important in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> that a
             special type has been implemented: the
             <link linkend="gimp-qmask">Quick mask</link>. See the
             <link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">Selection mask</link>
             section for more details.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
<emphasis>チャンネルマスク</emphasis>:
<emphasis>選択マスク</emphasis>:
チャンネルマスクは選択範囲の透過効果を定めます。 チャンネルマスクを
白く塗るとマスクは消えてゆき選択が増します。 黒く塗るにつれ選択は
減ります。 この方法なら選択範囲を極めて精緻に作成できます。 さらに 
<link linkend="gimp-selection-to-channel">チャンネルに保存</link> 
コマンドを実行すれば選択範囲をチャンネルマスクとして保存できます。 
再びとり出すにはチャンネルダイアログの 
<link linkend="gimp-channel-menu">脈絡メニュー</link> かボタンで
<guimenuitem>チャンネルを選択範囲に</guimenuitem> を実行します。 
チャンネルマスクには 
<link linkend="gimp-qmask">クイックマスク</link> という特例が実装
されているため、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のなかで重要な位置を占めて
います。 より詳しくは 
<link linkend="dialogs-selection-masks">選択マスク</link> をご覧
ください。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-moire">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Moiré Effect</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">モアレ現象</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Moiré</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>モアレ</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        The moiré effect (pronounce <quote>Moa-ray</quote>)is an unintended
        pattern which appears when a regular pattern of grids or lines
        interferes with another regular pattern placed over it. This can
        happen, for example, when you are scanning an image with a periodic
        structure (such as a checkered shirt or a half-toned image), scanning
        a digital image, taking a digital photograph of a periodic pattern,
        or even when silkscreening.
       </para>
      <para lang="en">
         If you discover the problem in time, the best solution is to move
         the original image a little bit in the scanner or to change the
         camera angle slightly.
       </para>
      <para lang="en">
         If you cannot re-create the image file, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
         offers some filters which may help you with the problem. For more
         information, see the
         <link linkend="plug-in-despeckle">Despeckle</link> and
         <link linkend="plug-in-nlfilt">NL Filter</link> (Non-Linear)
         filters.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
モアレもしくは干渉縞とは規則正しい格子縞模様や縞模様が他の整然とした
縞模様と重なり合ったときに干渉してできる予期せぬ文様のことです。 例えば
周期的な構成のある画像 (チェック柄のシャツやハーフーンを使った画像) を
スキャナで取り込んだときや、 デジタル画像をスキャンしたとき、 あるいは
規則的な文様をデジタルカメラで撮ったときやシルクスクリーンしたときに
さえも発生します。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
この問題が出てしまったらスキャナに置いた元画像を僅かにずらしたり、 
デジタルカメラのアングルをちょっとばかり変えましょう。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
元画像ファイルを作り直すわけにはいかないとき、 副作用がありますが
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>についてくるフィルタを利用する手があります。 
<link linkend="plug-in-despeckle">ノイズ除去</link> フィルタや
<link linkend="plug-in-nlfilt">非線形フィルタ</link> の説明をご覧
ください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-parasite">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Parasite</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">パラサイト</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>XCF</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>.xcf</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Parasite</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>パラサイト</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A Parasite is additional data which may be written to an XCF file. A
        parasite is identified by a name, and can be thought of as an
        extension to the other information in an XCF file.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Parasites of an image component may be read by <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        plug-ins. Plug-ins may also define their own parasite names, which are
        ignored by other plug-ins. Examples of parasites are comments, the
        save options for the TIFF, JPEG and PNG file formats, the gamma value
        the image was created with and EXIF data.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
パラサイトとは<acronym>XCF</acronym>ファイルに書き込める追加のデータの
ことです。 パラサイトは名前で識別できます。 これらは<acronym>XCF
</acronym>ファイルに収められた他の情報を拡張と考えてよいでしょう。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
画像の成分のパラサイトは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>のプラグインで読み取れ
ます。 そのようなパラサイトにはプラグインに関わる名前がつけられ、 他の
プラグインからは無視されるようになっています。 コメント文や<acronym>
TIFF</acronym>、 <acronym>JPEG</acronym>、 <acronym>PNG</acronym>の
各ファイル形式につく保存オプション、 画像が作成されたときのガンマ値、
Exifデータがプラグインの例です。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-path">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Path</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">パス</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A Path is a contour composed of straight lines, curves, or both. In
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, it is used to form the boundary of a
        selection, or to be <emphasis>stroked</emphasis> to create visible
        marks on an image. Unless a path is stroked, it is not visible when
        the image is printed and it is not saved when the image is written
        to a file (unless you use XCF format).
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        See the <link linkend="gimp-concepts-paths">Paths Concepts</link>
        and <link linkend="gimp-using-paths">Using Paths</link> sections for
        basic information on paths, and the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-path">Path Tool</link> section for
        information on how to create and edit paths. You can manage the
        paths in your image with the
        <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Paths dialog</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
パスとは直線や曲線を自在に組み合わせてできる輪郭線のことです。 
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>では選択範囲の境界線を形成したり、 画像上に
見えるかたちに <emphasis>境界線を描く</emphasis> 使い方があります。 
パスは境界線を描く処理がなければ画像の印刷物に現れることはなく、 画像を
(<acronym>XCF</acronym>形式を除く) ファイルに保存すると消えて
しまいます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-pdb">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>PDB</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        All of the functions which <acronym>GIMP</acronym> and its
        extensions make available are registered in the Procedure Database
        (PDB). Developers can look up useful programming information about
        these functions in the PDB by using the
        <link linkend="plug-in-dbbrowser">Procedure Browser</link>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>やその拡張プログラムがもつ機能は全てプロシージャ
・データベース (PDB) に登録されています。 各機能については 
<link linkend="plug-in-dbbrowser">プロシージャ・ブラウザ</link> を使えば
PDBから探し出してその有益なプログラミング用情報が得られます。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-pdf">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>PDF</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>PDF</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>PDF</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ケイシキ">形式</primary>
      <secondary>PDF</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        PDF (Portable Document Format) is a
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link> which was
        developed by Adobe to address some of the deficiencies of
        PostScript. Most importantly, PDF files tend to be much smaller than
        equivalent PostScript files. As with PostScript,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s support of the PDF format is through the
        free Ghostscript libraries.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>PDF</acronym> (Portable Document Format) とはAdobe社が
PostScriptの仕様上の欠落を充てて新たに開発した 
<link linkend="glossary-fileformat">ファイル形式</link> のことです。 
特筆すべきは<acronym>PDF</acronym>ファイルは同内容のPostScriptファイル
と比べてもっと小さな容量になりやすいことです。 PostScriptと一緒で、 
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の<acronym>PDF</acronym>形式サポートもシステムに
フリーの <productname>Ghostscript</productname> ライブラリが導入されて
いなければなりません。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-pixel">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Pixel</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">画素</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Pixel</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ガソ">画素</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A pixel is a single dot, or <quote>picture element</quote>, of an
        image. A rectangular image may be composed of thousands of pixels,
        each representing the color of the image at a given location. The
        value of a pixel typically consists of several
        <link linkend="glossary-channels">Channels</link>, such as the Red,
        Green and Blue components of its color, and sometimes its Alpha
        (transparency).
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
画素とは画像の小さなドットのことで、 ピクセルともいいます。 画像の矩形
は数千数万もの画素で成り立っており、 それぞれが画像の各位置の色を出して
います。 赤緑青の色成分や時にはアルファ (透明) を含むそれぞれの
<link linkend="glossary-channels">チャンネル</link> で画素の値が成り立
っている場合が典型的です。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-plug-in">
    <glossterm>
      <anchor id="glossary-plugin" xreflabel="Plugin"/>
      <phrase lang="en">Plugin</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">プラグイン</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Plugins</primary>
      <secondary>Definition</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>プラグイン</primary>
      <secondary sortas="ヨウゴカイセツ">用語解説</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Optional extensions for the <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Plugins are
        external programs that run under the control of the main GIMP
        application and provide specific functions on-demand. See
        <xref linkend="gimp-concepts-plugins"/> for further information.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
プラグインは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>に任意で追加できる拡張プログラム
です。 プラグインは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>アプリケーション本体の制御化
で稼動するようになっていて、 必要に応じて特定の機能を実行するために
呼び出されます。 より詳しくは
<xref linkend="gimp-concepts-plugins"/> をご覧ください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-png">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>PNG</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>PNG</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>.png</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        PNG is the acronym of <quote>Portable Network Graphic</quote>
        (pronounce <quote>ping</quote>. This recent format offers many
        advantages and a few drawbacks: it is not lossy and gives files
        more heavy than the JPEG format, but it is perfect for saving your
        images because you can save them several times without losing
        data each time (it is used for this Help). It supports True Colors
        (several millions of colors), indexed images (256 colors like GIF),
        and 256 transparency levels (while GIF supports only two levels).
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>PNG</acronym>は<quote><foreignphrase>Portable Network Graphic
</foreignphrase></quote>の略です (ピンと読むそうです)。 この最新の形式
にはつぎのような数々の利点と僅かな欠点があります。 画質の劣化がない
代わりに<acronym>JPEG</acronym>よりもファイルが大きくなりますが、 画像
を保存する用途なら何度繰り返してもデータの損失がないので最適です 
(このてびきの図画でも多用しています)。 True Colors (1677万色)、 
インデックス化カラー画像 (<acronym>GIF</acronym>と同じく256色)、
256階調の透過効果 (<acronym>GIF</acronym>なら2階調です) をサポートして
います。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-postscript">
    <glossterm>PostScript</glossterm>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>PostScript</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ケイシキ">形式</primary>
      <primary>形式</primary>
      <secondary>PostScript</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Created by Adobe, PostScript is a page description language mainly
        used by printers and other output devices. It's also an excellent way
        to distribute documents. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> does not support
        PostScript directly: it depends on a powerful free software program
        called Ghostscript.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The great power of PostScript is its ability to represent vector
        graphics—lines, curves, text, paths, etc.—in a resolution-independent
        way. PostScript is not very efficient, though, when it comes to
        representing pixel-based raster graphics. For this reason, PostScript
        is not a good format to use for saving images that are later going to
        be edited using <acronym>GIMP</acronym> or another graphics program.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
Adobe社の開発になるPostScriptとは印刷業務やプリンタなど出力デバイスの
ために使用されるページ記述言語のことです。 これも文書の配布には非常に
もってこいの規格です。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のPostScriptサポートは
直接ではなく、 Ghostscriptという強力なフリーソフトウェアプログラムに
依存しています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
PostScriptの最大の強みは直線や曲線とテキスト、 パスなどからなるベクタ
画像が解像度に左右されずに正しく描けることです。 しかしピクセルの寄り
集まりからなるラスター画像の再現は苦手です。 このためあとで<acronym>
GIMP</acronym>などの[ラスター画像系]画像処理プログラムで編集する
つもりがある画像を保存するには、 PostScriptはあまり良いファイル形式
とは言えません。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-psd">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>PSD</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>PSD</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>.psd</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>PSD</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ケイシキ">形式</primary>
      <secondary>PSD</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        PSD is Adobe Photoshop's native
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link>, and it is
        therefore comparable to <link linkend="glossary-xcf">XCF</link>
        in complexity. <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s ability to handle PSD files
        is sophisticated but limited: some
        features of PSD files are not loaded, and only older versions of PSD
        are supported. Unfortunately, Adobe has now made the Photoshop
        Software Development Kit — which includes their file format
        specifications — proprietary, and only available to a limited set of
        developers approved by Adobe. This does not include the
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        development team, and the lack of information makes it very difficult
        to maintain up-to-date support for PSD files.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>PSD</acronym>とは <productname>Adobe Photoshop</productname>
 由来の
<link linkend="glossary-fileformat">ファイル形式</link> のことで、 
その複雑さは
<link linkend="glossary-xcf">XCF</link> にひけをとりません。 <acronym>
GIMP</acronym>では洗練されたしくみで<acronym>PSD</acronym>ファイルを
扱えますが、 制限もあります。 まず<acronym>PSD</acronym>ファイルの機能
がいくつか読み込めません。 そのうえ古い版の<acronym>PSD</acronym>しか
サポートできません。 現在Adobe社はこのファイル形式の詳しい仕様説明を
含む<foreignphrase>Photoshop Software Development Kit</foreignphrase>
を作成していますが、 残念ながらこれは専有商品になっていて、 Adobe社が
認める一部の限られたソフトウェア開発者にのみ使用が許可されています。 
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の開発チームはその対象外にされていて情報が手に
入らないため、 <acronym>PSD</acronym>ファイルのサポートを最新に保つ
ことは非常に困難です。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-quantization">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Quantization</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">量子化</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Quantization</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="リョウシカ">量子化</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Quantization is the process of reducing the color of a pixel into one
        of a number of fixed values by matching the color to the nearest color
        in the colormap. Actual pixel values may have far more precision than
        the discrete levels which can be displayed by a digital display. If
        the display range is too small, then abrupt changes in colors (false
        contours, or banding) may appear where the color intensity changes
        from one level to another. This is especially noticeable in Indexed
        images, which have 256 or fewer discrete colors.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        One way to reduce quantization effects is to use
        <link linkend="glossary-dithering">Dithering</link>. The
        operations in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> which perform
        dithering are the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">Blend tool</link>
        (if you have enabled the dithering option) and the
        <link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">Convert to Indexed</link>
        command. However, they only work on RGB images and not on Indexed
        images.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
量子化とは画素の色と最も近い色をカラーマップに見付け出しその索引番号を
元の色の代わりに収めることにより使用される色数を減らす処理のことです。 
実際の画素が持つ値はデジタル画面に表示できるとびとびの階調よりはるかに
精緻です。 仮にデジタル画面の表現の幅が狭くなり過ぎると、 色の強さが
変化する部分で唐突な色変わり (輪郭線や結線のほつれ) が目立つように
なります。 これはとくに色数256色以下の離散した色の組み合わせで
インデックス化された画像に顕著に現れます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
量子化による乱れを減らす方法のひとつが
<link linkend="glossary-dithering">ディザリング</link> です。 <acronym>
GIMP</acronym>でディザリング処置ができる操作としては、 ディザリングを 
<link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">ブレンドツール</link> でオプション指定
する使い方や、 
<link linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed">インデックス化モードに変換
</link> コマンドがあります。 しかしいずれも<acronym>RGB</acronym>画像
でのみ動作し、 インデックス化された画像では使えません。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-rendering-intent">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>Rendering Intent</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Color Management</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="イロカンリ">色管理</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Rendering intents are ways of dealing with colors that are
        out-of-<xref linkend="glossary-gamut"/> colors present in the source
        space that the destination space is incapable of producing. There are
        four rendering intents defined by the ICC:
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<foreignphrase>Rendering Intent</foreignphrase> (レンダリング
インテント) とは、 元画像に含まれる色が、 再現する側のガモット 
<xref linkend="glossary-gamut"/> (再現可能な色の領域) を外れた場合の
その色の扱い方をさしています。 <acronym>ICC</acronym>が定めた4つの 
Rendering Intent はつぎのとおりです。
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">Perceptual</term>
          <term lang="ja">鮮やかさ重視</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              This rendering intent is typically used for photographic
              content. It scales one gamut to fit into the other while
              maintaining the relative position of colors.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
このレンダリングインテントならば写真からの内容に、 というのが典型的な
使い方です。 一方のガモットを他方のガモットに合うよう拡大・縮小します
が、 ガモット内での色の相対位置が変わらないようにします。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">Relative colorimetric</term>
          <term lang="ja">相対色距離</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              This rendering intent is typically used for spot colors. Colors
              that are not out of gamut are left unchanged. Colors outside the
              gamut are converted to colors with the same lightness, but
              different saturation, at the edge of the gamut.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
このレンダリングインテントの典型的な対象は集中的な色斑です。 
ガモットに入っている色はそのまま残されます。 ガモットから外れた色
は同じ輝度で彩度が異なる色をガモットの辺境部に得て、 この色が転用
されます。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">Saturation</term>
          <term lang="ja">彩度</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              This method is typically used for business graphics. The
              relative saturation of colors is mostly maintained, but
              lightning is usually changed.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
この方法はビジネス用の画像で使われるのが典型的です。 各色の彩度
の相対位置は保たれますが、 通常その明るさは変更を受けます。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">Absolute colorimetric</term>
          <term lang="ja">絶対色距離</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              This rendering intent is most often used in proofing. It
              preserves the native device white point of the source image.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
このレンダリングインテントは検証用図面によく用いられます。 
元画像の自然なデバイス白点が保持されます。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-rgb">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>RGB</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>RGB</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Additive color model</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="イロ">色</primary>
      <secondary sortas="カホウコンショクモデル">加法混色モデル</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <figure float="0">
        <title lang="en">Additive color model</title>
        <title lang="ja">加法混色モデル</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/glossary/color-model-additive.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en">
        RGB is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which has components for Red, Green and Blue. These colors are
        emitted by screen elements and not reflected as they are with paint.
        The resulting color is a combination of the three primary RGB colors,
        with different degrees of lightness. If you look closely at your
        television screen, whose pitch is less than that of a computer
        screen, you can see the red, green and blue elements lit with
        different intensities. The RGB color model is
        <emphasis>additive</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses eight bits per channel for each primary
        color. That means there are 256 intensities (Values) available,
        resulting in 256×256×256 = 16,777,216 colors.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        It is not obvious why a given combination of primary colors produces a
        particular color. Why, for instance, does 229R+205G+229B give a shade
        of pink? This depends upon the human eye and brain. There is no color
        in nature, only a continuous spectrum of wavelengths of light. There
        are three kinds of cones in the retina. The same wavelength of light
        acting upon the three types of cones stimulates each of them
        differently, and the mind has learned, after several million years of
        evolution, how to recognize a color from these differences.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        It is easy to see that no light (0R+0G+0B) produces complete darkness,
        black, and that full light (255R+255G+255B) produces white. Equal
        intensity on all color channels produces a level of gray. That is why
        there can only be 256 gray levels in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Mixing two <emphasis>Primary colors</emphasis> in RGB mode
        gives a <emphasis>Secondary color</emphasis>, that is, a
        color in the CMY model. Thus combining Red and Green gives
        Yellow, Green and Blue give Cyan, Blue and Red give Magenta.
        Don't confuse secondary colors with
        <emphasis>Complementary colors</emphasis> which are
        directly opposite a primary color in the chromatic
        circle:
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>RGB</acronym>とは赤、 緑、 青の3原色の成分からなる
<link linkend="glossary-colormodel">色モデル</link> のことです。
このような色は塗られた色から反射するのではなく画面の要素から発色され
ます。 ここで得られる色は全て3つの<acronym>RGB</acronym>原色がおのおの
明度を変えて合成された結果でできています。 もしテレビ画面を近付いて
ご覧になったら、 コンピュータの画面よりも画素の密度が粗いので、 赤、 
緑、 青の要素が別々の明るさできらめいているのが分かるはずです。
<acronym>RGB</acronym>色モデルは <emphasis>加法混色</emphasis> です。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>RGB</acronym>は各原色を任されているそれぞれのチャンネルごとに
8ビットを使います。 つまり[いずれのチャンネルも]256階調の強度がある
ので、 256 &times; 256 &times; 256 = 1677万7216色の表現力があります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
3つの原色の合成で特定の色が作れるとはいえ、 その原理はちょっと分かり
にくいものです。 例えば229R+205G+229Bがどうして淡い桃色になるの
でしょう。 答えばヒトの目と脳にあります。 色は自発的に存在するのでは
なく、 連続する光の波長のスペクトラムだけが存在します。 網膜内には3つ
の種類の角膜があります。 同じ波長の光が3層に分かれた角膜に差し込むと
それぞれ異なった刺激を受け、 数億年もの進化の歳月を経て我々が身に
つけた感覚能力でその差異から色を認識します。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
光が無い状態 (0R+0G+0B) が完全な漆黒の闇を作ることや、 光に満ちた状態
(255R+255G+255B) が白く輝くのは容易に見てとれます。 全ての色チャンネル
が等しい強度ならその程度の濃さの灰色になります。 ひいてはそのために
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>で256階調の灰色しか表現できない状態にも
なりえます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>RGB</acronym>から2色の <emphasis>原色</emphasis> を重ね合わ
せると <emphasis>2次色</emphasis> すなわち<acronym>CMY</acronym>
モデルの色が得られます。 こうした重ね合わせで赤と緑からイエローが、 
緑と青からシアンが、 青と赤からマゼンタができます。 2次色と
<emphasis>補色</emphasis> とを混同してはいけません。 補色とは下図に
示す色相環上で原色のちょうど対面にある色のことです。
      </para>
      <figure float="0">
        <title lang="en">Colorcircle</title>
        <title lang="ja">色相環</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/glossary/colorcircle.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="en">
              Mixing a primary color with its complementary color gives gray
              (a neutral color).
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
原色とその補色を混ぜ合わせると灰色 (無色) ができる。
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en">
        It is important to know what happens when you are dealing with colors
        in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
        The most important rule to remember is that decreasing the intensity
        of a primary color results in increasing the intensity of the
        complementary color (and vice versa). This is because when you
        decrease the value of a channel, for instance Green, you automatically
        increase the relative importance of the other two, here Red and Blue.
        The combination of these two channels gives the secondary color,
        Magenta, which is the complementary color of Green.
      </para>
      <para lang="en"><emphasis>Exercise</emphasis>
        : You can check this out. Create a new image with only a white
        background (255R+255G+255B). Open the
        <menuchoice moreinfo="none">
          <guimenu moreinfo="none">Tools</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu moreinfo="none">Color Tools</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Levels</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        dialog and select the Red channel. If necessary, check the preview
        box. Move the white slider to the left to decrease the Red value. You
        will notice that the background of your image gets closer and closer
        to Cyan. Now, decrease the Blue channel: only the Green will remain.
        For practice, go backwards, add a color and try to guess what hue will
        appear.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">Color Picker</link>
        tool lets you find out the RGB values of a pixel and the
        <link linkend="glossary-html-notation">hextriplet</link>
        for the color.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
肝心なのは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>で色を取り扱う際には何が行われている
のかを知っておくことです。 なかでも特に覚えておいてほしいことは、 原色
の強さを減らすとその補色の強さが増し、 またその逆もあるという大切な規則
です。 その理由はどれかのチャンネルを弱めるとその他の2つのチャンネルの
相対的な重みが増すからです。 例えば緑を減らすと赤と青が引き立ち
ますが、 その2色の混色はマゼンタという2次色で、 緑の補色なのです。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<emphasis>やってみましょう実験学習</emphasis>: まず背景が白 
(255R+255G+255B) の新しい画像を作成します。 つぎに画像ウィンドウの
メニューより
<menuchoice>
  <guimenu>ツール(<accel>T</accel>)</guimenu>
  <guisubmenu>色ツール(<accel>C</accel>)</guisubmenu>
  <guimenuitem>レベル(<accel>L</accel>)...</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice> と進んで
<link linkend="gimp-tool-levels">レベル</link> ツールのダイアログを
呼び出したら、 赤のチャンネルを選びます。 もしも <guilabel>
プレビュー(<accel>P</accel>)</guilabel> が無効になっていたらチェックを
入れてください。 入力レベルの白い三角形のスライダを左方向に移動して
赤の値を減らしてみます。 すると画像の背景色が徐々にシアンに近づいて
ゆくのがわかります。 そうしたら青のチャンネルも減らしてみましょう。 
結果的に緑だけが残るはずです。 別の実験として、 まず色を <guibutton>
リセット(<accel>R</accel>)</guilabel> してから画像に何か色を塗って
おき、 このスライダ調整でどんな色相が現れるか試してみましょう。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">スポイト</link> ツールを使うと
ポインタをかざした位置の<acronym>RGB</acronym>値や画素の色の
<link linkend="glossary-html-notation">16進数表記</link> が分かります。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-samplemerge">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Sample Merge</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">レイヤー結合色</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Sample Merged is an option you can set when you use the
        <link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">Bucket Fill</link>
        tool, the <link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">Color Picker</link>
        tool and various selection tools. It is useful when you are working on
        an image with several layers and the active layer is either
        semi-transparent or has a
        <link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">Layer Mode</link>
        which is not set to Normal. When you check the Sample Merged option,
        the color which is used for the operation is the composite color of
        all the visible layers. When the Sample Merged option is not checked,
        the color used is the color of the active layer itself.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
レイヤー結合色オプションは
<link linkend="gimp-tool-bucket-fill">塗りつぶし</link> ツールと
<link linkend="gimp-tool-color-picker">スポイト</link> ツールと幾種もの
選択ツールにあります。 これは複数のレイヤーがある画像でしかも活性
レイヤーが半透明あるいは <guimenuitem>標準</guimenuitem> 以外の
<link linkend="gimp-concepts-layer-modes">レイヤーモード</link> に指定
されている場合に役立ちます。 レイヤー結合色オプションを有効にすると、 
操作に参照される色は全ての可視レイヤーを通した合成色に求められます。 
レイヤー結合色オプションを無効にした場合には活性レイヤーの色が使われ
ます。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-saturation">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Saturation</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">彩度</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Saturation</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Saturation</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="サイド">彩度</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="イロ">色</primary>
      <secondary sortas="サイド">彩度</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        This term refers to color purity. Imagine you add pigment to white
        paint. Saturation varies from 0 (white, fully toned down, fully
        diluted) to 100 (pure color).
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
この用語は色の純度を指しています。 白の塗料を追加するところを想像
してください。 彩度の値は 0 (白、 色濃度は徹底的に下がり、 すっかり
薄くなった色) から 100 (純粋色) の範囲で変動します。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-supersampling">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Supersampling</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">スーパーサンプリング</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Supersampling</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>スーパーサンプリング</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        Supersampling is a more sophisticated antialiasing technique, that
        is, a method of reducing jagged and stair-stepped edges along a
        slanted or curved line. Samples are taken at several locations
        <emphasis>within</emphasis> each pixel, not just at the center, and
        an average color is calculated. This is done by rendering the image
        at a much higher resolution than the one being displayed and then
        shrinking it to the desired size, using the extra pixels for
        calculation. The result is a smoother transition from one line of
        pixels to another along the edges of objects.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The quality of the result depends on the number of samples.
        Supersampling is often performed at a range of 2× to 16× the original
        size. It greatly increases the amount of time needed to draw the image
        and also the amount of space needed to store the image in memory.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        One way to reduce the space and time requirement is to use Adaptive
        Supersampling. This method takes advantage of the fact that very few
        pixels are actually on an object boundary, so only those pixels need to
        be supersampled. At first, only a few samples are taken within a pixel.
        If the colors are very similar to each other, only those samples are
        used to calculate the final color. If not, more samples are used. This
        means that the higher number of samples is calculated only where
        necessary, which improves performance.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
スーパーサンプリングとは画像内に描かれた物体の輪郭が斜線や曲線のときに
発生する縁のギザギザを軽減する高度な
<link linkend="glossary-antialias">アンチエイリアス</link> 技法の
ひとつです。 各画素 <emphasis>内</emphasis> でのサンプリングはその中心
にこだわらずいろいろな位置で採色され、 それらの平均値が使われます。 
このサンプリング処理は画面の表示よりはるかに高い解像度で結果の画像を
描き出し、 計算のための追加的画素を利用しながら目的の大きさの画像に
縮小します。 そのおかげで画像内の物体の縁に並んだ画素はその隣りの画素
へとなめらかに色変化します。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
仕上りの品質はサンプル数の大小に依存します。 スーパーサンプリングは
主に元画像の2倍から16倍で処理されます。 サンプル数の大きな画像処理は、 
それに必要な処理時間もメモリ上の消費容量も格段に増えます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
容量や時間の必要量を減らす方法のひとつが適応型スーパーサンプリング
です。 この方法は物体の外縁だけなら僅かな画素しかなく、 その画素だけを
スーパーサンプリングすればよいことに着目したところが優れています。 
まず最初はひとつの画素内で少しだけサンプルを採ります。 それらが互いに
よく似た色ならばその僅かなサンプルだけを計算に利用します。 違いが認め
られたなら、 サンプル数が増やされます。 つまり必要な部分でのみサンプル
数を増やすことで処理能力を高めているのです。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-svg">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>SVG</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>SVG</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>SVG</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary>SVG</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ケイシキ">形式</primary>
      <secondary>SVG</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        SVG stands for Scalable Vector Graphics. It is a format for
        two-dimensional vector graphics, both static and animated. You can
        export GIMP paths to SVG and you can import SVG documents into GIMP
        from a vector graphic software. See
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-svg"/> for more details.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>SVG</acronym>とは <foreignphrase>Scalable Vector Graphics
</foreignphrase> の略です。 2次元ベクター画像の 
<link linkend="glossary-fileformat">ファイル形式</link> のひとつで、 
静止画とアニメーションの両方に対応しています。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
<link linkend="glossary-paths">パス</link> が<acronym>SVG</acronym>に
転換できますし、 他のベクター画像ソフトウェアで作成・処理された
<acronym>SVG</acronym>ファイルを<acronym>GIMP</acronym>に読み込むこと
もできます。 この形式についてのより詳しい情報は、 
<link linkend="bibliography-online-wkpd-svg">ウィキペディア</link>
をご覧ください。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-tga">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>TGA</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>TGA</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>TARGA</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>TGA</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ケイシキ">形式</primary>
      <secondary>TGA</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        TGA (TARGA Image File) is a
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link> which
        supports 8, 16, 24 or 32 bits per pixel and optional RLE compression.
        It was originally developed by the Truevision company.
        <quote>TGA</quote> stands for Truevision Graphics Adapter and
        <quote>TARGA</quote> stands for Truevision Advanced Raster Graphics
        Adapter.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>TGA</acronym> (<acronym>TARGA</acronym>画像アダプタ) ファイル
形式は1画素あたり8、 16、 24、 32ビットカラーのいずれかと可逆連長圧縮
がサポートされています。 この形式はトゥルービジョン社により開発され
ました。  <acronym>TGA</acronym>は <foreignphrase>Truevision Graphics
Adapter</foreignphrase> の略であり、 <acronym>TARGA</acronym>は 
<foreignphrase>Truevision Advanced Raster Graphics Adapter
</foreignphrase> の略です。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-tiff">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>TIFF</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>TIFF</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        TIFF (Tagged Image File Format) is a
        <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link> which was
        developed primarily for scanned
        raster graphics for color separation. Six different encoding routines
        are supported, each with one of three different image modes: black and
        white, grayscale and color. Uncompressed TIFF images may be 1, 4, 8 or
        24 bits per pixel. TIFF images compressed using the LZW algorithm may
        be 6, 8 or 24 bits per pixel. Besides Postscript format, TIFF is one
        of the most important formats for preliminary stages of printing. It
        is a high quality file format, which is perfect for images you want to
        import to other programs like FrameMaker or CorelDRAW.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>TIFF</acronym> (<foreignphrase>Tagged Image File Format
</foreignphrase>) とはそもそもスキャナで生成される色分け用ラスター画像
<link linkend="glossary-fileformat">ファイル形式</link> として開発
されました。 6つの異なる符号化処方が白黒2色とグレースケールとカラーの
3つの画像モードいずれにおいてもサポートされています。 画素ごとのビット
数は非圧縮<acronym>TIFF</acronym>像で1、 4、 8、 24のいずれかです。 
<acronym>LZW</acronym>アルゴリズムで圧縮された<acronym>TIFF</acronym>
画像は6、 8、 24ビット毎画素です。 <acronym>TIFF</acronym>はPostscript
形式とともに印刷の前段階で最も重要な形式のひとつです。 これは高品質の
ファイル形式で、 <application>FrameMaker</application> や
<application>CorelDRAW</application> のような他のプログラムに画像を
転用する用途には完璧な形式です。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-tile">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Tile</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">タイル</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A Tile is a part of an image which <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        currently has open. In order to avoid having to store an
        entire image in memory at the same time,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> divides it into smaller pieces.
        A tile is usually a square of 64 x 64 pixels, although tiles at
        the edges of an image may be smaller than that.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        At any time, a tile may be in main memory, in the tile cache
        in RAM, or on disk. Tiles which are currently being worked on are
        in main memory. Tiles which have been used recently are in RAM.
        When the tile cache in RAM is full, tiles which have been used
        least recently are written to disk. <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        can retrieve the tiles from RAM or disk when they are needed.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Do not confuse these tiles with those in the
        <link linkend="plug-in-tile">Tile Filter</link>
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
タイルとは現時点で<acronym>GIMP</acronym>が開いている画像の断片です。 
一気に画像を丸ごとメモリに読み込まないようにするため、 <acronym>GIMP
</acronym>は画像を小さな断片に切り分けています。 タイルは通常64 &times;
64 ピクセルの正方形をします。 外縁部でこれよりも小さくなってしまい
ますが同様の切り分けを行ないます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
タイルはメインメモリ、 <acronym>RAM</acronym>上のタイルキャッシュ、 
ディスク上のいずれかにいつも置かれています。 現時点で作業対象のタイルは
メインメモリ上に置かれます。 最近使われたタイルは<acronym>RAM</acronym>
上です。 <acronym>RAM</acronym>のタイルキャシュが満杯になると、 最も
古くに使われたタイルからディスクに移されます。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
は必要になったタイルを<acronym>RAM</acronym>やディスクから取り出し
ます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<link linkend="plug-in-tile">タイル状に並べる</link> フィルタと
混同しないようにしましょう。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-uri">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>URI</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>URI</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a string of characters that
        serves to identify an abstract or a physical resource. URIs are used
        for the identification of resources in the Internet (such as web
        pages, miscellaneous files, calling up web services, and for receivers
        of e-mail) and they are especially used in the Worldwide Web.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>URI</acronym> (<foreignphrase>Uniform Resource Identifier
</foreignphrase>: 統一資源識別子) とは抽象的もしくは物理的な資源を
示す文字列です。  <acronym>URI</acronym>はウェブページや様々なネット上
のファイルやウェブサービスの呼び出しやEメールのレシーバなどの
インターネット上の資源を指し示すために利用され、 とくに世界的なウェブ
<acronym>WWW</acronym>でよく使われています。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-url">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>URL</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>URL</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        URLs (Uniform Resource Locators) are one type of Uniform Resource
        Identifiers (URIs). URLs identify a resource by its primary access
        mechanism (commonly http or ftp) and the location of the resource in
        the computer network. The name of the URI scheme is therefore
        generally derived from the network protocol used for it. Examples of
        network protocols are http, ftp and mailto.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        Since URLs are the first and most common kinds of URIs, the terms are
        often used synonymously.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>URL</acronym> (<foreignphrase>Uniform Resource Locator
<foreignphrase>: 統一資源位置指定子) は
<link linkend="glossary-uri"><acronym>URI</acronym></link> (統一資源
識別子) の一種であると位置づけられています。 (通例httpやftpなどの) 
第一義的な接取機構にまつわる資源や、 コンピュータネットワーク上の資源の
位置情報を<acronym>URL</acronym>は指し示します。 <acronym>URI</acronym>
の枠組みに基づく名前はそれゆえ一般的には利用されるネットワーク規約から
派生したものになります。 ネットワーク規約には例えばhttpやftpやmailtoが
あります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>URL</acronym>は最初の最もありふれた<acronym>URI</acronym>で
あることから、 両者はしばしば同義語として扱われています。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-value">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase lang="en">Value</phrase>
      <phrase lang="ja">値</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Value</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Color</primary>
      <secondary>Value</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="アタイ">値</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="イロ">色</primary>
      <secondary sortas="アタイ">値</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        This term often refers to the light intensity, the luminosity of
        a color. It varies from 0 (black) to 100 (full light).
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
この用語はしばしば光の強さすなわち明度の意味で使われています。 値の範囲
は 0 (黒) から 100 (最大限の光) です。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-xcf">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>XCF</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>XCF</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>.xcf</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>.xcf.gz</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="en">
      <primary>Formats</primary>
      <secondary>XCF</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal" lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="ケイシキ">形式</primary>
      <secondary>XCF</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        XCF is a <link linkend="glossary-fileformat">file format</link>
        which is special because it is <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
        native file format: that is, it was designed specifically to store all
        of the data that goes to make up a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image.
        Because of this, XCF files may be quite complicated, and there are
        few programs other than <acronym>GIMP</acronym> that can read them.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        When an image is stored as an XCF file, the file encodes nearly
        everything there is to know about the image: the pixel data for each
        of the layers, the current selection, additional channels if there are
        any, paths if there are any, and guides. The most important thing that
        is <emphasis>not</emphasis> saved in an XCF file is the undo history.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The pixel data in an XCF file is represented
        in a lossless compressed form: the image byte blocks are compressed
        using the lossless RLE algorithm. This means that no matter how many
        times you load and save an image using this format, not a single
        pixel or other image data is lost or modified because of this format.
        XCF files can become very large, however <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        allows you to compress the files themselves, using either the gzip
        or bzip2 compression methods, both of which are fast, efficient, and
        freely available. Compressing an XCF file will often shrink it by a
        factor of 10 or more.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> developers have made a great effort to
        keep the XCF file format compatible across versions. If you create a
        file using <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.x, it ought to be possible to
        open the file in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2. However, some of the
        information in the file may not be usable: for example,
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 has a much more sophisticated way of
        handling text than <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2, so a text layer
        from a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.0 XCF file will appear as an
        ordinary image layer if the file is opened in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1.2.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>XCF</acronym>は<acronym>GIMP</acronym>由来の 
<link linkend="glossary-fileformat">ファイル形式</link> なので、 
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>画像を構成する全てのデータが保存されるよう特別に
用意されました。 このため<acronym>XCF</acronym>ファイルはすっかり
こんがらがってしまうようで、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>以外にこれを読み
こなせるプラグラムはとても少ない。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
画像を<acronym>XCF</acronym>で保存するとその画像で分かることがほとんど
何もかもデータ化されてファイルに収められます。 その対象は各レイヤーや
現在の選択範囲の画素の情報、 もしあれば追加されたチャンネルやパスや
見当線です。 ただし重要なことですが<acronym>XCF</acronym>ファイルに
操作履歴だけは保存されません。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>XCF</acronym>ファイルの画素の情報は劣化のない圧縮をかけられた
状態になります。 画像の断片ブトックは連長圧縮アルゴリズムで圧縮され
ます。 これはつまりこの形式で画像の保存と読み込みを何度繰り返しても
画像のデータは1画素でさえも失われることがないのです。 <acronym>XCF
</acronym>は非常に大きなものになりやすいファイル形式です。 <acronym>
GIMP</acronym>ではフリーで使える高速で効果的な <application>gzip
</application> や <application>bzip2</application> 圧縮方法のいずれか
をかけられた<acronym>XCF</acronym>ファイルも扱えますので、 圧縮しない
場合に比べて10分の1以下に縮められますが、 やはり大きくなって
しまいます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の開発者は<acronym>XCF</acronym>ファイル形式が
これまでの<acronym>GIMP</acronym>のさまざまな版と互換性を保てるよう、 
膨大な努力を重ねてきました。 仮に<acronym>GIMP</acronym>2以上でこの
ファイルを作成したなら、 これを<acronym>GIMP</acronym>1.2でも開け
ます。 ただしファイル内の情報がいくつかが利用できません。 例えば
<acronym>GIMP</acronym>2.0からテキストの扱いが<acronym>GIMP</acronym>
1.2よりはるかに高度になりましたので、 仮に<acronym>GIMP</acronym>2以降
でテキストを含む画像を<acronym>XCF</acronym>で保存すれば、 このファイル
は<acronym>GIMP</acronym>1.2で開くとテキストレイヤーの代わりに普通の
画像レイヤーが現れます。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-ycbcr">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>YCbCr</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>YCbCr</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        YCbCr is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which was developed for the PAL television standard as a simple
        modification to the YUV color model. In the
        meantime, it has become the CCIR-601 standard for image and video
        recording. For example, it is used for JPEG pictures and MPEG videos,
        and therefore also on DVDs, video CDs and for most other widespread
        digital video standards. Note that a color model is still not a color
        space, since it doesn't determine which colors are actually meant by
        <quote>red</quote>, <quote>green</quote> and <quote>blue</quote>.
        For a color space, there must still be a reference to a specific
        absolute color value.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        There are color models which do not express a color by the additive
        basic colors, red, green and blue (RGB), but by other properties, for
        example, the brightness-color model. Here, the criteria are the basic
        brightness of the colors (from black, through gray, to white), the
        colors with the largest portion (red, orange, yellow, green, blue,
        violet, or other pure colors that lie between them) and the saturation
        of the colors (<quote>gaudy</quote> to pale). This color model is
        based on the
        ability of the eye to recognize small differences in luminosity
        better than small color differences, and to recognize those better
        than small differences in saturation. That makes gray text written on
        a black background easy to read, but blue text on a red background
        very hard to read, even with the same basic brightness. Such color
        models are called brightness-color models.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The YCbCr model is a slight adaptation of such a brightness-color
        model. An RGB color value is divided into a basic brightness, Y, and
        two components, Cb and Cr, where Cb is a measurement of the deviation
        from gray in the blue direction, or if it is less than 0.5, in the
        direction of yellow. Cr is the corresponding measurement for the
        difference in the direction of red or turquoise. This representation
        uses the peculiarity of the eye of being especially sensitive to green
        light. That is why most of the information about the proportion of
        green is in the basic brightness, Y, an only the deviations for the
        red and blue portions need to be represented. The Y values have twice
        the resolution of the other two values, Cb and Cr, in most practical
        applications, such as on DVDs.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
YCbCrとはテレビ用の標準信号の<acronym>PAL</acronym>規格のために開発され
たもので、 <acronym>YUV</acronym>色モデルの単純な変形です。 一方でこの
信号規格は画像と映像の標準規格<acronym>CCIR</acronym>-601 (<acronym>
CCIR</acronym>は国際電気通信連合無線通信部門の前身) になりました。 
例えば<acronym>JPEG</acronym>画像や<acronym>MPEG</acronym>映像に、 また
それゆえ<acronym>DVD</acronym>ビデオやビデオ<acronym>CD</acronym>など
よく使われるデジタルビデオ標準規格で使われています。 ちなみに
<link linkend="glossary-colormodel">色モデル</link> は<quote>赤
</quote>、 <quote>緑</quote>、 <quote>青</quote>の3原色がどのような色を
指し示しているかを明確には定義していないため色空間とはなりえません。 
色空間においては特定の絶対的な色の値が示されています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
色モデルは必ずしも赤緑青 (<acronym>RGB</acronym>) の3原色を加法混色して
色を表現するものだけではありません。 例えば<quote>明るさ-色<quote>
モデルのように他の属性で表現するモデルもあります。 その判断基準は、 
色の輝度 (黒から灰色を経て白へ)、 最大のまとまりがある色 (赤、 
オレンジ、 イエロー、 緑、 青、 紫やその間にある純粋な色)、 色の彩度 
(けばけばしい色から淡く薄い色まで) といった属性です。 この色モデルは
ヒトの目が僅かな色の違いや彩度の違いよりも僅かな明るさの違いをより強く
認識できる能力に基づいています。 このことは灰色の文字の背景が黒くても
読めるのに対し、 青い文字と赤い背景の場合は同じ明るさにしていても非常に
読み取りづらくなることに現れています。 このような色モデルを<quote>
明るさ-色<quote>モデルと言うのです。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
YCbCrモデルはそのような<quote>明るさ-色</quote>モデルにちょっとばかり
手を加えたものです。 <acronym>RGB</acronym>の色の値は、 基本の明るさY
と2つの成分Cb、 Crに分解されます。 Cbは青の方向に灰色陰影からの差を得て
もし0.5より小さければイエローの方向で差を得ます。 Crは赤もしくは青緑色
への方向で同様な差を得ます。 このとらえ方はヒトの目が特に緑の光に敏感
な特性を生かしています。 このような理由から、 緑の配分に関する情報は
基本の明るさYと、 表現に必要な赤と青部分の差だけになっています。 Yの値
は<acronym>DVD</acronym>[ビデオプレーヤ]のようなほとんどの実用的な
アプリケーションではCbとCrの2つの他の値よりも解像度が2倍です。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="glossary-yuv">
    <glossterm>
      <phrase>YUV</phrase>
    </glossterm>
    <indexterm significance="normal">
      <primary>YUV</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para lang="en">
        YUV is a <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">color model</link>
        which uses two components to represent the color
        information, luma (the strength of the light per area) and the
        chrominance, or proportion of color (chroma), where the chrominance
        again consists of two components. The development of the YUV color
        model also goes back to the development of color television (PAL),
        where ways were sought for transmitting the color information
        along with the black-and-white signal, in order to achieve backwards
        compatibility with old black and white televisions without having to
        increase the available transmission bandwidth. From the YUV color
        model of the analog television techiques, the YCrCb color model was
        developed, which is used for most kinds of digital image and video
        compression. Erroneously, the YUV color model is also often spoken
        about in those fields, although the YCbCr model is actually used.
        This often causes confusion.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        For the calculation of the luma signals, the underlying RGB data is
        first adjusted with the <link linkend="glossary-gamma">gamma</link>
        value of the output device, and an R'G'B' signal is obtained. The
        three individual components are added together with different
        weights, to form the brightness information, which also functions as
        the VBS signal (Video Baseband Signal, the black-and-white signal)
        for the old black and white televisions.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">Y=R+G+B</para>
      <para lang="en">
        The exact calculation is more complicated, however, since some aspects
        of the color perception of the human eye have to be taken into
        account. For example, green is perceived to be lighter than red, and
        this is perceived to be lighter than blue. Furthermore, in some
        systems gamma correction of the basic color is first performed.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        The chrominance signals, and the color difference signals also,
        contain the color information. They are formed by the difference of
        blue minus luma or red minus luma.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">U=B-Y</para>
      <para lang="en">V=R-Y</para>
      <para lang="en">
        From the three generated components, Y, U and V, the individual
        color proportions of the basic color can be calculated again later:
      </para>
      <para lang="en">Y + U = Y + ( B - Y ) = Y - Y + B = B</para>
      <para lang="en">Y + V = Y + ( R - Y ) = Y - Y + R = R</para>
      <para lang="en">Y - B - R = ( R + G + B ) - B - R = G</para>
      <para lang="en">
        Furthermore, because of the structure of the retina of the human
        eye, it turns out that the brightness information is perceived at a
        higher resolution than the color, so that many formats based on
        the YUV color model compress the chrominance to save bandwidth
        during transmission.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
<acronym>YUV</acronym>は色の情報を表すのに2つの成分を用いる 
<link linkend="glossary-colormodel">色モデル</link> です。 luma
(領域ごとの光の強さ) とchroma (クロミナンスつまり色質) とに分かれ、 
クロミナンスはさらに2つに分解できます。 <acronym>YUV</acronym>色
モデルの発展もカラーテレビ (<acronym>PAL</acronym>) の開発に遡り
ます。 当時は白黒テレビとの互換性を保ちつつテレビの信号帯域を
増やさずに白黒用信号と一緒にカラー信号を送れるようにする意図が
ありました。 アナログテレビ放送の<acronym>YUV</acronym>色モデル
からYCbCr色モデルが開発され、 ほとんどのデジタル画像や映像圧縮に
利用されています。  実際はYCbCrモデルが使わているにもかかわらず
しばしば誤用でこの分野が<acronym>YUV</acronym>色モデルで語られて
しまうことがあり、 混乱を招いています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
luma信号の算出の際には、 根底にある<acronym>RGB</acronym>データが
まず出力デバイスの 
<link linkend="glossary-gamma">ガンマ</link> 値で調整されてから
R'G'B'の各信号値を得ます。 3つの個々の成分が異なる比率で足し合わ
され、 かつての白黒テレビに使われた<acronym>VBS</acronym> (
<foreignphrase>Video BaseBand Signal</foreignphrase>, 白黒信号)
のようにも機能する輝度情報の形になります。
      </para>
      <para lang="en">Y=R+G+B</para>
      <para lang="ja">
しかし実際はヒトの目の色覚のさまざまな特徴を考慮する必要がある
ため、 正確な計算方法はもっと複雑です。 例えば緑は赤よりも明るく
感じられ、 青りも明るく感じられます。 さらにシステムによっては
基本色のガンマ補正がさいしょ に行われます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
クロミナンス信号と色差信号も色情報を含んでいます。 これらは青
からlumaを減じたり赤からlumaを減じた形です。
      </para>
      <para lang="en">U=B-Y</para>
      <para lang="en">V=R-Y</para>
      <para lang="ja">
生成された<acronym>YUV</acronym>の3つの成分から、 つぎのように
基本色の個々の色質がつづいて算出できます。
      </para>
      <para lang="en">Y + U = Y + ( B - Y ) = Y - Y + B = B</para>
      <para lang="en">Y + V = Y + ( R - Y ) = Y - Y + R = R</para>
      <para lang="en">Y - B - R = ( R + G + B ) - B - R = G</para>
      <para lang="ja">
なお、 ヒトの目の網膜の構造上、 輝度情報が色より高い解像度で知覚
されることが分かります。 そのため<acronym>YUV</acronym>色モデルに
基づく大多数の形式が転送に要する帯域を節約するためクロミナンスを
圧縮しています。
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossary>
