<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2012-03-18 j.h: update to v2.7
  2009-07-09 ude: added scroll wheel tip (#585823),
                  fixed "entering special chars" (#589532)
  2009-03-09 j.h: updated to v2.6
  2008-01-05 j.h: updated to v2.4.
  2006-07-03 lexa: enhanced docbook compliance
  2006-06-17 added note for special characters by j.h
  2005-12-07 replaced <simplesect> by <sect3> by lexa
  2005-12-06 replaced informalfigure by figure by lexa
  -->
<!--2012-06-13-->
<sect2 id="gimp-tool-text">
  <title lang="en">Text</title>
  <title lang="ja">テキスト</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Tools</primary>
    <secondary>Text</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Text</primary>
    <secondary>Tool</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ツール</primary>
    <secondary>テキスト</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>テキスト</primary>
    <secondary>ツール</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">The Text tool in Toolbox</title>
    <title lang="ja">
      ツールボックス上の<quote>テキスト</quote>ツールアイコン
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/toolbox-text.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">
    The Text tool places text into an image. With <acronym>GIMP-2.8</acronym>,
    you can write your text directly on the canvas. No Text Editor is needed
    anymore (although you can still use it if you want by checking the
    <guilabel>Use editor</guilabel> option in the Tool Options dialog. A text
    toolbar has been added which allows you to edit text in different ways but
    you can still go on using the <emphasis>Text Option dialog</emphasis>, to
    change the font, color and size of your text, and justify it,
    interactively. Right clicking on the frame opens a context menu that allows
    you to copy, cut, paste, load a text...
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    As soon as you type your text, it appears on the canvas in a rectangular
    frame. If you draw the rectangular frame first, the text is automatically
    adapted to the frame size. You can enlarge this frame as you do with
    rectangular selections.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    テキストツールは画像内に文字や語句を置くために使います。
    <application><acronym>GIMP</acronym>&nbsp;2.8</application> では画像に
    文字を直接書き込めます。 テキストエディターはもう必要なくなりました
    (とはいえツールオプションダイアログの
    <guilabel>エディターウィンドウで編集</guilabel> を有効にすればウィンドウ
    からも記入できます)。 テキストツールバーができたのでここからも操作が可能に
    なりましたが従来どおり<quote>テキストオプションダイアログ</quote>を使って
    相互対話的に文字のフォントを換えたり色や大きさを設定したり、 調整したりも
    できます。 画像上の文字枠を <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> で
    クリックすると脈絡メニューが出てきますのでここからでもテキストを
    <quote>コピー</quote>、 <quote>貼り付け</quote>、 <quote>読み込み</quote>
    などができます。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    文字を打ち込むとすぐさまその文字が画像上に矩形の枠で囲まれて出現します。
    先に矩形の枠を描けば、 書き込んだ文字は枠の大きさに合わせて自動適合します。
    枠は選択範囲の枠と同じ方法で拡大できます。
  </para>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="images/using/text-tool.png"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <para lang="en">
    To move the text on canvas, you have to select the Move tool and click
    on a character to drag the frame and its text.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    画像上の文字を移動するには、 移動ツールを呼び出してから、 文字の筆画を
    クリックして枠とテキストごと曳きます。
  </para>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Activate the Tool</title>
    <title lang="ja">呼び出し方</title>
    <para lang="en">
      You can access this tool in several ways:
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <quote>テキスト</quote>ツールを起用する方法はつぎのいずれかです。
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          In the image menu through
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>T</accel>ools</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Te<accel>x</accel>t</guisubmenu>
            </menuchoice>,
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像ウィンドウのメニューより
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>ツール</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>テキスト</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          by clicking the tool icon
          <guiicon>
            <inlinegraphic
                fileref="images/toolbox/stock-tool-text-22.png"/>
          </guiicon>
          in Toolbox,
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          ツールボックスのツールアイコン
          <guiicon>
            <inlinegraphic
                fileref="images/toolbox/stock-tool-text-22.png"/>
          </guiicon>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          or by using the <keycap>T</keycap> keyboard shortcut.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          キーボードショートカット <keycap>T</keycap>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title lang="en">Options</title>
    <title lang="ja">オプション</title>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Text tool options</title>
      <title lang="ja"><quote>テキスト</quote>ツールのツールオプション</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/tool-options-text.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <xi:include href="about-common-options-display.xml"/>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Font</term>
        <term lang="ja">フォント</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Click on the fonts button <guibutton>A&alpha;</guibutton> to open
            the font selector of this tool, which offers you a list of
            installed X fonts.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            フォントボタン <guibutton>永</guibutton> をクリックすると簡易型
            フォント選択ウィンドウが開きます。 ここからシステムにインストール
            されているフォントや、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の
            フォントディレクトリーに追加したフォントが選べます。
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <para lang="en">
              At the bottom of the font selector you find some icons which
              act as buttons for:
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              フォント選択ウィンドウの底部のアイコンボタンでつぎの操作が
              できます。
            </para>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">resizing the font previews,</para>
              <para lang="ja">フォント見本の大きさ変更</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                selecting <emphasis>list view</emphasis> or <emphasis>grid
                view</emphasis>,
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                <emphasis>リストで表示</emphasis> か 
                <emphasis>グリッドで表示</emphasis> かを選択
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                opening the <link linkend="gimp-font-dialog">font
                dialog</link>.
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                <link linkend="gimp-font-dialog">フォントダイアログ</link> を
                開く
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para lang="en">
            Choose a font from the installed fonts. When you select a font it
            is interactively applied to your text.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            インストールされているフォントからいずれかを選択します。 テキスト
            レイヤーを活性化してからフォントを変更すると直ちに画像にもその
            フォントが適用されます。
          </para>
          <tip>
            <!--cf. bug #585823 (2009-06-15)-->
            <para lang="en">
              You can use the scroll wheel of your pointing device (usually
              your mouse) on the fonts button in order to quickly change the
              font of your text (move the pointer on the fonts button, and
              don't click, just use the wheel button).
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              ポインティングデバイス (マウスなど) についているスクロール
              ホイールをフォントボタン上で回すとテキストに使われている
              フォントを素早く変更できます。 この操作ではクリックする
              必要はなく、 マウスホイールだけを使用します。
            </para>
          </tip>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Size</term>
        <term lang="ja">サイズ</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This control sets the size of the font in any of several
            selectable units.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            ここでフォントの大きさを調節できます。
            単位も数種類から利用できます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Use editor</term>
        <term lang="ja">エディターウィンドウで編集</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Use an external editor window for text editing instead of
            direct-on-canvas editing.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            画像に直接書き込み編集するのではなく画像ウィンドウの外に
            エディターウィンドウを開いてそこでテキストを編集します。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Antialiasing</term>
        <term lang="ja">なめらかに</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Antialiasing will render the text with much smoother edges and
            curves. This is achieved by slight blurring and merging of the
            edges. This option can radically improve the visual appearance of
            the rendered typeface. Caution should be exercised when using
            antialiasing on images that are not in RGB color space.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            アンチエイリアス処理は文字の筆画の縁や曲線をより滑らかに描きます。
            そのために縁の線をわずかにぼかしたりまとめたりしています。 この
            オプションは書体の描画表現を視覚的に向上させることが可能です。
            ただし非<acronym>RGB</acronym>色空間でアンチエイリアスを使用
            するには経験を積む必要がありますのでご注意ください。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Hinting</term>
        <term lang="ja">ヒンティング</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Uses the index of adjustment of the font to modify the characters in
            order to produce clear letters in small font sizes.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            小さな文字がつぶれたり歪んだりするのを防ぐ補正情報を利用します。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Color</term>
        <term lang="ja">色</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Color of the text that will be drawn next. Defaults to black.
            Selectable from the color picker dialog box that opens when the
            current color sample is clicked.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            これから書く文字の色をあらかじめ指定します。 既定の色は黒です。 
            この色ボタンをクリックすると現れる<quote>文字色</quote>ダイアログで
            色を指定できます。
          </para>
          </para>
          <tip>
            <para lang="en">
              You can also click-and-drag the color from the Toolbox color
              area onto the text.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              ツールボックスの色標識をクリックしてテキストレイヤー上まで曳いて
              きて直接放っても文字色を変更できます。
            </para>
            <para lang="en">
              You can use a gradient or a pattern to embellish your text.
              Before changing color of a text, set <guilabel>Lock:</guilabel>
              at Layer Dialog, so that text face is filled but
              transparent area around the text is kept.  Then apply colors
              by gradient or fill with a pattern.  Although this layer will
              enclose the specificity as a text layer temporally, you can
              edit this text again by clicking this layer,
              and this text will colored with the foreground color.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              グラデーションやパターンを使って着色するときはレイヤーダイアログで
              <guilabel>透明保護</guilabel> を有効にしてから行なってください。
              ただしこのときからテキストレイヤーとしての属性が一時的に
              失われます。 この文字列はテキストツールでクリックすれば再び編集
              できますが、 そのときは文字色が描画色一色に戻されます。
            </para>
          </tip>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Justify</term>
        <term lang="ja">揃え位置</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Justify</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary sortas="ソロエイチ">揃え位置</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            Causes the text to be justified according to any of four rules
            selectable from the associated icons.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <quote>左揃え</quote>、 <quote>右揃え</quote>、 
            <quote>中央揃え</quote>、 <quote>両端揃え</quote>の 4 つの
            ボタンから文字列の揃え方を選びます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Indent</term>
        <term lang="ja">インデント</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Indent</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>インデント</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary sortas="ジサゲ">字下げ</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            Controls the indent spacing from the left margin, for the first
            line.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            一行目の字下げの幅を指定します。 単位はピクセルです。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Line Spacing</term>
        <term lang="ja">行間隔</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Line spacing</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary sortas="ギョウカンカク">行間隔</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            Controls the spacing between successive lines of text. This
            setting is interactive: it appears at the same time in image text.
            The number is not the space between lines itself, but how many
            pixels must be added to or subtracted from this space (the value
            can be negative).
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            複数行の文章の行間の幅を調節します。 単位はピクセルです。 変更は
            即座に画像のテキストレイヤーに反映します。 行送り間隔ではないので
            既定値は 0.0 です。 さらに近づけるには負の値を用います。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Letter Spacing</term>
        <term lang="ja">文字間隔</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Controls the spacing between letters. Also in this case the number
            is not the space itself between letters, but how many pixels must
            be added to or subtracted from this space (the value can be
            negative).
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            文字と文字の間の幅を調節します。 これも文字幅ではないので既定値は
            0.0 です。 文字を重ねるようにするには負の値が必要でしょう。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Box</term>
        <term lang="ja">テキストボックス</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Concerns the text box. The associated drop down list offers two
            options:
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            <emphasis role="bold">Dynamic</emphasis>: default option. The size
            of the text box increases as you type. Text may go out of the
            image. You have to press the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key to add a
            new line. The indent option indents all lines. If you increase the
            box size, the option turns to "Fixed".
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            <emphasis role="bold">Fixed</emphasis>: you must enlarge the text
            box first. Else, usual shortcuts are active! The text is limited
            by the right side of the box and continues on next line. This is
            not true new line: you must press the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key
            to add a real new line. The text may go out the lower border of the
            image. The indent option works on the first line only.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            テキストボックス (文字枠) にまつわるオプションです。 付随する
            引き出しメニューで 2 つのオプションから選びます。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <guimenuitem>流動的</guimenuitem>: これがデフォルトです。
            テキストボックスの大きさは記入した文字の数に応じて拡大します。
            場合によっては画像からはみ出るかもしれません。 行を増やすには
            <keycap>Enter</keycap> キーを押します。 インデントオプションは
            全部の行を字下げします。 テキストボックスの大きさを増すとこの
            オプションは<quote>固定</quote>に切り替わります。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <guimenuitem>固定</guimenuitem>: まず先にテキストボックスを
            拡げてやらねばなりません。 そのかわりいつものショートカットが
            健在です。 テキストはテキストボックスの横幅に遮られ次の行へ
            折り返します。 これは本来の新しい行ではありません。 改行するには
            <keycap>Enter</keycap> キーを押す必要があります。 文が画像の下辺を
            越えるかもしれません。 インデントオプションは最初の行だけを
            字下げします。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>      
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="text-tool-popup">
    <title lang="en">The Text tool context menu</title>
    <title lang="ja">テキストツールの脈絡メニュー</title>
    <para lang="en">
      You get this menu by right clicking in a text frame with handles.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ハンドルつきテキスト枠を <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> で
      クリックするとこのメニューが現れます。
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          <guilabel>Cut, Copy, Paste, Delete</guilabel>: these options concern
          a selected text. They remain grayed out as long as no text is
          selected. <quote>Paste</quote> is activated if the clipboard
          is full of text.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <guilabel>切り取り</guilabel> <guilabel>写し取り</guilabel>
          <guilabel>貼り付け</guilabel> <guilabel>削除</guilabel>:
          これらのオプションは選択してある文字に作用します。 選択されている
          文字がないときはいずれも灰色無効の表示になります。
          <guilabel>貼り付け</guilabel> はクリップボードの中身が文や語句の
          ときに利用できます。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          <guilabel>Open text file</guilabel>: this command opens a file browser
          where you can find the wanted text file.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <guilabel>テキストファイルを開く</guilabel>: このコマンドは
          ファイルブラウザーを開きますので目当てのファイルを探し出しましょう。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          <guilabel>Clear</guilabel>: this command deletes all the text,
          selected or not.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <guilabel>消去</guilabel>: このコマンドはそのレイヤー内の文字を
          選択のあるなしにかかわらず全部消去します。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          <guilabel>Path from text</guilabel>: this command creates a
          path from the outlines of the current text. The result is not
          evident. You have to open the Path dialog and make path visible.
          Then select the Path tool and click on the text. Every letter
          is  now surrounded with a path component. So you can modify
          the shape of letters by moving path control points.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          This command is similar to
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Layer</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Text to Path</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <guilabel>テキストからパスを作成</guilabel>: このコマンドは現在の
          テキストの文字の輪郭をもとにパスを作成します。 しかしその結果は
          すぐには解りません。 キャンバスで表示するにはパスダイアログを開いて、 
          できたパスを可視状態に切り替える必要があります。 そのあとパスツールを
          呼び出してから文字をクリックします。 すべての文字や記号がパス成分で
          囲まれている様子が見られます。 つまりこのあとパスの
          コントロールポイントを操作すれば文字の形が加工できるのです。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          このコマンドは画像ウィンドウのメニューの
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>レイヤー</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>テキストをパスに</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>
          と同じものです。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          <guilabel>Text along path</guilabel>:
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Text along Path</primary>
          </indexterm>
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          This option is enabled only if a
          <link linkend="gimp-using-paths">path</link> exists. When your
          text is created, then create or import a path and make it active.
          If you create your path before the text, the path becomes
          invisible and you have to make it visible in the Path Dialog.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          This command is also available from the <quote>Layer</quote> menu:
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <guilabel>パスに沿ってテキストを変形</guilabel>:
          <indexterm>
            <primary sortas="パスニソッテテキストヲヘンケイ">
              パスに沿ってテキストを変形
            </primary>
          </indexterm>
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          このオプションは
          <link linkend="gimp-using-paths">パス</link> があるときだけ利用
          可能です。 文字を収めたテキストレイヤーを作ったら、 パスを作成するか
          もしくはインポートで生成してからそれを活性化します。 もし既に作った
          パスを利用する場合は不可視になっていることが多いのでパスダイアログで
          可視化します。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          このコマンドも同じものが <guimenu>レイヤー</guimenu> メニューに
          あります。
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title lang="en">
            The Text along Path command among text commands in the Layer menu
          </title>
          <title lang="ja">
            <guimenuitem>パスに沿ってテキストを変形</guimenuitem> は
            レイヤーメニューのテキスト用コマンドのひとつ
          </title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/menus/layer/text-commands.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para lang="en">
                This group of options appears only if a layer text exists.
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                これらテキスト用コマンドの一群はテキストレイヤーが画像に
                あるときだけ現れる。
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para lang="en">
          If you want to use a text that already exists, make it active
          in the <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">Layer dialog</link>,
          select the Text tool and click on the text in the image window.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          Click on the <guibutton>Text along Path</guibutton> button. The
          text is bent along the path. Letters are represented with their
          outline. Each of them is a component of the new path that
          appears in the <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">Path
          dialog</link>. All path options should apply to this new path.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          もし既に書かれているテキストを利用するのなら、
          <link linkend="gimp-layer-dialog">レイヤーダイアログ</link> にて
          そのテキストレイヤーを活性化します。 つづいてテキストツールを
          呼び出してから画像ウィンドウのテキストをクリックします。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          ツールオプションの <guibutton>パスに沿ってテキストを変形</guibutton> 
          ボタンをクリックします。 するとテキストはパスに沿ってうねるように
          綴られます。 それぞれの文字は輪郭だけが描かれています。 これらは
          新たなパスの成分になっていて、 
          <link linkend="gimp-path-dialog">パスダイアログ</link> でも確認でき
          ます。 パスに適用できるオプションはすべてこのパスにも適用できます。
        </para>
        <figure>
          <title lang="en"><quote>Text along Path</quote> example</title>
          <title lang="ja"><quote>パスに沿ってテキストを変形</quote>の例</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/text-along-path.png"
              format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/toolbox/text-path.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          <guilabel>From Left to Right / From Right to Left</guilabel>: fix
          the writing direction of your language.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          左から右への書式<quote>LTR</quote>と右から左への書式
          <quote>RTL</quote>: 使う言語の文字綴り方向をここで指定します。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-text-editor-dialog">
    <title lang="en">Text Editor</title>
    <title lang="ja">テキストエディター</title>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Text</primary>
      <secondary>Editor</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary>テキスト</primary>
      <secondary>エディター</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary sortas="モジ">文字</primary>
      <secondary sortas="ヘンシュウ">編集</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">The Text Editor</title>
      <title lang="ja">テキストエディターダイアログ</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/toolbox/tool-dialog-text.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para lang="en">
      With <acronym>GIMP-2.8</acronym>, this text editor is available only if
      the <guilabel>Use editor</guilabel> option is checked. It persists
      probably because all its functions are not transferred to the
      direct-on-canvas mode, for instance the Unicode characters.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      You can correct the text you are writing and you can change the text
      font with the Font Editor.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      As soon as you start writing, a Text layer is created in the Layer
      Dialog. On an image with such a layer (the image you are working on, or
      a <filename class="extension">.xcf</filename> image), you can resume
      text editing by activating this text layer then clicking on it (double
      click). Of course, you can apply to this text layer the same functions
      you use with other layers.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      To add another text to your image click on a non-text layer: a new Text
      Editor will appear and a new text layer will be created. To pass from a
      text to another one activate the corresponding text layer and click on
      it to activate the editor.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      このテキストエディターは
      <application><acronym>GIMP</acronym>&nbsp;2.8</application> 以降
      <guilabel>エディターウィンドウで編集</guilabel> オプションを有効にした
      ときだけ使えるようになりました。 撤廃されない理由はおそらくユニコード入力
      のような一部の機能がまだ<quote>画像に直接記入</quote>モードに移植されて
      いないからだと考えられます。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      テキストレイヤーに書き込まれた文はフォントエディターを通じていつでも
      書体が変更できます。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      語句や文章を書き込み始めるとすぐにレイヤーダイアログにテキストレイヤー
      が現れます。 こんなふうにレイヤーがある画像 (今実践されているのなら
      その画像、 あるいは <filename class="extension">.xcf</filename> 
      画像) ならば、 テキストレイヤーを活性化してテキスト上でクリック (もしくは
      ダブルクリック) すればテキスト編集を再開できます。 もちろん他の一般の
      レイヤーと同じように様々な機能を使ってテキストレイヤーを操作できます。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      他に新たなテキストを画像に貼り付けたいときはテキストレイヤーのない領域を
      クリックしてください。 新たなテキストエディターが現れるとともに新しい
      テキストレイヤーが画像に加わります。 どれかのテキストを扱っていたあとで
      他のテキストの編集を行ないたい場合は、 そのテキストレイヤーを活性化した
      うえでテキストの枠内をクリックしてテキストエディターを開きます。
    </para>
    <!--cf. bug #580532 (2009-06-15)-->
    <para lang="en">
      You can get Unicode characters with
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>U</keycap>
      </keycombo>
      plus hexadecimal Unicode code of the desired char, for example:
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ユニコードで文字をコード入力するには、 キーボードショートカット
      <keycombo>
        <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>U</keycap>
      </keycombo>
      を押してから引き出したい文字のコード番号を 16 進数で打鍵します。 例えば、 
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Entering Unicode characters</title>
      <title lang="ja">ユニコードで文字入力</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/enter-unicode-char1.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <keycap>Shift</keycap>
              <keycap>U</keycap>
            </keycombo>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/enter-unicode-char2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <keycombo action="seq">
              <keycap>4</keycap><keycap>7</keycap>
            </keycombo>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/enter-unicode-char3.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            <keycap>Enter</keycap>
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para lang="en">
      Of course this feature is more useful for entering special (even exotic)
      characters, provided that the required glyphs for these characters are
      supplied by the selected font &mdash; only few fonts support Klingon.
      ;-)
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ここではアルファベット入力の例でしたが、 もちろん特殊な文字も (外国語の
      文字も) 引き出せます。 ただしその文字が入っているフォントを選択している
      場合に限ります。 クリンゴン語用の書体を収めたフォントはなかなかないです
      から。
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/using/enter-unicode-char4.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          Unicode 0x47 (<quote>G</quote>), 0x2665, 0x0271, 0x03C0
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <variablelist>
      <title lang="en">The Text Editor options</title>
      <title lang="ja">テキストエディターのオプション</title>
      <varlistentry>
      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Text</primary>
        <secondary>Load from file</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="ja">
        <primary>テキスト</primary>
        <secondary sortas="ファイルカラヨミコミ">
          ファイルから読み込み
        </secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinegraphic fileref="images/dialogs/stock-fileopen-16.png"/>
          </guiicon>
          <phrase condition="tag-is-required" lang="en">
            Load text from file
          </phrase>
          <phrase condition="tag-is-required" lang="ja">
            ファイルからテキストを読み込む
          </phrase>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Text can be loaded from a text file by clicking the folder icon in
            the text editor. All the text in the file is loaded.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            テキストはテキストファイルの内容を利用できます。 テキストエディター
            にあるこのボタンをクリックして<quote>テキストファイル (UTF-8) 
            を開く</quote> ダイアログからファイルを選んでください。 
            ファイル内のすべてのテキストが読み込まれます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guiicon>
            <inlinegraphic fileref="images/dialogs/stock-edit-clear-16.png"/>
          </guiicon>
          <phrase condition="tag-is-required" lang="en">Clear all text</phrase>
          <phrase condition="tag-is-required" lang="ja">文面を消去</phrase>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Clicking this icon clears the editor and the associated text on
            the image.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このボタンをクリックするとテキストエディター内の
            すべての文字と画像上の連関したテキストレイヤーの文字が消えます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">From left to right</term>
        <term lang="ja">左から右への書式 <guilabel>LTR</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This option causes text to be entered from left to right, as
            is the case with most Western languages and may Eastern
            languages.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このオプションは左からはじまって右方向に書き連ねられるテキスト
            のためのもので、 ほとんどの西洋諸語や東洋の一部の言語に適用
            されます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">From right to left</term>
        <term lang="ja">右から左への書式 <guilabel>RTL</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This option allows text to be entered from right to left, as is
            the case with some Eastern languages, such as Arabic (illustrated
            in the icon).
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このオプションは右からはじまって左方向に書き連ねられるテキスト
            のためのもので、 (アイコンにも示されているように) アラビア語の
            ような東洋の一部の言語に適用されます。
          </para>
          <note lang="ja">
            <para lang="en">
              Unfortunately, on the current versions the text tool does not
              allow to align text vertically.  Though, some scripts or
              plug-ins which can do this are available at elsewhere.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              現在のところテキストツールは縦書きには対応していません。 
              代わりにプラグインやスクリプトで実現可能です。 配布されている
              サイトをお探しください。
            </para>
          <note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Use Selected font</term>
        <term lang="ja">アクティブなフォントで表示</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Default doesn't use the font you have selected in the Options
            dialog. If you want to use it, check this option.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            既定ではオプションダイアログで指定している書体をこのエディター上
            では使用しません。 使用するにはこのオプションにチェックを入れます。
          </para>
          <note>
            <para lang="en">See also <xref linkend="gimp-using-text"/>.</para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <xref linkend="gimp-using-text"/> もご覧ください。
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
