<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2009-08-25 ude: updated again due to the recent Bugzilla upgrade
  2009-06-25 ude: updated (incl. new screenshots)
  2006-10-21 lexa: added german translation
  2006-02-27 no added by kolbjoern stuestoel
  2005-12-12 moved to the appendix and made it valid docbook by lexa
-->
<!--2009-10-03-->
<appendix id="gimp-introduction-bugs">
  <title lang="en">Reporting Bugs and Requesting Enhancements</title>
  <title lang="ja">バグ報告や改善要求のしかた</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>Bugs</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Bugs</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>バグ</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>バグ</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    Sad to say, no version of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    has yet been absolutely perfect. Even sadder, it is likely that no version
    ever will be. In spite of all efforts to make everything work, a program
    as complicated as <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    is bound to screw things up occasionally, or even crash.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    But the fact that bugs are unavoidable does not mean that they should be
    passively accepted. If you find a bug in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, the
    developers would like to know about it so they can at least try to fix it.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Suppose, then, that you have found a bug, or at least think you have: you
    try to do something, and the results are not what you expect. What should
    you do? How should you report it?
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    こんなことを言うのは悲しいのですが、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>はいまだかつて
    完璧といえる版を提供できた例しがありません。 もっと悲しいことに今後も
    そう言える版が作れることはないでしょう。 あらゆる部分がちゃんと動くように
    日々努力を重ねてはいますが、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のような複雑な
    プログラムは、 不意に混乱に陥りあまつさえ異常終了するかもしれない不安を
    いつもかかえています。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    バグ (不具合) が避けられないのは事実ですが、 それを黙って受け入れるべきだ
    という意味で言ったのではありません。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のバグが発見
    されたら、 開発者はどうにかしてそのバグを退治できるようそのいきさつを知り
    たがりますので教えてあげましょう。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    それでは仮にあなたがバグを見付けた、 もしくは見付けたかも知れないと思って
    いるとしましょう。 何か操作してみたとき起こるはずのない結果が出てきたと
    いう想定です。 さてどうすればいいのでしょう。 
    何を報告すれば良いのでしょう。
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para lang="en">
      The procedure for making an <emphasis>enhancement
      request</emphasis>&mdash;that is, for asking the developers to add a
      missing feature&mdash;is nearly the same as the procedure for reporting
      a bug. The only thing you do differently is to mark the report as an
      <quote>enhancement</quote> at the appropriate stage, as described below.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      改善要求 (<foreignphrase>enhancement request</foreignphrase> 開発者に
      機能の改善や追加をお願いすること) の手続きはバグ報告の手順とほとんど
      同じです。 たったひとつの違いは、 その報告に<quote>enhancement</quote>
      の徴表をつけることだけです。 手続きのなかでそのための場面がありますので
      あとで説明します。
    </para>
  </tip>
  <para lang="en">
    In common with many other free software projects,
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses a bug-reporting mechanism called
    <emphasis>Bugzilla</emphasis>.
    This is a very powerful web-based system, capable of managing thousands
    of bug reports without losing track. In fact, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    shares its Bugzilla database with the entire Gnome project. At the time
    this is being written, Gnome Bugzilla contains 148632 bug reports-no, make
    that 148633.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    他の多くのフリーソフトウェア事業と同じく<acronym>GIMP</acronym>も
    <application>Bugzilla</application> と呼ばれるバグリポート機構を活用
    しています。 バグジラはWebを基盤として幾千ものバグ報告を絶えず追跡できる
    非常に強力なシステムです。 確かに<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は Bugzilla の
    データベースを <productname>Gnome</productname> のあらゆる事業と共有して
    使っています。 この解説を書いた時点では Gnome の Bugzilla に 148632 件の
    バグ報告があり今も増えつづけています。
  </para>

  <sect1 id="gimp-bug-confirm">
    <title lang="en">Making sure it's a Bug</title>
    <title lang="ja">バグかどうかの見極め</title>
    <para lang="en">
      The first thing you should do, before reporting a bug, is to make
      an effort to verify that what you are seeing really
      <emphasis>is</emphasis> a bug.  It is hard to give a method for
      doing this that applies to all situations, but reading the
      documentation will often be useful, and discussing the question on
      IRC or a mailing list may also be quite helpful.  If you are
      seeing a <emphasis>crash</emphasis>, as opposed to mere
      misbehavior, the odds that it is a true bug are pretty high: well
      written software programs are not designed to crash under
      <emphasis>any</emphasis> circumstances.  In any case, if you have
      made an conscientious effort to decide whether it is really a bug,
      and at the end still aren't sure, then please go ahead and report
      it:  the worst that can happen is that you will waste a bit of
      time for the development team.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      バグを報告する前に大切なのは遭遇された事態が果たして本当にバグなのか
      どうか検証する努力を惜しまないことです。 あらゆる場面に通用する
      検証方法を提示するのはなかなか難しいのですが、 いつもは文献を読めば
      何とかなるものですし、 <acronym>IRC</acronym>上で質問を投げかけて
      みたり、 メーリングリストを活用するのもたいへん有益です。 クラッシュ
      (異常終了) に遭遇したのなら、 単なる動作不良に比べて正真正銘のバグで
      ある確率がずいぶん高くなります。 しっかりと書かれたソフトウェアとは
      そもそもプログラムが <emphasis>どんな</emphasis> 扱い方をされても
      壊れたりしないように設計するものだからです。 本当にバグなのかいろいろ
      な条件を試しつつ入念に努力して検証された結果なら、 判断がつかない状態
      であってもどうぞバグ報告してください。 たとえバグではなかったとしても
      精々、 開発陣の時間がほんのちょっと削られるだけで済みますから。
    </para>
    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        Actually there are a few things that are known to cause
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to crash but have turned out to be too
        inconvenient to be worth fixing.  One of them is asking
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to do something that requires vast amounts of
        memory, such as creating an image one million pixels on a side.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        現実には<acronym>GIMP</acronym>を異常終了させると分かっていながら
        あまりに面倒で直すほどのことはないと判断されたものが少しあります。 
        例えば1辺が百万ピクセルもある画像を作成させるといったような、 莫大な
        量のメモリを使用する操作を<acronym>GIMP</acronym>で行なった場合が
        これにあたります。
      </para>
    </note>
    <para lang="en">
      You should also make sure that you are using an up-to-date version
      of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>: reporting bugs that have already been
      fixed is just a waste of everybody's time.  (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1
      is no longer maintained, so if you use it and find bugs, either
      upgrade to <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 or live with
      them.)  Particularly if you are using the development version of
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, make sure that you can see the bug in the
      latest release before filing a report.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      If after due consideration you still think you have a legitimate
      bug report or enhancement request, the next step is to go to
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s bugzilla query page
      (<ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/query.cgi"/>),
      and try to see whether somebody else has already reported the same
      thing.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      There are two forms you can use for searching bugs: a simple form to
      <quote>Find a Specific Bug</quote>, and an <quote>Advanced
      Search</quote>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      お使いの<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の版が最新のものであるかどうかも確かめて
      ください。 既に修正されたバグを報告したら皆が時間を損するからです。 
      (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> 1系は維持管理が終了しており一切整備が行なわれ
      ません。 バグを見付けられても、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2 に乗り換える
      か、 [ご自分でソースから修繕して]そのまま使い続けるしかありません。)
      開発者版の<acronym>GIMP</acronym>を使っている場合は特に、 最新の
      リリースでも同じバグが発生するのを確かめてからレポートを書いて
      ください。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      以上の注意義務を果たしたうえでなお正当なバグ報告か改善要求といえるもの
      があるなら、 つぎは Bugzilla の<acronym>GIMP</acronym>用質疑のページ 
      (<ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/query.cgi"/>) に行って誰か他の
      人が同じ内容の報告を出していないか確かめてください。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      バグを検索するには単純な<quote><foreignphrase>Find a Specific Bug
      </foreignphrase></quote>フォームか高度な検索条件が設定できる
      <quote><foreignphrase>Advanced Search</foreignphrase></quote>フォーム
      のいずれかが使えます。
    </para>

    <simplesect id="bugzilla-find-specific-bug">
      <title lang="en">Find a Specific Bug</title>
      <title lang="ja">特定のバグを呼び出し</title>
      <figure>
        <title>Bugzilla: Find a Specific Bug</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/misc/bugzilla/find-specific-bug.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="en">
              Searching for bugs using the simple bug search form
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">単純なバグ検索フォームでバグを検索</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en">
        Using this form, you first should select the
        <guilabel>Product</guilabel> <quote>GIMP</quote> (classified as
        <quote>Other</quote>) using the drop down list. Then you just have to
        enter some (space separated) search terms, e.g.
        <blockquote>
          <para>
          <userinput>filter&nbsp;crash</userinput>
          </para>
        </blockquote>
        in the text box and click on <guibutton>Search</guibutton>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        このフォーム上ではまず <guilabel>Product</guilabel> 欄で 
        <guimenuitem>&emsp;GIMP</guimenuitem> を選んでください。 この項目は
        <guimenuitem>Others</guimenuitem> 以下に分類されています。 そのあと
        は <guilabel>Words</guilabel> 欄に用件を空白文字で区切って 
        <blockquote>
          <para>
          <userinput>filter&nbsp;crash</userinput>
          </para>
        </blockquote>
        のように記入して、 <guibutton>Search</guibutton> ボタンをクリック
        します。
      </para>
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect id="bugzilla-advanced-search">
      <title lang="en">The Advanced Bug Search Form</title>
      <title lang="ja">バグの高度な検索フォーム</title>
      <para lang="en">
        The alternative form, the advanced query page, allows you to search
        the bug database in a variety of ways:
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        隣りのフォームは高度な検索ページになっていて、 いろいろな条件でバグ
        データベースを検索できます。
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Bugzilla: Advanced Search</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/misc/bugzilla/advanced-search.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="en">
              Searching for bugs using the advanced bug search form
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              高度な検索フォームでバグを検索
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en">
        Unfortunately this page is a bit more <quote>complicated</quote> to
        use than it really ought to be (at least, some items are hyperlinks
        leading to detailed help), but here is basically what you should do:
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        このページは実態以上に少し<quote>複雑</quote>に見えてしまうのが難点
        です。 ともあれいくつかの項目は詳しいヘルプページにハイパーリンク
        しています。 最低限ここでやるべきことはつぎのとおりです。
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Summary</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              Set this to <quote>contains any of the words/strings</quote>.
            </para>
            <para lang="en">
              In the adjoining text box, give one or more words that somebody
              would be likely to use in writing a one-sentence summary of a
              bug similar to yours. For example, if the problem is that
              zooming too much causes <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to crash, the
              word <quote>zoom</quote> would be good.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              この引き出しメニューでは 
              <guimenuitem>contains any of the words</guimenuitem> か 
              <guimenuitem>contains any of the strings</guimenuitem> を
              選んでください。 [つぎの記入欄に書いた語句の、 いずれかに
              該当する報告だけに絞るという意味です。]
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              その隣りの記入欄には、 お探しのバグをひとことで表すときに誰
              でも使いそうな単語や語句を書きます。 たとえばもし<acronym>
              GIMP</acronym>の表示倍率を極端に上げたときに異常終了が起きる
              問題があったとするなら、 <quote>zoom</quote>の語がふさわしい
              でしょう。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Classification</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              Other (since <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is not part of the GNOME
              Desktop suite).
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は GNOME Desktop suite には分類され
              ませんので、 ここは <guimenuitem>Other</guimenuitem> を指定
              します。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Product</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              Set this to <quote>GIMP</quote> (or <quote>GEGL</quote>,
              <quote>GIMP-manual</quote> etc., if appropriate).
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              ここには <guimenuitem>GIMP</guimenuitem> (あるいは場合により
              <guimenuitem>GEGL</guimenuitem> や <guimenuitem>GIMP-manual
              </guimenuitem>) を指定します。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Component, Version, Target Milestone</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">Don't do anything for these.</para>
            <para lang="ja">これらの欄には何もしません。</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Comment, Whiteboard, Keywords</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              For now, leave this alone. If your search does not turn up
              anything, it might be worth entering your search terms in the
              <quote>Comment</quote> area here, but this often turns out to
              give you either great masses of stuff or nothing.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              今のところはここも手をつけずにおきます。 検索結果に何も引っか
              からなかった場合に <guilabel>A Comment</guilabel> のところで
              記入欄に用件を書いて検索してみる価値がありますが、 しばしば
              べらぼうな数の報告の山になるか何も出てこないかのどちらかに
              なってしまいます。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Status</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              This field encodes the status of a bug report: whether it is
              still open, has been resolved, etc. You want to see all relevant
              bug reports, regardless of status, so you should hold down the
              mouse and sweep it across all entries. Leaving it alone will not
              work.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              この欄は現在審議中のバグ報告か既に解決済みのバグ報告かといった
              現在の状態を指定するために使います。 関係しているバグ報告なら
              状態に関係なく全部見たいでしょうから、 枠内をクリックしたまま
              下までなぞって (あるいは最初の項目をクリックして <keycap>Shift
              </keycap> キーを押したまま最後の項目をクリックして) 
              全部の項目を選んでください。 単独のままでは作動しません。<!--??
              -->
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Resolution, Severity, Priority, OS</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">
              Usually you shouldn't touch these items.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              解決方針、 深刻度、 優先度には普段手をつけることはありません。
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term lang="en">(Any other items)</term>
          <term lang="ja">(それ以外の項目)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">Don't do anything for these.</para>
            <para lang="ja">何もしないでください。</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para lang="en">
        When you have set these things up, click on the <quote>Search</quote>
        button at either the top or bottom; they both do the same thing. The
        result is either a list of bug reports &ndash; hopefully not too long
        &ndash; or a message saying <quote>Zarro boogs found</quote>. If you
        don't find a related bug report by doing this, it may be worth trying
        another search with different terms. If in spite of your best efforts,
        you file a bug report and it ends up being resolved as
        <quote>Duplicate</quote>, don't be too upset: it has happened
        repeatedly to the author of this documentation, who works with
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Bugzilla nearly every day.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        以上の設定が終わったらページの右上か下寄り左端にある <guibutton>
        Search</guibutton> ボタンのどちらかをクリックします。 どちらを
        クリックしても結果は同じになります。 現れ出るページにはバグ報告の
        一覧表が表示される&ndash;長過ぎなければいいですけれど&ndash;か、 
        単に<quote>Zarro boogs found</quote>と表示されるかのいずれかになり
        ます。 関係のありそうなバグ報告が見付からなかったときは用件に別の
        語句を与えて再度検索してみるとよいかもしれません。 思いつく限りの手
        を尽くしバグ報告を提出したのに、 <quote>DUPLICATE</quote>(重複) の
        ひとことで解決済みの処理が行なわれてもどうか落ち込まないでください。
        同じ処置は頻繁に起こっていて、 Bugzilla で<acronym>GIMP</acronym>
        関連の業務を担当している筆者のところにはほぼ毎日重複したバグ報告が
        上がってきています。
      </para>
      <tip>
        <para lang="en">
          Depending on your browser configuration (i.e. whether JavaScript is
          enabled), you may see a link
          <guilabel>Give&nbsp;me&nbsp;some&nbsp;help</guilabel>. If you click
          on this link, the page will be reloaded and then moving the mouse
          pointer over an input widget produces a little help popup.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          お使いのウェブブラウザの設定 (JavaScript有効) により <guilabel>
          Give&nbsp;me&nbsp;some&nbsp;help</guilabel> と書かれたリンクが表示
          されます。 このリンクをクリックするとページが読み込み直され、 各
          項目や記入欄にはマウスポインタをかざしたときに小さなヘルプ表示が
          飛び出すしかけが付きます。
        </para>
      </tip>
    </simplesect>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimp-bug-report">
    <title lang="en">Reporting the Bug</title>
    <title lang="ja">バグ報告</title>
    <para lang="en">
      Okay, so you have done everything you could to make sure, and you still
      think it's probably a bug. You should then go ahead and file a bug
      report on the Bugzilla page.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      分かりました。 あらゆる方法を試したけれどやはりどうやらバグらしいとの
      結論になったのですね。 それではいよいよ Bugzilla のページでバグ報告の
      提出にとりかかります。
    </para>
    <note>
      <para lang="en">
        The first time you file a bug report, you will be asked to create a
        Bugzilla account. The process is easy and painless, and you probably
        won't even get any spam as a result.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        バグ報告は初めてという方には Bugzilla 用のアカウントを作成して
        いただきます。 手続きは簡単ですし、 登録したがために迷惑メールが
        舞い込むこともおそらくありません。
      </para>
    </note>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <title>Bugzilla: Select Classification</title>
        <para lang="en">
          Go to <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/enter_bug.cgi"/>, and
          select the classification <quote>Other</quote>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/enter_bug.cgi"/> に行き、 
          <guilabel>Other</guilabel> を選択します。
        </para>
        <!-- IMHO a screenshot is not useful here (ude 2009-08-25) -->
        <para lang="en">
          If you are not logged in, you are automatically redirected to the
          login page. After entering your user name (login) and password,
          you get back to the <quote>Select Classification</quote> page.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          まだログインされていないときは直にログインページに飛びます。 
          ユーザネーム[かメールアドレス]と Bugzilla 用のパスワードをそれぞれ
          記入してログインすると再び<quote>Select Classification</quote>の
          ページに帰れます。
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <title>Bugzilla: Pick Product</title>
        <para lang="en">
          Scroll down the next page until you can select the product
          <quote>GIMP</quote>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          つぎのページを下に繰り寄せて <guilabel>GIMP</guilabel> を探し
          出します。
        </para>
        <!-- IMHO a screenshot is not useful here (ude 2009-08-25) -->
        <tip>
          <para lang="en">
            You can skip the above steps and go directly to
           <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=GIMP"/>
           (You still have to login, of course.)
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=GIMP"/>
            に直接行けば探す手間が省けます。 (もちろんログイン手続きは必要
            です。)
          </para>
        </tip>
      </step>

      <step>
        <title>Bugzilla: Enter Bug: <acronym>GIMP</acronym></title>
        <para lang="en">
          Selecting <quote>GIMP</quote> as product takes you to the
          following bug report form, which you should fill out as follows.
          Note that most of the information you enter can be changed later
          by the developers if you get it wrong, so try to get it right but
          don't be obsessive about it.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          製造物 (product) に <guilabel>GIMP</guilabel> を選ぶと、 下図の
          ようなバグ報告フォームが現れますので、 つぎに示す内容で埋めて
          ください。 ちなみにここで設定した指標のほとんどはもし間違いが
          あれば開発者の方で変更できるようになっていますから、 できるだけ
          正確な設定が望ましいとはいえあまり恐れる必要はありません。
        </para>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo>2009-08-25</screeninfo>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="PNG"
                fileref="images/misc/bugzilla/enter-bug.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
              <para>Enter Bug: <acronym>GIMP</acronym></para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Component</term>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                Set this to the part of <acronym>GIMP</acronym> that the bug
                affects. Note that you get a short
                <quote>Component&nbsp;Description</quote> in the text box next
                to the list when you select a component.
              </para>
              <para lang="en">
                You have to pick something here, but if you aren't sure, make
                a guess and don't worry about it.
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                <acronym>GIMP</acronym>でバグが発生したと思われる部分をここに
                示します。 ちなみにこの表で選択されている項目についての簡潔な
                情報が右隣の<quote>Component&nbsp;Desciption</quote>欄に表示
                されますので参考にしてください。
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                どれかひとつを選ばなくてはなりません。 どれなのか分からない
                ときは悩まず近そうなのをとりあえず選びましょう。
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Version</term>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                Set this to the version of <acronym>GIMP</acronym> that you
                are using. You always find the version in the menu of the
                image window:
                <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
                  <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                お使いの<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の版番号をここに示して
                ください。 バージョンの情報は画像ウィンドウのメニューより 
                <menuchoice>
                  <guimenu>ヘルプ</guimenu>
                  <guimenuitem>GIMPについて</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
                を実行すれば必ず分かります。
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Severity</term>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                In most cases you should either leave this as
                <quote>Normal</quote> or set it to <quote>Enhancement</quote>,
                if it is an enhancement request rather than a malfunction. The
                maintainers will adjust the severity if they think it is
                warranted.
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                大抵の場合<quote>深刻度</quote>の設定は <guimenuitem>Normal
                </guimenuitem> のままで結構ですが、 動作不良の話ではなく改善
                要求をするつもりなら <guimenuitem>Enhancement</guimenuitem> 
                に設定することになるでしょう。 管理者の方でお墨付きがあると
                深刻度を調節するつもりです。
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term lang="en">OS (Operating System)</term>
            <term lang="ja">OS (オペレーティングシステム)</term>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                Set this to your OS unless you have a very good reason for
                thinking that the bug applies to all operating systems.
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                お使いのオペレーティングシステムをここに示します。 バグが
                他の全ての<acronym>OS</acronym>でも起こりうるという
                十分正当な理由がある場合のみ <guimenuitem>All</guimenuitem>
                を選んでください。
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Summary</term>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                Give a one-sentence summary that is descriptive enough so that
                somebody searching for similar bugs would find your bug report
                on the basis of the words this summary contains.
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                要約をここにまとめます。 誰かが同じようなバグを検索したときに
                この要約の語句が引き金となってあなたのバグ報告が引き出されるの
                に十分な、 説明的な記述を心掛けましょう。
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Description</term>
            <listitem>
              <para lang="en">
                Describe the problem. Be as specific as you can, and include
                all information that you think might possibly be relevant.
                The classic totally useless bug report is, <quote>GIMP
                crashes. This program sucks</quote>. There is no hope that the
                developers can solve a problem if they can't tell what it is.
              </para>
              <para lang="ja">
                問題を説明します。 できるだけ明白に、 かつ関係しそうだと思える
                情報を全て網羅します。 よくあるさっぱり無意味なバグ報告の
                典型は<quote><acronym>GIMP</acronym>がクラッシュしやがった。 
                クソプログラムだな。</quote>です。 こんな報告では何が起きたか
                推し量りようがなく、 そうなると開発者が解決できる望みは
                なくなってしまいます。
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para lang="en">
          There are more fields which are hidden by default. (Click
          <quote>Show Advanced Fields</quote> to show them.) You can ignore
          them, so we won't describe these fields here.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          Sometimes it is very helpful to augment a bug report with a
          screenshot or some other type of data. If you need to do this, click
          on the button <guibutton>Add&nbsp;an&nbsp;attachment</guibutton>,
          and follow the directions. But please don't do this unless you think
          the attachment is really going to be useful&mdash;and if you need to
          attach a screenshot, don't make it any larger than necessary. Bug
          reports are likely to remain on the system for years, so there is no
          sense in wasting memory.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          When you have filled out all of these things, press the
          <guibutton>Commit</guibutton> button and your bug report will be
          submitted. It will be assigned a number, which you may want to make
          note of; you will, however, be emailed any time somebody makes a
          comment on your bug report or otherwise alters it, so you will
          receive reminders in any case. You can see the current state of your
          bug report at any time by going to
          <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org"/>, entering the bug number in
          one of the entry boxes and pressing the
          <guibutton>Find</guibutton> or <guibutton>Quick Search</guibutton>
          button.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          他にも記入欄がありますが初期状態では隠されています。 <guilabel>
          Show Advance Fields</guilabel> をクリックすると現れます。 無視して
          構わないものばかりなのでこれらについては説明しません。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          ときにはバグ報告にスクリーンショットや何か他の形式のデータを添付
          すると大いに役立つ場合があります。 ファイルの添付のしかたは 
          <guibutton>Add&nbsp;an&nbsp;attachment</guibutton> ボタンをクリック
          すると表示される案内のとおりです。 でも添付するときっと役立つ
          という確信がなければファイルを添付しないでください。 とくに
          スクリーンショットを添付する場合は必要以上に大きな画像にしては
          いけません。 バグ報告はこの先何年もシステムが保管するようになって
          いるので、 メモリの浪費につながるような行為は非常識です。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          それぞれの項目を埋めてから <guibutton>Commit</guibutton> ボタンを
          クリックするとバグ報告が提出されます。 報告には番号が振られますので
          後で見返すために控えておくとよいでしょう。 とはいえ提出したバグ報告
          に誰かがコメントを寄せるかさもなくば変更を加えたならばすぐさま
          電子メールで知らせてくれますから、 いろいろな場面で記憶が甦ることに
          なります。 バグ報告の現在の状態を知るには 
          <ulink url="http://buzgilla.gnome.org"/> に行ってどの記入欄でも
          構いませんからバグ報告番号を書き込み、 その隣りの <guibutton>Find
          </guibutton> ボタンもしくは <guibutton>Quick&nbsp;Search</guibutton>
          ボタンをクリックすればいつでも見られます。
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimp-bug-submitted">
    <title lang="en">What Happens to a Bug Report after you Submit it</title>
    <title lang="ja">バグ報告提出後の進展</title>
    <para lang="en">
      At any time after it is submitted, a bug report has a
      <quote>Status</quote>
      that describes how it is currently being handled.  Here are the
      possible values of <emphasis>Status</emphasis> and what they mean:
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      バグ報告には現在どのような扱いになっているかを示す<quote>Status</quote>
      が、 提出した直後からずっとついてまわります。 この状態指標にはつぎの種類
      があります。
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Unconfirmed</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This is the initial status of a bug report, from the time it is
            submitted until one of the maintainers reads it and decides
            whether it is really a valid bug report. Sometimes the maintainers
            aren't sure, and in the meantime leave the status as
            <quote>Unconfirmed</quote>. In the worst cases, a bug report can
            stay
            unconfirmed for a year or longer, but this is considered a bad
            thing and does not happen very often.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            バグ報告は最初この状態になり、 提出直後の時点から、 管理者の誰かが
            読んでバグ報告の審査をするまでの間、 初期状態が続きます。 管理者が
            うっかりすることもたまにあり、 その間は<quote>Unconfirmed</quote>
            の状態が続きます。 最悪の場合一年以上も未認証の状態が続く可能性が
            ありますが、 これは一大事だと考えられており、 あまり何度も起こる
            ものではありません。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>New</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This means that the bug report has been read by one of the
            maintainers, and is considered, for the moment at least, to be
            valid. It does not necessarily mean that anything is going to be
            done about it immediately: some bug reports, especially
            enhancement requests, may be perfectly valid and still go for a
            long time before anybody is able to deal with them. Many bugs, on
            the other hand, are fixed within hours of being reported.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            これは管理者の誰かがバグ報告を読み、 少なくともその時点で有効と
            見做したことを示しています。 しかし必ずしもこの状態は直ちに処置に
            とりかかってもらえるという意味にはなりません。 バグ報告のいつくか、
            とりわけ改善要求の場合はちゃんと承認が与えられても誰かが対処する
            まで随分と時間がかかることがあります。 でもバグ報告の多くは提出
            されて数十時間以内に処置が済みます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Assigned</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This means that a specific person has agreed to work on the bug.
            It does not, this world being the kind of world that it is, mean
            that that person will actually <emphasis>do</emphasis>
            anything in particular, so for practical purposes this status
            means nearly the same thing as <quote>New</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            割り当て済み状態とは関係者がそのバグに取り組む合意があったことを
            示します。 しかし開発者の世界も世間一般と同じですから、 これでその
            人物が実際に特段何かを <emphasis>する</emphasis> という意味には
            なりません。 ですから現実的に見ればこの状態指標は<quote>New
            </quote>とほぼ同じです。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Reopened</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This means that the bug report was at some point considered by the
            maintainers to be resolved (i.e., finished), but new information
            came in that caused them to change their minds: most likely, a
            change that was intended to fix the problem did not completely
            work.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            再発状態とはそのバグ報告がある部分で解決した (つまり終了した) と
            管理者がいったん認めたのに、 新たにもたらされた情報によってその判断
            が変わったことを示します。 大概は問題を解いたはずの変更が完璧には
            用を果たさなかったような場合にこうなります。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Needinfo</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This is a status you should pay particular attention to. It means
            that you did not supply enough information in your bug report to
            enable anything to be done about it. In most cases, no further
            action will be taken on the bug report until you supply additional
            information (by adding a comment). If too much time goes by
            without any input from you, the bug report will eventually be
            resolved as <quote>Incomplete</quote>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            要情報状態になったときは特に注意を払うべきです。 これはバグに対処
            するのに充分な情報がバグ報告に欠けていることを示しています。 
            ほとんどの場合コメントを追加するなどして新たに情報を加えなければ、
            バグ報告にはこれ以上反応してもらえません。 そのまま長い間放って
            おくと、 そのバグ報告はついには<quote>Incomplete</quote> (未成) 
            として処分されます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Resolved</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This means that the maintainers believe that they have finished
            dealing with the bug report. If you disagree, you can re-open it,
            but since you cannot force anybody to work on a bug against their
            will, you should have a good reason for doing so. Bugs can be
            resolved in a variety of ways. Here are the possible values of
            <emphasis>Resolution</emphasis> and what they mean:
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            解決済み状態とはバグ報告の取り扱いが終了したと管理者が確信したこと
            を示しています。 もしそうは思えないのなら<quote>Reopen</quote>
            (再発) させる方法がありますが、 他人の意思に逆らって強制的にバグに
            取り組ませることはできませんから、 ちゃんとした理由を提示しなくては
            なりません。 バグの対処方法はいろいろあります。 <quote>Resolution
            </quote> (解決方針) にはつぎの種類があります。
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Fixed</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  The bug report is considered valid, and
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has been
                  changed in a way that is considered to fix it.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  修繕済みとはバグ報告が有効だと認められ、 その処置ができたと
                  考えられる変更が<acronym>GIMP</acronym>に加えられたことを
                  示します。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Wontfix</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  The maintainers agree that the bug report is valid, but it
                  would take so much effort to fix, in relation to its
                  importance, that it is not worth the trouble.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  修繕求むとはバグ報告を管理者が有効と認めたあと、 問題の
                  重要度に比べて処置に大変な労力を要する場合を示します。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Duplicate</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  This means that the same bug has already been reported by
                  somebody else. If you see this resolution, you will also see
                  a pointer to the earlier bug report, which will often give
                  you a lot of useful information.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  重複とは誰かが同じ内容のバグ報告を既に出していることを示し
                  ます。 この解決方針が出たら既出のバグ報告へのリンクが張られて
                  いるはずですからご覧ください。 しばしばここで役立つ情報が
                  たくさん得られます。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Notabug</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  This means that the behavior described in the bug
                  report is intentional. It may seem like a bug to you
                  (and there may be many people who agree with you), but
                  the program is working the way it was intended to
                  work,  and the developers don't want to change it.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  非バグとはバグ報告に記載された説明が恣意的なものだと判断
                  されたことを示します。 しかし報告した問題がバグのように見え、
                  他にもそう思う人がたくさんいそうなのに、 実際は
                  プログラムは仕様通りの動作をしていて、 開発者は変更する
                  つもりがないという事態でもあります。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>NotGnome</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  The bug report is valid, but it can't be addressed by
                  changing <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Problems in operating
                  systems, window managers, or libraries that
                  <acronym>GIMP</acronym> depends on will often be
                  given this resolution. Sometimes the next appropriate step
                  is to file a bug report for the software that is really at
                  fault.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  Gnomeと無関係とはバグ報告が正当なものだけれど<acronym>GIMP
                  </acronym>に変更を加えても対処できない問題であることを示し
                  ます。 オペレーティングシステムやウィンドウマネージャ、 
                  ライブラリなど<acronym>GIMP</acronym>が依拠する製造物に問題
                  がある場合はしばしばこの解決方針が出ます。 ときにはそのつぎに
                  そのソフトウェアに対し問題を引き起こしているとバグ報告を提出
                  するのが適切な行動でしょう。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Incomplete</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  The bug report did not contain enough information for
                  anything to be done about it, and the reporter did not
                  respond to requests for more information. Usually a bug
                  report will be open for at least a month or two before it is
                  resolved in this way.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  未成とはバグ報告がバグに対処するには不十分な情報しか提供して
                  おらず、 しかも報告者がさらなる情報の求めに応じないことを
                  示しています。 普段はバグ報告がこうした形で処分されるまで
                  少なくとも1～2ヶ月間は<quote>Open</quote> (開示) 期間と
                  なります。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Invalid</term>
              <listitem>
                <para lang="en">
                  Something is wrong with the form of the bug report: most
                  commonly, the reporter has accidentally submitted the same
                  bug report multiple times. (This can easily happen by
                  mistake with some web browsers.) Bug reports that
                  incorrectly describe how the program behaves may also be
                  resolved as Invalid.
                </para>
                <para lang="ja">
                  たまにバグ報告の形式が間違っていることがあります。 よくある
                  例が、 報告者が不意に同じバグ報告を重複して送った場合です。 
                  これはウェブブラウザの誤操作で簡単に引き起こされます。 報告に
                  プログラムの動作について不正な記述がある場合も不正として処分
                  されます。
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <note>
            <para lang="en">
              If you disagree with the resolution of a bug report, you are
              always free to add your comments to it. Any comment added to any
              bug report, resolved or not, causes email to be sent to the
              <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
              Bugzilla mailing list, so it will at least be seen by the
              maintainers. This does not, of course, mean that they will
              necessarily respond to it.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              バグ報告の処分に同意できないときはいつでもコメントを追加して
              構いません。 解決済みと未解決を問わずあらゆるバグ報告に対する
              どんなコメントも Bugzilla の<acronym>GIMP</acronym>用メーリング
              リストを通じて配信され、 管理者はいずれ電子メールでそれを見る
              ことになります。 もちろんそのコメントが必ずしも返信を得られる
              とは限りません。
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
