<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2007-05-27 ude: removed <acronym> tags for
             C, Linux, Lisp, LISP, Motiv, Perl, Python, Scheme,
             Unix, UNIX, X, yacc
  2007-04-21 lexa: fixed bug #420007
  2006-09-29 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2005-12-12 fixed cs lang tags by lexa
  2005-12-12 moved to the appendix by lexa
  2005-12-11 added de description for version 2.0 to the history by lexa
  2005-12-10 added de translation, made the file valid docbook by lexa
-->
<!--2012-04-11-->
<appendix xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-introduction-history">
  <title lang="en">GIMP History</title>
  <title lang="ja">GIMPの歴史</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>History</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>GIMP</primary>
    <secondary>歴史</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-beginning">
    <title lang="en">The Very Beginning</title>
    <title lang="ja">そもそものはじめ</title>
    <para lang="en">
      According to Peter Mattis and Spencer Kimball, the original creators of
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, in their announcement of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
      0.54:
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The <acronym>GIMP</acronym> arose from the ashes of a hideously
      crafted CS164 (compilers)
      class project. The setting: early morning. We were both weary from lack
      of sleep and the terrible strain of programming a compiler in
      LISP. The limits of our patience had long been
      exceeded, and yet still the dam held.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      And then it happened. Common LISP
      messily dumped core when it could not allocate the 17 MB it needed to
      generate a parser for a simple grammar using <application>yacc</application>.
      An unbelieving moment passed, there was one shared look of disgust,
      and then our project was vapor. We had to write something...
      <emphasis>ANYTHING</emphasis> ... useful. Something in
      C. Something that did not rely on nested lists to
      represent a bitmap. Thus, the <acronym>GIMP</acronym> was born.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Like the phoenix, glorious, new life sprung out of the burnt remnants of
      LISP and <application>yacc</application>. Ideas went
      flying, decisions were made, the
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> began to take form.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      An image manipulation program was the consensus. A program that would at
      the very least lessen the necessity of using commercial software under
      <quote>Windoze</quote> or on the <quote>Macintoy</quote>. A program
      that would provide the features missing from the other
      X painting and imaging tools. A program
      that would help maintain the long tradition of excellent and free
      UNIX applications.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Six months later, we've reached an early beta stage. We want to release
      now to start working on compatibility issues and cross-platform
      stability. Also, we feel now that the program is actually usable and
      would like to see other interested programmers developing plug-ins and
      various file format support.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の創始者 Peter Mattis と Spencer Kimball が
      <application><acronym>GIMP</acronym> 0.54</application> の告知文で
      明かしたいきさつはつぎのとおり。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は CS164 コンパイラ用のぞっとするようなクラス
      プロジェクト制作のとき、 その灰の中から現れた。 舞台は早朝。 我々 2 人は
      睡眠不足だったし、 <acronym>LISP</acronym>コンパイラでプログラミングし
      続けてひどい過労だったので疲れきっていた。 とうに我慢の限界は超えて
      いたし、 目の前の障害は越えられないでいた。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      そう、 そしてそのときが来た。 Common <acronym>LISP</acronym>は 
      <application>yacc</application> を使った簡単な文法解析器を生成するのに
      必要な 17MB のメモリ割り当てができずこんがらがったコアファイルを吐く。 
      天に見放されたような気がする時間が過ぎ、 うんざりした視線が互いに
      交わされたとき、 我々のプロジェクトがおぼろげに現れた。 書くべきだ
      &hellip;何から何まで&hellip;使えるものにして&hellip;。 C 言語で書いて。 
      ビットマップを表すのはネストしまくったリストじゃないのがいいね&hellip;。
      かくして<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は産声をあげたんだ。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
     不死鳥の如く、 (栄光あれ)、 <acronym>LISP</acronym> と <application>
     yacc</application> の燃えかすから新しい生命が誕生した。 ひらめきが
     飛び交い、 決断が行なわれ、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>がいよいよ立ち現れて
     くる。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      画像編集プログラムで意見が一致した。 <quote>Windoze</quote>や<quote>
      Macintoy</quote>用の商用ソフトが最終的に要らなくなるようなプログラムに
      すること。 X 用の他のお絵描きソフトや画像ツールには無い機能もついた
      プログラムにすること。 卓越した物でありながらフリーな <productname>
      UNIX</productname> 系アプリケーションの伝統を承け継ぐに足るプログラム
      にすること。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      それから 6 ヶ月が経ち、 我々は初期ベータ段階を迎える。 互換性の問題や
      異機種横断で安定させる課題に着手したいので、 いよいよ公開に踏み切ろうと
      考えたんだ。 しかももうこのプログラムは実用できるものになってきたと
      思えるから、 関心を寄せてくれるプログラマがプラグインやいろいろな
      ファイル形式サポートを開発してくれるのを期待している。
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-early-days">
    <title lang="en">The Early Days of GIMP</title>
    <title lang="ja">最初期の<acronym>GIMP</acronym></title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Version 0.54</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Version 0.54 was released in February 1996, and had a major impact
            as the first truly professional free image manipulation program.
            This was the first free program that could compete with the big
            commercial image manipulation programs.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Version 0.54 was a beta release, but it was so stable that you
            could use it for daily work. However, one of the major drawbacks
            of 0.54 was that the toolkit (the slidebars, menus, dialog boxes,
            etc.) was built on Motif, a commercial
            toolkit. This was a big drawback for systems like
            <quote>Linux</quote>, because you had to buy
            Motif if you wanted to use the faster,
            dynamically linked <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Many
            developers were also students running Linux,
            who could not afford to buy Motif.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            Version 0.54 は1996年2月に公開され、 最初の真に実用的でフリーな
            画像編集プログラムとして、 大きな衝撃をもって迎えられました。 
            かの大壮な商用の画像編集プログラムに匹敵しうる最初のフリーな
            プログラムでもありました。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            Version 0.54 はベータ版ですが、 日々の使用に耐えうる安定した版
            でした。 しかしながら 0.54 が使うツールキット (サイドバーや
            メニューやダイアログボックスなどの部品) が 
            <trademark class="registered">Motif</trademark> だったので、 商用
            ツールキットを使用していることが大きな障害のひとつとなりました。 
            この仕様では<acronym>GIMP</acronym>を高速に動かそうと思ったら動的
            リンクさせるために <trademark class="registered">Motif</trademark>
            を購入しなくてはならず、 <productname>Linux</productname> のような
            システムにとっては大きな足かせになります。 開発には <productname>
            Linux</productname> を使う学生も携わっており、 
            <trademark class="registered">Motif</trademark> を買う余裕のない
            者が大勢いました。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Version 0.60</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            When 0.60 was released in July 1996, it had been under S and P
            (Spencer and Peter) development for four months. Main programming
            advantages were the new toolkits, <acronym>GTK</acronym>
            (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Toolkit) and <acronym>gdk</acronym>
            (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Drawing Kit), which eliminated the
            reliance on Motif. For the
            graphic artist, 0.60 was full of new features like: basic layers;
            improved painting tools (sub-pixel sampling, brush spacing); a
            better airbrush; paint modes; etc.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            Version 0.60 was only a developer's release, and was not intended
            for widespread use. It served as a workbench for 0.99 and the
            final 1.0 version, so functions and enhancement could be tested
            and dropped or changed. You can look at 0.60 as the alpha version
            of 0.99.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            0.60 が1996年7月に公開されたとき、 SとP (Spencer と Peter) が開発
            を始めて4ヶ月目となりました。 今回のプログラムの目玉は<acronym>
            GTK</acronym> (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Tool Kit) と <acronym>GDK
            </acronym> (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Drawing Kit) という新しい
            ツールキットが使われることになり、 <trademark class="registered">
            Motif</trademark> 依存から脱却を果たしたことです。 グラフィック
            アーティストにとっては、 0.60 は新機能が目白押しの版でした。 
            たとえば、 基本のレイヤー、 サブピクセルサンプリングやブラシ間隔
            が扱える改良型描画ツール、 よりすぐれたエアブラシ、 描画モード、 
            などなどです。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            Version 0.60 は普及させる意図がなく開発者向けの公開でした。 0.99
            や果ては 1.0 となるたたき台の版として提供されたものであり、 加え
            られた機能や拡張は検証されたうえで廃棄もしくは変更される手筈に
            なっていました。 0.60 を 0.99 の版に対するアルファ版と位置付ける
            見方もできます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Version 0.99</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            In February 1997, 0.99 came on the scene. Together with other
            developers, S and P had made several changes to
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> and added
            even more features. The main difference was the new API
            (Application Programming Interface) and the
            <quote>PDB</quote>, which made it possible to write scripts;
            Script-Fus (or
            macros) could now automate things that you would normally do by
            hand. <acronym>GTK/gdk</acronym> had also changed and was now
            called <acronym>GTK+</acronym>. In
            addition, 0.99 used a new form of tile-based memory handling that
            made it possible to load huge images into <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            (loading a 100 MB image into <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is no
            problem). Version 0.99 also introduced a new
            native <acronym>GIMP</acronym> file format called XCF.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            The new API made it really easy to write extensions and plug-ins
            for <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Several new plug-ins and extensions
            emerged to make <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            even more useful (such as <acronym>SANE</acronym>, which enables
            scanning directly into <acronym>GIMP</acronym>).
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            In the summer of 1997, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> had reached
            version 0.99.10, and S and
            P had to drop most of their support since they had graduated and
            begun jobs. However, the other developers of
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> continued under
            the orchestration of Federico Mena to make
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> ready for prime time.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            <acronym>GTK+</acronym> was separated from
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> in September 1997.
            <acronym>GTK+</acronym> had been
            recognized as an excellent toolkit, and other developers began
            using it to build their own applications.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> went into feature freeze in October
            1997. This meant that no
            new features would be added to the <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            core libraries and program. <acronym>GUM</acronym> (GIMP Users
            Manual) version 0.5 was also released early in October 1997.
            The developing work continued to make <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            stable and ready for version 1.0.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            1997年2月、 0.99 が登場しました。 S と P は他の開発者とともに
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>にいろいろな変更を行ない、 さらに機能を
            加えました。 主な変更点は新しい<acronym>API</acronym> 
            (<foreignphrase>Application Programming Interface</foreignphrase>)
            の採用と、 スクリプトを書いて活用できるようにする<acronym>PDB
            </acronym>が加わったことです。 Script-Fu (マクロ機能の一種) を利用
            すれば普段手作業でする操作を自動化できるようになりました。 
            <acronym>GTK</acronym>と<acronym>GDK</acronym>はさらに変更が加え
            られ、 <acronym>GTK+</acronym>と呼ばれるようになりました。 さらに
            0.99 はタイルベースのメモリ管理形態を取り入れ、 巨大な画像も
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>で読み込めるように、 例えば 100MB の画像を
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>に読み込んでも問題が起きないように
            なります。 Version 0.99 からは 
            <link linkend="glossary-xcf"><acronym>XCF</acronym></link> と呼ば
            れる<acronym>GIMP</acronym>由来のファイル形式が導入されました。 
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            新しい<acronym>API</acronym>のおかげで<acronym>GIMP</acronym>用の
            拡張やプラグインを書くのが格段に容易になりました。 新しい
            プラグインや拡張機能がいくつか出現し、 たとえば <application>
            <acronym>SANE</acronym></application> で<acronym>GIMP</acronym>へ
            直にスキャン画像が取り込めるようになったように、 <acronym>GIMP
            </acronym>がさらに使い易くなりました。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            1997年の夏、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>が Version 0.99.10 に達した
            頃、 S と P が大学を卒業し就職したのを機に開発の大部分から手を
            ひきました。 それでも他の開発者は Federico Mena の指揮の下で
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の開発を継続し、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
            の至高の瞬間を迎える準備を進めます。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <acronym>GTK+</acronym>は1997年9月に<acronym>GIMP</acronym>から
            分離されました。 それ以降<acronym>GTK+</acronym>は上質なツール
            キットのひとつとして受け入れられるようになり、 他の
            アプリケーションの開発に利用しはじめる開発者も現れます。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は1997年10月に機能凍結期を迎えます。 これは
            [1.0 が公開されるまで]<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の中枢ライブラリや
            プログラムの一切の機能追加を停止するという意味です。 
            また<acronym>GUM</acronym> (<acronym>GIMP</acronym> Users Manual) 
            version 0.5 も1997年10月の初旬に公開されました。 開発者は
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym>を安定化させる作業を続け、 着々と 
            Version 1.0 の準備が整います。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gimp-introduction-history-1-0">
    <title lang="en">The One to Change the World</title>
    <title lang="ja">世界を変えた一品</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Version 1.0</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> version 1.0 was released on June 5,
            1998. Finally, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> was
            considered stable enough to warrant a worldwide announcement and
            professional use.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Version 1.0 は1998年6月5日に公開
            されました。 とうとう<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は世界中に告知され
            専門家に使用が勧められる十分な安定化を果たしたと受けとめ
            られました。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Version 1.2</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> version 1.2.0 was released on
            December 25, 2000.
            Compared to the version 1.0, it included mostly fixes
            and improvements of the user interface.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <acronym>GIMP</acronym> Version 1.2.0 は2000年12月25日に公開
            されました。 主に Version 1.0 からの修正とユーザーインタフェースの
            向上が行なわれました。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
  <xi:include href="history-20.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="history-22.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="history-24.xml"/>
</appendix>
