<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-07-15 KoSt: added 'no'
  2008-04-05 Mr.Dust : added 'ko' contents
  2007-12-26 lexa: initial version for en and de
-->
<!--2009-05-15-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-color-management">
  <title lang="en">Color Management in GIMP</title>
  <title lang="ja"><acronym>GIMP</acronym>での色管理</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Color</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>ICC profile</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="イロ">色</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ICCカラープロファイル</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    Many devices you use in your design or photography workflow, like digital
    photo cameras, scanners, displays, printers etc., have their own color
    reproduction characteristics. If those are not taken into account during
    opening, editing and saving, harmful adjustments can be done to images.
    With GIMP you can have reliable output for both Web and print.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    デザインの工程や写真を扱う工程ではデジタルカメラやスキャナ、 ディスプレイ
    モニタ、 プリンタなど様々な機器が使われますが、 これらは色再現指標を個別に
    持っています。 このことを何ら考慮せず画像を開いたり編集したり保存すると、
    その画像に有害な調整が行われるはめになります。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>なら
    ウェブ掲示と印刷の両方にまたがって信頼できる出力を得る方法があります。
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Image Processing Workflow</title>
    <title lang="ja">画像処理の工程</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/using/colormanagement-workflow1.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">Workflow without Color management</para>
        <para lang="ja">色管理を欠いた作業工程</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
         fileref="images/using/colormanagement-workflow2.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">Process with Color management</para>
        <para lang="ja">色管理をとり入れた作業工程</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2>
    <title lang="en">Problems of a non Color Managed Workflow</title>
    <title lang="ja">色管理のない工程に発生する問題</title>
    <para lang="en">
      The basic problem of image manipulation without color management is that
      you do simply not see what you do. This affects two different areas:
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      色管理のない画像加工には、 本質的には何をどのように編集したのかが見えない
      という問題があります。 この状況はつぎの2つの場面で発生します。
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          There are differences in Colors caused by different color
          characteristics of different devices like cameras, scanners,
          displays or printers
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          カメラ、 スキャナ、 ディスプレイモニタ、 プリンタなど、 使った
          機器によって色指標がまちまちになっていると、 色が食い違います。
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          There are differences in Colors caused by the limitations of the
          colorspace a specific device is able to handle
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          機器によっては扱える色空間に制限があるために、 色に齟齬が生まれます。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para lang="en">
      The main purpose of color management is to avoid such problems. The
      approach taken to do so involves the addition of a description of the
      color characteristic to an image or devices.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      These descriptions are called <emphasis>color profile</emphasis>. A
      color profile is basically a look-up table to translate the specific
      color characteristic of a device to a device-independent color space -
      the so called working-space. All the image manipulation is then done to
      images in the working-space. In addition to that the color profile of a
      device can be used to simulate how colors would look on that device.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      The creation of color profiles is most often done by the manufacturer
      of the devices themselves. To make these profiles usable independent of
      platform and operating system, the ICC (International Color Consortium)
      created a standard called ICC-profile that describes how color profiles
      are stored to files and embedded into images.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      色管理の主な目的はこういった問題を避けることです。 その目的のために、
      画像や機器には色指標の記述が追加される必要があります。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      その記述を <emphasis>カラープロファイル</emphasis> といいます。 カラー
      プロファイルは、 基本的には機器固有の色指標を機種非依存の色空間 (いわゆる
      作業空間) に読み替えるための対照表です。 そして画像編集は全て作業空間に
      置かれた画像に対して行なわれます。 さらにカラープロファイルは機器によって
      色がどのように表現されるのかを試演するのにも役立ちます。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      いろいろなカラープロファイルを最も頻繁に作成するのは機器自身の生産者
      (メーカー) です。 これらプロファイルが機種やオペレーティングシステムに
      依存せずに使えるように、 <acronym>ICC</acronym> (International Color
      Consortium) は<acronym>ICC</acronym>プロファイルという標準規格を作成
      しました。 この規格ではカラープロファイルのファイルへの保存方法や画像への
      埋め込み方が定められています。
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="plug-in-icc-profile-set">
    <title lang="en">Introduction to a Color Managed Workflow</title>
    <title lang="ja">色管理のある工程へのいざない</title>
    <tip>
      <para lang="en">
        Most of the parameters and profiles described here can be set in the
        GIMP preferences. Please see
        <xref linkend="gimp-prefs-color-management"/> for details.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        ここに示した媒介変数やプロファイルはほとんどが<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の
        環境設定ダイアログで決められます。 詳しくは
        <xref linkend="gimp-prefs-color-management"/> をご覧ください。
      </para>
    </tip>
    <sect3 id="plug-in-icc-profile-apply">
      <title lang="en">Input</title>
      <title lang="ja">入力</title>
      <para lang="en">
        Most digital cameras embed a color profile to individual photo files
        without user interaction. Digital scanners usually come with a color
        profile, which they also attach to the scanned images.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        大概のデジタルカメラは撮影者の介在なしにそれぞれの写真ファイルに
        カラープロファイルを埋め込みます。 デジタルスキャナも普通はカラー
        プロファイルがついていて、 同じく取り込んだ画像に添付します。
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title lang="en">Applying the ICC-profile</title>
        <title lang="ja"><acronym>ICC</acronym>プロファイルの適用</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/using/icc-apply.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para lang="en">
        When opening an image with an embedded color profile, GIMP offers to
        convert the file to the RGB working color space. This is sRGB by
        default and it is recommended that all work is done in that color
        space. Should you however decide to keep the embedded color profile,
        the image will however still be displayed correctly.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        In case for some reason a color profile is not embedded in the image
        and you know (or have a good guess) which one it should be, you can
        manually assign it to that image.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        カラープロファイルが埋め込まれた画像を<acronym>GIMP</acronym>で開くと、
        そのファイルを作業空間 (<acronym>RGB</acronym>色空間) に合わせて変換
        するかどうか尋ねられます。 この色空間は初期設定では s<acronym>RGB
        </acronym>が指定されていますが、 作業の全工程をその色空間で行うよう
        お勧めします。
        Should you however decide to keep the embedded color profile,
        the image will however still be displayed correctly.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        何らかの事情があって画像にカラープロファイルが埋め込まれていなくても、
        もしその内容をご存知ならば (あるいは推測がつくならば)、 手づから自ら
        画像に書き加えて構いません。
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="gimp-concepts-cm-display">
      <title lang="en">Display</title>
      <title lang="ja">ディスプレイ画面</title>
      <para lang="en">
        For the best results, you need a color profile for your monitor. If a
        monitor profile is configured, either system-wide or in the Color
        Management section of the GIMP Preferences dialog, the image colors
        will be displayed most accurately.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        One of the most important GIMP commands to work with color
        management is described in
        <xref linkend="gimp-display-filter-dialog"/>.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        If you do not have a color profile for your monitor, you can
        create it using hardware calibration and measurement tools. On
        UNIX systems you will need
        <productname>Argyll Color Management System</productname>
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-argyllcms"/> and/or
        <productname>LProf</productname>
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-lprof"/>
        to create color profiles.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        最良の結果を得るためには、 モニタ装置にカラープロファイルが必要です。
        モニタプロファイルの作成は、 システム全般で行うにせよ<acronym>GIMP
        </acronym>環境設定ダイアログの色管理のページで行うにせよ、 いずれの場合
        も画像の色が最も正確に表現されるようになります。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の色管理用の最重要コマンドのひとつが
        <xref linkend="gimp-display-filter-dialog"/> に述べられています。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        お使いのモニタ装置にカラープロファイルが無くても、 装置を測定・計測する
        ツールを使って作成できます。 UNIX系のシステムなら
        <productname>Argyll Color Management System</productname>
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-argyllcms"/> や
        <productname>LProf</productname>
        <xref linkend="bibliography-online-lprof"/>
        がカラープロファイル作成に必要です。
      </para>
      <sect4 id="gimp-concepts-cm-display-profiling">
        <title lang="en">Display Calibration and Profiling</title>
        <title lang="ja">ディスプレイ装置の測定とプロファイル作成</title>
        <indexterm lang="en">
          <primary>Color management</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm lang="en">
          <primary>Color profile</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm lang="ja">
          <primary sortas="イロカンリ">色管理</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm lang="ja">
          <primary>カラープロファイル</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para lang="en">
          For displays there are two steps involved. One is called calibration
          and the other is called profiling. Also, calibration generally
          involves two steps. The first involves adjusting external monitor
          controls such as Contrast, Brightness, Color Temperature, etc, and
          it is highly dependent on the specific monitor. In addition there
          are further adjustments that are loaded into the video card memory
          to bring the monitor as close to a standard state as possible. This
          information is stored in the monitor profile in the so-called vgct
          tag. Probably under Windows XP or Mac OS, the operating system loads
          this information (LUT) in the video card in the process of starting
          your computer. Under Linux, at present you have to use an external
          program such as xcalib or dispwin. (If one just does a simple visual
          calibration using a web site such as that of Norman Koren, one might
          only use xgamma to load a gamma value.)
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          The second step, profiling, derives a set of rules which allow GIMP
          to translate RGB values in the image file into appropriate colors on
          the screen. This is also stored in the monitor profile. It doesn't
          change the RGB values in the image, but it does change which values
          are sent to the video card (which already contains the vgct LUT).
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          ディスプレイ装置には2段階必要です。 第一は測定、 第二はプロファイル
          作成です。 さらに測定には通例2段階必要です。 そのひとつがコントラスト
          や明るさ、 色温度などの外部モニタ制御を調節することですが、 これらは
          モニタの機種に大きく依存しています。 さらにモニタを標準状態にできる
          だけ近づけるためにビデオカードメモリ[画像処理器基盤の記憶装置]に
          読み込ませることになる調整項目があります。 この情報はいわゆる
          <acronym>vgct</acronym>タグ内のモニタプロファイルに保存されます。
          <productname>Windows XP</productname> や <productname>Mac OS
          </productname> では恐らく起動時にオペレーティングシステムがこの情報
          (<acronym>LUT</acronym>[対照表]) をビデオカードに読み込ませる
          はずです。 UNIX系なら今のところ <application>xcalib</application> や
          <application>dispwin<application> のような外部プログラムが必要です
          (Norman Koren氏のウェブサイトの方法のような簡単な視覚的測定をされた
          方は、 ガンマ値は <application>xgamma</application> だけを使って
          読み込ませることになります。)。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          第二段階はプロファイル作成です。 これをもとに<acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          が画像の<acronym>RGB</acronym>値を画面の適正な色に転換するための
          規則集が生成できます。 これはモニタプロファイルにも収められます。
          この転換は画像の<acronym>RGB</acronym>値を変更するのではなく、 ビデオ
          カードに送られる信号内の値を変更しています。 (ビデオカードは既に
          <acronym>vgct</acronym> <acronym>LUT</acronym>を持っている
          ものとします。)
        </para>
      </sect4>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title lang="en">Print Simulation</title>
      <title lang="ja">模擬印刷実験</title>
      <para lang="en">
        Using GIMP, you can easily get a preview of what your image will look
        like on paper. Given a color profile for your printer, the display can
        be switched into Soft Proof mode. In such a simulated printout, colors
        that cannot be reproduced will optionally be marked with neutral gray
        color, allowing you to correct such mistakes before sending your
        images to the printer.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>を使えば、 印刷物での画像の見え方が簡単に
        プレビューできます。 お使いのプリンタからカラープロファイルを得れば、
        ディスプレイ装置は色校正モードに切り替えることが可能になります。
        こういった印刷試演においては性能上再現ができない色は灰色無色で表示
        されるため、 プリンタに画像を送る前にこのような過失が正せます。
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
