<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2011-02-26 Michael added "resolution" and improved "layers"
  2009-03-20 j.h: fixed bug #557343
  2007-02-27 lexa: reorganized concepts
  2006-01-07 HdJ: Added quote and acronym tags, added English and Dutch
             version of layers explanation
  2005-12-18 Lexa: reviewed and added de translation
-->
<!--2012-06-10-->
<sect1 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-concepts-basic">
  <title lang="en">Basic Concepts</title>
  <title lang="ja">基本概念</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Concepts</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="ガイネン">概念</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Wilber, the GIMP mascot</title>
    <title lang="ja">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のマスコットキャラクター Wilber (ウィルバー) 君
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="images/using/wilber.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          The Wilber_Construction_Kit (in src/images/) allows you to give the
          mascot a different appearance. It is the work of Tuomas Kuosmanen
          (tigertATgimp.org).
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>配布ソースの <filename class="directory">
          docs/</filename> ディレクトリーにはこのマスコットの多彩な変身ぶりが
          見られる <filename>Wilber_Construction_Kit.xcf.gz</filename> という
          ファイルがあります。 この絵は Tuomas Kuosmanen 氏
          &lt;tigert AT gimp.org&gt; の作品です。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    This section provides a brief introduction to the basic concepts and
    terminology used in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. The concepts presented here are explained in
    much greater depth elsewhere. With a few exceptions, we have avoided
    cluttering this section with a lot of links and cross-references:
    everything mentioned here is so high-level that you easily 
    locate it in the index.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    この章は<acronym>GIMP</acronym>でつかわれる用語や概念の基本的な
    ことがらを手短に紹介します。 ただし折に触れてもっと詳しい説明も
    いたします。 またこの章においては相互参照やリンクでいっぱいになるのを
    (一部の例外を除き) あえて避けました。 しかし索引から容易に説明へ
    辿り着けるよう、 ここに挙げた内容はいずれも高度にまとめてあります。
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Images</term>
      <term lang="ja">画像</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Images are the basic entities used by <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
          Roughly speaking, an <quote>image</quote> corresponds to a single
          file, such as a TIFF or JPEG file. You can also think of an image
          as corresponding to a single display window (although in truth it
          is possible to have multiple windows all displaying the same image).
          It is not possible to have a single window display more than one
          image, though, or for an image to have no window displaying it.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          A <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image may be quite a complicated thing.
          Instead of thinking of it as a sheet of paper with a
          picture on it, think of it as more like a stack of sheets, called
          <quote>layers</quote>. In addition to a stack of layers, a
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image may contain a selection mask, a set of
          channels, and a set of paths. In fact, <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          provides a mechanism for attaching arbitrary pieces of data, called
          <quote>parasites</quote>, to an image.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, it is possible to have many images open
          at the same time. Although large images may use many megabytes of
          memory, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses a sophisticated
          tile-based memory management system that allows
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to handle very large images gracefully.
          There are limits, however, and having more memory available may
          improve system performance.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像は<acronym>GIMP</acronym>が扱う根源的な要素です。 誤解を恐れずに
          言えば、 ひとつの<quote>画像</quote>が<acronym>TIFF</acronym>や
          <acronym>JPEG</acronym>といった種類のファイルひとつに対応しています。
          画像ひとつにつき画像ウィンドウひとつが対応するという見方もできます。
          (ただし実際はひとつの画像ファイルを複数のウィンドウで同時に開くことも
          可能です。) もちろんひとつのウィンドウのなかでふたつ以上の画像は
          表示できませんが、 一方でウィンドウ表示をしないまま開いている
          画像がありえます。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>形式の画像はいくぶん複雑なものです。
          画像は一枚の紙面に見立てるのではなく、 そのようなシートを
          いくつも重ね合わせたものととらえてください。 その一層一層を
          <quote>レイヤー</quote>と呼びます。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>形式では
          さらに選択マスクや一揃いのチャネル、 数面のパスが画像に含められます。
          じっさい<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は画像に対するいろんな加工を
          ひとつひとつ情報の断片としてとらえる機構があり、 それらを
          画像の<quote>parasites(寄生体)</quote>と呼んでいるのです。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は複数の画像を同時に開いておくことが可能
          です。 大きな画像だと数メガバイトものメモリーを占めるはずですが、 
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>では精巧にタイル分割して
          メモリー管理を行うしくみがあり、 たいへん大きな画像でも流麗に扱える
          ようになっています。 無論これにも限界がありますが、 もっと使える
          メモリーを増やせばシステムの処理能力は高まります。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Layers</term>
      <term lang="ja">レイヤー</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          If a simple image can be compared to a single sheet of paper, an
          image with layers is likened to a sheaf of transparent papers
          stacked one on top of the other. You can draw on each paper, but
          still see the content of the other sheets through the transparent
          areas. You can also move one sheet in relation to the others.
          Sophisticated <acronym>GIMP</acronym> users often deal with images
          containing many layers, even dozens of them.  Layers need not be
          opaque, and they need not cover the entire extent of an image, so
          when you look at an image's display, you may see more than just the
          top layer: you may see elements of many layers.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          簡単な画像なら一枚の紙面に喩えられる一方で、 レイヤーが複数ある
          画像となると紙は半透明もしくは透明でそれが幾層にも重ね合わさった
          紙束のようなものが画像ということになります。
          それぞれの紙面に絵が描けますが、 見える範囲は上の層の透過した
          部分からのみに限られます。 どの紙も場所をずらして重ね位置が
          変えられます。 熟達した<acronym>GIMP</acronym>ユーザーならば、 
          レイヤーが何層にも重なった画像を何十枚と扱うことになるでしょう。
          レイヤーは不透明とは限らず、 しかも画像全体を覆う
          必要もないので、 画像を見たときそこには最前面だけでなく
          その背面側のレイヤーの部品がいくつも見えているかもしれません。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
        <phrase lang="en">Resolution</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ja">解像度</phrase>
        <indexterm lang="en">
          <primary>Resolution</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm lang="ja">
          <primary sortas="カイゾウド">解像度</primary>
        </indexterm>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Digital images comprise of a grid of square elements of varying
          colors, called pixels. Each image has a pixel size, such as 900
          pixels wide by 600 pixels high. But pixels don't have a set size in
          physical space. To set up an image for printing, we use a value
          called resolution, defined as the ratio between an image's size in
          pixels and its physical size (usually in inches) when it is printed
          on paper. Most file formats (but not all) can save this value, which
          is expressed as ppi &mdash; pixels per inch. When printing a file,
          the resolution value determines the size the image will have on
          paper, and as a result, the physical size of the pixelss. The same
          900x600 pixel image may be printed as a small 3x2" card with barely
          noticeable pixels &mdash; or as a large poster with large, chunky
          pixels. Images imported from cameras and mobile devices tend to
          have a resolution value attached to the file. The value is usually
          72 or 96ppi. It is important to realize that this value is arbitrary
          and was chosen for historic reasons. You can always change the
          resolution value inside <acronym>GIMP</acronym> &mdash; this has no
          effect on the actual image pixels. Furthermore, for uses such as
          displaying images on line, on mobile devices, television or video
          games &mdash; in short, any use that is not print &mdash; the
          resolution value is meaningless and is ignored, and instead the
          image is usually displayed so that each image pixel conforms to one
          screen pixel.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          ディジタル画像は方眼図状に並んだいろんな色の正方形の升目の集まりで
          できています。 これらの升目を画素 (ピクセル) といいます。 幅 900 
          ピクセル &times; 高さ 600 ピクセルというふうに画素数で画像の大きさが
          表せます。 しかし画素数のサイズだけでは画像の実寸を示せません。
          画像を印刷するときは解像度という値を用います。 これは画像の大きさを
          示す画素数と印刷物の実寸 (通常はインチ単位) との比率で表されます。
          ほとんどすべてのファイル形式が ppi 値 (<foreignphrase>pixels per
          inch</foreignphrase> - 1 インチあたりの画素数) で解像度を
          保存できます。 ファイルの画像を印刷するとその解像度に従って紙面上での
          大きさが決まるので、 結局これは画素の実寸を示したものともいえます。
          同じ 900&times;600 ピクセルの画像といえど片や 2&times;3 インチ大の
          小さなカードに印刷するのなら画素は個々の見分けがつかないほど小さく
          なるのに、 大きなポスターに引き伸ばして印刷すれば画素が粗く目立つ
          ものになるでしょう。 ディジタルカメラや携帯端末で撮った画像には
          解像度の値が添付されていることがよくあります。 たいていが 72ppi や
          96ppi になっています。 でもこれは歴史的な事情から付けられた値に
          すぎないのだと理解しておくことが大事です。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>に
          かかれば解像度はいつでも変更が可能です。 それでも画像の個々の画素に
          実害はありません。 さらにいえば、 オンラインで画像を表示したり、 
          携帯端末やテレビやビデオゲームで表示させる場合、 つまり端的に言えば
          印刷以外の表示方法であるなら、 解像度という値は意味がないので
          無視され、 いつもはその代わりに画像の画素とディスプレイ装置の画素が
          相応するような等倍率で表示されます。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry id="gimp-concepts-channels" xreflabel="Channels">
      <term>
        <phrase lang="en">Channels</phrase>
        <phrase lang="ja">チャンネル</phrase>
        <indexterm lang="en">
          <primary>Channels</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm lang="ja">
          <primary>チャンネル</primary>
        </indexterm>
      </term>
      <listitem>
        <!--TRANSLATORS: this is the modified text from glossary.xml, so
        you should check po/LANG/glossary.po for an old translation.-->
        <para lang="en">
          A Channel is a single component of a pixel's color. For a colored
          pixel in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, these components are usually Red,
          Green, Blue and sometimes transparency (Alpha). For a
          <link linkend="glossary-graylevel">Grayscale</link> image, they are
          Gray and Alpha and for an
          <link linkend="glossary-indexedcolors">Indexed</link> color image,
          they are Indexed and Alpha.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          The entire rectangular array of any one of the color components for
          all of the pixels in an image is also referred to as a Channel. You
          can see these color channels with the
          <link linkend="gimp-channel-dialog">Channels dialog</link>.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          When the image is displayed, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> puts these
          components together to form the pixel colors for the screen,
          printer, or other output device. Some output devices may use
          different channels from Red, Green and Blue. If they do,
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s channels are converted into the
          appropriate ones for the device when the image is displayed.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          Channels can be useful when you are working on an image which needs
          adjustment in one particular color. For example, if you want to
          remove <quote>red eye</quote> from a photograph, you might work on
          the Red channel.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          You can look at channels as masks which allow or restrict the output
          of the color that the channel represents. By using Filters on the
          channel information, you can create many varied and subtle effects
          on an image. A simple example of using a Filter on the color
          channels is the
          <link linkend="plug-in-colors-channel-mixer">Channel Mixer</link>
          filter.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          In addition to these channels, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> also allows
          you to create other channels (or more correctly, Channel Masks),
          which are displayed in the lower part of the Channels dialog. You
          can create a <link linkend="gimp-channel-new">New channel</link> or
          save a <link linkend="gimp-selection-to-channel">selection to a
          channel (mask)</link>.
          See the glossary entry on
          <link linkend="glossary-masks">Masks</link> for more information
          about Channel Masks.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          チャンネルとは画素の色成分ひとつを示すことばです。 
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>で扱う色つき画素は、 通常は赤・緑・青の
          色成分と、 必須ではありませんが透過効果 (アルファ) 成分によって
          構成されます。 
          <link linkend="glossary-graylevel">グレースケール</link> 画像は灰色
          陰影のチャンネルとアルファチャンネルで、
          <link linkend="glossary-indexedcolors">インデックス化</link> カラー
          画像はインデックス化カラーマップとアルファチャンネルで
          構成されています。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          なに色の成分であっても、 画像の全ての画素の色から値を抽出して四角い
          画面一杯の全体像にすればそれはチャンネルです。 このような
          色チャンネルのようすは
          <link linkend="gimp-channel-dialog">チャンネルダイアログ</link> 上で
          見られます。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像を表示するとき、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は色成分を画面や
          プリンターをはじめとする出力デバイスに合わせて再編成します。 一部の
          出力デバイスは赤・緑・青とは異なる色チャンネル構成を使用しています。
          このようなデバイスで画像が表示されるとき、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の
          チャンネルはそのデバイスに最適なものへ変換されます。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          ある特定の画像の色を調節したいとき、 チャンネルを利用すると便利です。 
          たとえば写真から<quote>赤目</quote>を除去したいときは、 赤チャンネルで
          作業するとよいでしょう。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          チャンネルがもつ色だけに着目できることから、 チャンネルはその色の出力
          マスクとしても活用できます。 チャンネルの情報にフィルタをかければ、 
          多種多様で繊細な効果を画像につけられます。 色チャンネルにフィルターを
          かける単純な例として
          <link linkend="plug-in-colors-channel-mixer">チャンネルミキサー</link>
          フィルターがあります。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          3 つの色チャンネルに加え、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>では他にもチャンネル
           (正確にはチャンネルマスク) を作成できます。 これらはチャンネル
          ダイアログの下側に表示されます。 新しい
          <link linkend="gimp-channel-new">チャンネルを追加</link> したり
          選択範囲を 
          <link linkend="gimp-selection-to-channel">チャンネルに保存</link> 
          することもできます。 この他のチャンネルについての情報は用語集の 
          <xref linkend="glossary-masks"/> の項でご覧ください。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Selections</term>
      <term lang="ja">選択</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Often when modify an image, you only want a part of the image
          to be affected. The <quote>selection</quote>
          mechanism makes this possible. Each image has its own selection,
          which you normally see as a moving dashed line separating the
          selected parts from the unselected parts (the so-called
          <quote>marching ants</quote> ). Actually this is a bit misleading:
          selection in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          is graded, not all-or-nothing, and really the selection is
          represented by a full-fledged grayscale channel. The dashed line
          that you normally see is simply a contour line at the 50%-selected
          level. At any time, though, you can visualize the selection channel
          in all its glorious detail by toggling the
          <link linkend="gimp-image-window-qmask-button">QuickMask</link>
          button.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          A large component of learning how to use <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          effectively is acquiring the art of making good
          selections—selections that contain exactly what you need and nothing
          more. Because selection-handling is so centrally important,
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> provides many tools for doing
          it: an assortment of selection-making tools, a menu of selection
          operations, and the ability to switch to Quick Mask mode, in which
          you can treat the selection channel as though it were a color
          channel, thereby <quote>painting the selection</quote>.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像に手を加えるとき、 画像の一部に限定して作業したくなることが
          よくあります。 <quote>選択</quote>のしくみはこのためにあります。 
          選択範囲は画像ごとに作れて、 通常は明滅する点線が選択範囲と
          非選択範囲とを分けているのがそれです。 ただし本当はこれですべてでは
          ありません。 実際<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の選択は一切か無かの二分論に
          留まらぬ高度なもので、 その実体はよく描き込まれたグレースケール
          チャンネルなのです。 点線が示しているのは選択の強度が 50% のレベルを
          なぞった単なる輪郭線にすぎません。 ところが
          <link linkend="gimp-image-window-qmask-button">クイックマスク</link>
          ボタンを押すだけで選択チャネルが可視化されいつでもそのすばらしい
          詳細がご覧になれます。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の扱い方の秘訣のほとんどは、 選択範囲をいかに
          思い描いたとおりに選択するかということと不可分です。 選択範囲の
          とりかたこそが重要なカギを握っており、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>はこの
          機構に係る道具を数多く用意しています。 数々の選択ツール、 選択作業の
          メニュー、 さらにはクイックマスクモードに切り替えるボタン―-
          このモードでは選択チャンネルがまるで色のチャンネルであるかのように
          <quote>選択を描く</quote>ことも可能なのです。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Undoing</term>
      <term lang="ja">取り消し</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          When you make mistakes, you can undo them. Nearly everything you can
          do to an image is undoable. In fact, you can usually undo a
          substantial number of the most recent things you did, if you decide
          that they were misguided. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> makes this
          possible by keeping a history of your actions. This history consumes
          memory, though, so undoability is not infinite. Some actions use
          very little undo memory, so that you can do dozens of them before
          the earliest ones are deleted from this history; other types of
          actions require massive amounts of undo memory. You can configure
          the amount of memory <acronym>GIMP</acronym> allows for the undo
          history of each image, but in any situation, you should always be
          able to undo at least your 2-3 most recent actions. (The most
          important action that is not undoable is closing an image. For this
          reason, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> asks you to confirm that you really
          want to close the image if you have made any changes to it.)
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          何か失敗したら、 取り消しましょう。画像に加えた作業はほとんど全て
          取り消しができます。 失敗に気付いたときに、 仮にそこまでかなりの
          手数を経ていてもやはり取り消せるのです。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は
          このために作業履歴を録っています。 メモリーを消費するとはいえ、 
          履歴は無制限です。 履歴は最も古いものから順に消されてゆきますが、
          数十手もの取り消しを可能にするため一部の動作についてはメモリーの
          消費を極めて小さくしてできるだけ多く履歴が残るようにしています。
          しかし莫大なメモリを履歴のために消費する動作もあります。 
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>では一画像あたりの履歴用メモリーの上限を設定
          できるようにしてありますが、 そのままでも少なくとも 2 〜 3 手まで
          戻れます。 (履歴の及ばない重大な動作に<quote>画像を閉じる</quote>が
          あります。 このため<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は何かしら操作が
          加えられた画像を閉じる際には確認を求めるようにしています。)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Plug-ins</term>
      <term lang="ja">プラグイン</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Many, probably most, of the things that you do to an image in
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> are done by the <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          application itself. However, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> also makes
          extensive use of <quote>plug-ins</quote>, which are external programs
          that interact very closely with <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, and are
          capable of manipulating images and other <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          objects in very sophisticated ways. Many important plug-ins are
          bundled with <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, but there are also
          many available by other means. In fact, writing
          plug-ins (and scripts) is the easiest way for people not on the
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym> development team to add new capabilities to
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
        </para>
        <para lang="en">
          All of the commands in the Filters menu, and a substantial number of
          commands in other menus, are actually implemented as plug-ins.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          画像を<acronym>GIMP</acronym>で加工するうえで、 大多数の工程は
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>自身が行いますが、 さらに
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>と密接に連携する<quote>プラグイン</quote>と
          呼ばれる外部プログラムを利用し、 より洗練された方法で画像や
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の部品を処理するしくみが備わっています。
          多くの重要なプラグインは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>に同梱されていますが、
          別口で入手できるものも多数あります。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>に
          新機能を追加するというと大変そうですが、 実はプラグインを
          (スクリプトも) 書くのは簡単なので
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の開発スタッフでなくてもできてしまいます。
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          実際フィルターメニューの全コマンドと、 その他のメニューの
          かなりの数のコマンドが、 プラグインで実装されています。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Scripts</term>
      <term lang="ja">スクリプト</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          In addition to plug-ins, which are programs written in the C
          language, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> can also make use of scripts. The
          largest number of
          existing scripts are written in a language called Script-Fu, which
          is unique to <acronym>GIMP</acronym> (for those who care, it is a
          dialect of the
          Lisp-like language called Scheme). It is also possible to write
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          scripts in Python or Perl. These languages are more flexible and
          powerful than Script-Fu; their disadvantage is that they depend on
          software that does not automatically come packaged with
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, so
          they are not guaranteed to work correctly in every
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
          installation.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          プラグインは C 言語で書かれますが、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>では
          スクリプト言語も使えます。いま大多数のスクリプトは Script-Fu という
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>特有の言語で書かれています。 (ご興味のある方に
          ひとこと: これは Scheme と呼ばれる Lisp 風言語の方言です。)
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>では Python や Perl で書かれたスクリプトも
          使用可能です。これらの言語ならば Script-Fu よりも柔軟で強力ですが、
          ひとつ問題があって、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>をインストールした
          ところでこれらの言語のシステムが自動的に設置され利用可能となる
          わけではないので、 そのスクリプトが直ちに動作する保証はありません。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect1>
