<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2007-05-28 Fixed Auto Follow Active Image by j.h
  2005-12-18 reviewed by lexa
-->
<!--2012-05-03-->
<sect2 id="gimp-concepts-docks">
  <title lang="en">Dialogs and Docking</title>
  <title lang="ja">ダイアログとその合体</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Docking</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Dialogs</primary>
    <secondary>Docking</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="ガッタイ">合体</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ダイアログ</primary>
    <secondary sortas="ガッタイ">合体</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3 id="gimp-dockable-dock-bars">
    <title lang="en">Organizing Dialogs</title>
    <title lang="ja">ダイアログを整頓</title>

    <para lang="en">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has great flexibility for arranging dialog on
      your screen. A <quote>dialog</quote> is a moving window which
      contains options for a tool or is dedicated to a special task. A
      <quote>dock</quote> is a container which can hold a collection of
      persistent dialogs, such as the Tool Options dialog, Brushes dialog,
      Palette dialog, etc. Docks cannot, however, hold non-persistent dialogs
      such as the Preferences dialog or the New Image dialog.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は画面上のダイアログを極めて柔軟に配置できます。 
      ダイアログは移動可能なウィンドウの一種であり、 ツールのオプションが
      並んでいるウィンドウ、 あるいはある特定の作業の専用ウィンドウのことを
      そう呼びます。 ドックとは、 ツールオプションダイアログや
      ブラシダイアログやパレットダイアログ等の常設ダイアログを重ねあわせて
      保持する容器ウィンドウのことです。 ただし設定ダイアログや
      画像ウィンドウのような非常設ダイアログは入れられません。
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym> has three default docks:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            the Tool Options dock under the Toolbox in the left panel,
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            the Layers, Channels, Paths and Undo dock in the upper part of the
            right panel,
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            the Brushes, Patterns and Gradients dock in the lower part of the
            right panel.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      In these docks, each dialog is in its own tab.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は初期状態で 3 種類のドックがつきます。
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            左のパネルではツールボックスの下にツールオプションが連結
            (ドッキング)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            右のパネル上半分はレイヤー, チャンネル, パス, 作業履歴のドック
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            右のパネル下半分はブラシ, パターン, グラデーションのドック
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      いずれのドックでもダイアログがタブ化されています。
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      In multi-window mode, the Toolbox is a <emphasis>utility
      window</emphasis> and not a dock. In single-window mode, it belongs to
      the single window.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      マルチウィンドウモードの場合、 ツールボックスは
      <emphasis>補助ウィンドウ</emphasis> です。 ドックではありません。
      シングルウィンドウモードの場合、 ツールボックスはウィンドウの中の一部と
      なります。
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Use
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Dockable Dialogs</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      to view a list of dockable dialogs. Select a dockable dialog from
      the list to view the dialog. If the dialog is available in a dock,
      then it is made visible. If the dialog is not in a dock, the behavior
      is different in multi and single window modes:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In multi-window mode, a new window, containing the dialog, appears
            on the screen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In single-window mode, the dialog is automatically docked to the
            Layers-Undo dock as a tab.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ドッキング可能なウィンドウの一覧表は
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>ウィンドウ</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>ドッキング可能なダイアログ</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      のサブメニューにあります。 この一覧表でダイアログを選ぶとそのダイアログが
      現れます。 既にどれかのドックにそのダイアログが入っていた場合は隠れた
      ダイアログならば表に見えるように出てきます。 まだそのダイアログが開かれて
      いなかった場合の挙動については、 ウィンドウモードが複数ウィンドウのときと
      単一ウィンドウのときとでつぎのように異なった反応を見せます。
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            マルチウィンドウモードの場合、 選んたダイアログが入っている
            新しいウィンドウが画面に登場します。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            シングルウィンドウモードの場合、 選んだダイアログは自動的にタブ化
            して<quote>レイヤー, チャンネル, パス, 作業履歴</quote>ドックに
            加わります。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      You can click-and-drag a tab and drop it in the wanted place:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            either in the tab bar of a dock, to integrate it in the dialog
            group,
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            or on a docking bar that appears as a blue line when the mouse     
            pointer goes over a dock border, to anchor the dialog to the dock.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      タブはクリックしたままドラッグできます。 そのまま任意のドックまで
      曳いてきて、
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            ドックのタブバーが色を換えて反応する位置で放つとそこのダイアログ
            群に統合されます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            ドックの 4 辺のいずれかが (図では青い線に色を換えて) ドッキングバー
            を顕して反応する位置で放つと、 ダイアログはドックに接合します。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para lang="en">
      In multi-window mode, you can also click on the dialog title and drag it
      to the wanted place.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      マルチウィンドウモードであればダイアログのタイトルをクリックしたまま
      ドラッグすれば任意の位置へ移動できます。
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Integrating a new dialog in a dialog group</title>
      <title lang="ja">新たにダイアログをダイアロググループへ統合</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/dock-integrate-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            Here, in multi-window mode, the Histogram dialog was dragged to the
            tab bar of the Layers-Undo dock.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            マルチウィンドウモードでヒストグラムダイアログを
            <quote>レイヤー, チャンネル, パス, 作業履歴</quote>ドックの
            タブバーに曳き入れる様子
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para lang="en">
      More simpler: the <command>Add tab</command> command in the Tab menu <xref
      linkend="gimp-dockable-menu"/>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      単純な方法ですが、 タブメニュー
      <xref linkend="gimp-dockable-menu"/> の
      <guimenuitem>タブを追加</guimenuitem> コマンドも使えます。
    </para>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Anchoring a dialog to a dock border</title>
      <title lang="ja">ドックの縁にダイアログを連結</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/dock-anchor-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para lang="en">
            The Histogram dialog dragged to the left vertical docking bar and
            the result: the dialog anchored to the left border of the
            Layers-Undo dock (this dialog now belongs to the right panel).
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            So, you can arrange dialogs in a <emphasis>multi-column</emphasis>
            display, interesting if you work with two screens, one for dialogs,
            the other for images.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            ヒストグラムダイアログを左側面ドッキングバーまでドラッグした
            様子と結果:
            [統合されタブ化していた]ダイアログがこんどは<quote>レイヤー,
            チャンネル, パス, 作業履歴</quote>ドックの左隣に連結された
            (そしてこのダイアログは右のパネルの一部となった)
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            こうして
            <emphasis>ダイアログは縦にも横にも繋げられるので</emphasis>、
            2 枚のディスプレイモニターを利用している環境なら片方の画面に
            ダイアログ類をまとめ、 もう一方の画面をすべて
            作画用に充てる使い方もできる
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <tip>
      <para lang="en">
        Press <keycap>TAB</keycap> in an Image window to toggle the
        visibility of the docks. This is useful if the docks hide a portion
        of the image window. You can quickly hide all the docks,
        do your work, then display all the docks again.
        Pressing <keycap>TAB</keycap> inside a dock to navigate
        through the dock.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        画像ウィンドウ上で <keycap>Tab</keycap> キーを押すたびにツールボックス
        とすべてのドックは隠れた状態と開いた状態が切り替わります。 この機能は
        ドックが画像の一部を覆い隠してしまったときに使えます。 さっとドックを
        片づけて作業をすすめたあと、 再び元通りにドックを表示できるのです。
        ドック上で <keycap>Tab</keycap> キーを押した場合はドック内の焦点が
        移動巡回します。
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-dock-image-menu">
    <title lang="en">Image Selection</title>
    <title lang="ja">画像選択メニュー</title>
    <anchor id="gimp-dock-auto-button" xreflabel="Auto button"/>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Docks</primary>
      <secondary>Auto button</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary>ドック</primary>
      <secondary sortas="ジドウボタン">自動ボタン</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para lang="en">
      Some docks contain an <emphasis>Image Selection Menu</emphasis>:
      a menu listing all of the images open in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      The Image Menu displays the name of the image whose information
      is shown in the dock.
      Use the <guilabel>Auto</guilabel> button to toggle the value of
      <guilabel>Auto Follow Active Image</guilabel>.
      Suppose you are using the Layers dialog and you want to see
      the layers for a different image. Select the desired image from the
      Image Selection Menu. Although this is convenient, do not forget that
      you changed the working image for the dock. Setting
      <guilabel>Auto Follow Active Image</guilabel> from the Tab menu
      helps to avoid this problem.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      一部のドックには<acronym>GIMP</acronym>が読み込んだ画像全てを一覧にした
      <emphasis>画像選択メニュー</emphasis> がついています。 このメニューには、
      現在ドックで表示されている画像の名前が表示されます。 
      <guilabel>自動</guilabel> ボタンを使うとタブメニューの 
      <guimenuitem>アクティブな画像を自動的に追跡</guimenuitem> の状態が切り
      替わります。 例えばレイヤーダイアログを使っていて別々の画像のレイヤーを
      見たいというときなどは、 画像選択メニューを使って見たい画像に切り替えると
      よいでしょう。 とても便利な反面、 ドックで表示する画像を他の画像に切り
      替えたことを忘れないようにする必要があります。 この問題はタブメニューの 
      <guimenuitem>アクティブな画像を自動的に追跡</guimenuitem> を有効にすると
      回避できます。
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      By default, a <quote>Layers, Channels, and Paths</quote>
      dock shows an Image Menu at the top, and other types of docks do not.
      You can always add or remove an Image Menu, however, using the
      <quote>Show Image Menu</quote> toggle in the Tab menu, as described
      below. (Exception: you
      cannot add an Image Menu to the dock that contains the Toolbox.)
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      初期設定では<quote>レイヤー, チャンネル, パス</quote>の各ダイアログを
      まとめたドックにはその最上部に画像選択メニューがついていて、 他のドック
      にはそれがありません。 画像選択メニューは後で述べる 
      <guilabel>画像選択ボックスの表示</guilabel> メニューで
      ドック上に表示したり隠したりできます。 (ただし、
      ツールボックスを含むドックには画像選択メニューを加えられません。)
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="gimp-dockable-menu">
    <title lang="en">Tab Menu</title>
    <title lang="ja">タブメニュー</title>
    <indexterm lang="en">
      <primary>Docks</primary>
      <secondary>Tab menu</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm lang="ja">
      <primary>ドック</primary>
      <secondary>タブメニュー</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">
        A dialog in a dock, with the Tab menu button highlighted.
      </title>
      <title lang="ja">
        ドック内のダイアログ。 そのタブメニューを強調してある。
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/dialog-highlight-tabmenu.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para lang="en">
      In each dialog, you can access a special menu of tab-related operations
      by pressing the Tab Menu button, as highlighted in the figure above.
      Exactly which commands are shown in the menu varies a bit from
      dialog to dialog, but they always include operations for creating new
      tabs, or closing or detaching tabs.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ダイアログにはいずれもタブメニューボタンがあって、 これを押すとそのタブに
      関連した操作ができるようになっています。 上図はこの部分を強調しています。
      メニューはその属するダイアログによって内容コマンドが少しづつ異なって
      いますが、 いずれも新規タブの生成および消去と分離の指示が含まれます。
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">The Tab menu of the Layers dialog.</title>
      <title lang="ja">レイヤーダイアログのタブメニュー</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/tab-menu.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para lang="en">
      The Tab menu gives you access to the following commands:
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">タブメニューで提供されるコマンドは次のとおり。</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Context Menu</term>
        <term lang="ja">脈絡メニュー (直接関連のあるメニュー)</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Context Menu</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>ドック</primary>
            <secondary sortas="ミャクラクメニュー">脈絡メニュー</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            At the top of each Tab menu, an entry opens the
            dialog's context menu, which contains operations specific to that
            particular type of dialog. For example, the context menu for the
            Layers tab is <guilabel>Layers Menu</guilabel>, which contains
            a set of operations for manipulating layers.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            タブメニューの最初の項目はダイアログの機能に関連のある項目を
            まとめた脈絡メニューです。 たとえば、 レイヤータブの脈絡メニュー
            <guisubmenu>レイヤー</guisubmenu> にはレイヤーを操作する項目が
            揃っています。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-tab-add">
        <term lang="en">Add Tab</term>
        <term lang="ja">タブの追加</term>
        <listitem>
          <!--<anchor id="gimp-dock-tab-add"/>-->
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Add Tab</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>ドック</primary>
            <secondary sortas="タブノツイカ">タブの追加</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            <guilabel>Add Tab</guilabel> opens into a submenu allowing you to
            add a large variety of dockable dialogs as new tabs.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <guisubmenu>タブの追加</guisubmenu> はドック入りが可能な
            ダイアログを一覧にまとめたサブメニューを開き、 ここで選んだ
            ダイアログはタブ化して追加されます。
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title lang="en"><quote>Add tab</quote> sub-menu</title>
            <title lang="ja"><quote>タブの追加</quote>サブメニュー</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/using/tab-menu-add-tab.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-tab-close">
        <term lang="en">Close Tab</term>
        <term lang="ja">タブを閉じる</term>
        <listitem>
          <!--<anchor id="gimp-dock-tab-close"/>-->
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Close tab</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>ドック</primary>
            <secondary sortas="タブヲトジル">タブを閉じる</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            Close the dialog. Closing the last dialog in a dock
            causes the dock itself to close.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            ダイアログを閉じます。 最後の一つのダイアログを閉じたときは
            ドックも閉じます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-tab-detach">
        <term lang="en">Detach Tab</term>
        <term lang="ja">タブの切り放し</term>
        <listitem>
          <!--<anchor id="gimp-dock-tab-detach"/>-->
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Detach tab</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>ドック</primary>
            <secondary sortas="タブノキリハナシ">タブの切り放し</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            Detache the dialog from the dock, creating a new dock
            with the detached dialog as its only member. It has the same
            effect as dragging the tab out of the dock and releasing it at a
            location where it cannot be docked.
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            It's a way to create a paradoxical new window in single-window mode!
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            If the tab is <link linkend="gimp-dock-tab-lock">locked</link>,
            this menu item is insensitive and grayed out.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            この項目はダイアログをドックから切り離し、 そのダイアログだけが
            入った新たなドックをつくります。 このメニュー項目はタブをクリック
            してドックの及ばないところまでドラッグし出すのと同じ効果があります。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            新しいドックウィンドウをつくるといいましたが、 シングルウィンドウ
            モードの場合は厳密に言えば新しいドック区画の作成となります。
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            タブが
            <link linkend="gimp-dock-tab-lock">ロック</link> されると
            このメニュー項目は灰色無効になり使用できません。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-tab-lock">
        <term lang="en">Lock tab to Dock</term>
        <term lang="ja">タブのロック</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Lock tab</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>ドック</primary>
            <secondary sortas="タブノロック">タブのロック</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            Prevent the dialog from being moved or detached. When activated,
            <guimenuitem>Detach Tab</guimenuitem> is insensitive and grayed
            out.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            ダイアログの移動や切り放しを禁じます。 これが有効なときは 
            <guimenuitem>タブの切り放し</guimenuitem> 
            メニュー項目を灰色無効にして使用できなくします。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-preview-size">
        <term lang="en">Preview Size</term>
        <term lang="ja">プレビューサイズ</term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Previews</primary>
            <secondary>Tab preview size</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Layer</primary>
            <secondary>Preview size</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>プレビュー</primary>
            <secondary sortas="サイズヲヘンコウ">サイズを変更</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>レイヤー</primary>
            <secondary>プレビューサイズ</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <figure>
            <title lang="en">Preview Size submenu of a Tab menu.</title>
            <title lang="ja">
              タブメニューよりプレビューサイズ-サブメニュー
            </title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/using/tab-menu-preview-size.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Preview size</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>ドック</primary>
            <secondary>プレビューサイズ</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            Many, but not all, dialogs have Tab menus containing a
            <guilabel>Preview Size</guilabel>
            option, which opens into a submenu giving a list of sizes for the
            items in the dialog (see the figure above).
            For example, the Brushes dialog shows pictures of all available
            brushes: the Preview Size determines how large the pictures are.
            The default is <guilabel>Medium</guilabel>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            大多数のダイアログはそのタブメニューに <guisubmenu>プレビューサイズ
            </guisubmenu> の項目があり、 このサブメニューはダイアログ内で
            扱われる絵や図形の大きさを選べるリストになっています (上図参照)。 
            たとえば、 ブラシダイアログには利用できるたくさんのブラシが絵で
            表されていますが、プレビューサイズとはこういった絵の大きさのことを
            指しています。 初期設定値は <guimenuitem>中間</guimenuitem> です。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-tab-style">
        <term lang="en">Tab Style</term>
        <term lang="ja">タブの見出し</term>
        <listitem>
          <figure>
            <title lang="en">Tab Style submenu of a Tab menu.</title>
            <title lang="ja">タブメニューよりタブの見出し-サブメニュー</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                  fileref="images/using/tab-menu-tab-style.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>Tab style</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>ドック</primary>
            <secondary sortas="タブノミダシ">タブの見出し</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            Available only when multiple dialogs are in the same dock,
            <guilabel>Tab Stype</guilabel> opens a submenu allowing you
            to choose the appearance of the tabs at the top (see the figure
            above). There are five choices, not all are available for every
            dialog:
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            複数のダイアログが同じドックに入っているときにこの項目が
            サブメニューとして現れます。 ここでタブの爪の姿を選択できます 
            (上図参照)。 5つの選択肢がありますが、 そのすべてがどんな
            ダイアログにでも適用できるのではありません。
          </para>
          <para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term lang="en">Icon</term>
                <term lang="ja">アイコン</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para lang="en">
                    Use an icon to represent the dialog type.
                  </para>
                  <para lang="ja">
                    ダイアログの種類を表すアイコンのみを表示します。
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term lang="en">Current Status</term>
                <term lang="ja">現在の状態</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para lang="en">
                    <guilabel>Current Status</guilabel>
                    is only available for dialogs that allows you
                    to select something, such as a brush, pattern,
                    gradient, etc. <guilabel>Current Status</guilabel>
                    shows a representation of the currently selected
                    item in the tab top.
                  </para>
                  <para lang="ja">
                    <guilabel>現在の状態</guilabel>
                    はブラシやパターンやグラデーションのような
                    画材を選ぶダイアログに対してのみ有効です。
                    選ばれた画材がタブの爪に表示されます。
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term lang="en">Text</term>
                <term lang="ja">文字</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para lang="en">
                    Use text to display the dialog type.
                  </para>
                  <para lang="ja">
                    ダイアログの種類をタブの爪に文字で表わします。
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term lang="en">Icon and Text</term>
                <term lang="ja">アイコンと文字</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para lang="en">
                    Using both an icon and text results in wider tabs.
                  </para>
                  <para lang="ja">
                    アイコンと文字の両方で表示しますので
                    タブの爪が横長になります。
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term lang="en">Status and Text</term>
                <term lang="ja">状態と文字</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para lang="en">
                    Show the currently selected item and text with the dialog
                    type.
                  </para>
                  <para lang="ja">
                    これは現在選択されている画材を示すアイコンと、
                    ダイアログの種類を表す文字とを表示します。
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-view-as-list">
        <term lang="en">View as List; View as Grid</term>
        <term lang="ja">一覧で表示, 並べて表示</term>
        <listitem>
          <anchor id="gimp-dock-view-as-grid" xreflabel="View as Grid"/>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>Docks</primary>
            <secondary>View as List/Grid</secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="en">
            <primary>List search field</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary>ドック</primary>
            <secondary sortas="ナラベテヒョウジ/イチランデヒョウジ">
              並べて表示/一覧で表示
            </secondary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm lang="ja">
            <primary sortas="ケンサクマド">検索窓</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para lang="en">
            These entries are shown in dialogs that allow you to select an
            item from a set: brushes, patterns, fonts, etc. You can choose
            to view the items as a vertical list, with the name of
            each beside it, or as a grid, with representations of the items
            but no names. Each has its advantages: viewing as a list gives you
            more information, but viewing as a grid allows you to see
            more possibilities at once. The default for this varies across
            dialogs: for brushes and patterns, the default is a grid; for most
            other things, the default is a list.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            この二つの項目が現れるダイアログは、 ブラシやパターンやフォント 
            など、 一揃いからひとつの細目を選択する一覧表があるダイアログです。 
            細目とその名前の組を縦排列に並べるか、 名前を省き細目を升目状に
            並べるかを選べます。 それぞれに利点があり、 縦排列にすれば
            その名前まで詳しくわかりますが、 升目状ならば一度により多くの
            選択肢を見て選べます。 初期設定は一律にしませんでした。
            ブラシやパターンのダイアログは升目状に、
            それ以外のほとんどのダイアログは縦排列にしてあります。
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            When the tree-view is <guilabel>View as List</guilabel>, you can
            use tags. Please see <xref linkend="gimp-tagging"/>.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            <guimenuitem>一覧で表示</guimenuitem> を選択しているときはタグが
            利用できます。 使い方は
            <xref linkend="gimp-tagging"/> でご覧ください。
          </para>

          <para lang="en">
            You can also use a list search field:
            <figure>
              <title>The list search field.</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="images/using/list-search-field.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>
                    Use
                    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo>.
                    to open the list search field.
                  </para>
                </caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            リストの検索窓も利用できます。
            <figure>
              <title>検索窓</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="images/using/list-search-field.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                  <para>
                    検索窓を開くにはキーボードショートカット 
                    <keycombo>
                      <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F</keycap>
                    </keycombo> 
                    を使う
                  </para>
                </caption>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </para>
          <para lang="en">
            The list search field automatically closes after five seconds
            if you do nothing.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            この検索窓は何も操作がない時間が 5 秒を過ぎると自動的に閉じます。
          </para>
          <note>
            <para lang="en">
              The search field shortcut is also available for the tree-view you
              get in the <quote>Brush</quote>, <quote>Font</quote> or
              <quote>Pattern</quote> option of several tools.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              いろいろなツールのダイアログ上の<quote>ブラシ</quote>、 
              <quote>フォント</quote>、 <quote>パターン</quote>を選ぶオプション
              の一覧表で検索窓を呼び出せるショートカットが利用できます。
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry id="gimp-dock-show-button-bar">
        <term lang="en">Show Button Bar</term>
        <term lang="ja">ボタンバーの表示</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            Some dialogs display a button bar on the bottom of the dialog; for
            example, the Patterns, Brushes, Gradients, and Images dialogs.
            This is a toggle. If it is checked, then the Button Bar is
            displayed.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            ダイアログのいくつかはその底部にボタンバーが表示できるようになって
            います。 たとえばパターン、 ブラシ、 グラデーションのダイアログに
            あります。 これは切り替え式になっていて、 チェックが入っている場合
            にボタンバーが表示されます。
          </para>
          <figure>
            <title lang="en">Button Bar on the Brushes dialog.</title>
            <title lang="ja">ブラシダイアログのボタンバー</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata format="PNG"
                           fileref="images/using/dialog-button-bar.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Show Image Selection</term>
        <term lang="ja">画像選択ボックスの表示</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This option is available in multi-window mode only.
            This is a toggle. If it is checked, then an Image Menu is shown at
            the top of the dock:
            <figure id="figure-highlight-imagemenu">
              <title>A dock with an Image Menu highlighted.</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/using/dialog-highlight-imagemenu.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            It is not available for dialogs docked below the Toolbox. This
            option is interesting only if you have several open images on your
            screen.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このオプションはマルチウィンドウモードでのみ現れます。
            これは二者択一です。 チェックを入れているときは、 画像メニューが
            ドックの上部に置かれます。
            <figure id="figure-highlight-imagemenu">
              <title>ドック。 画像メニューを強調してある。</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata format="PNG"
                    fileref="images/using/dialog-highlight-imagemenu.png"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            ただしツールボックス下に合体したダイアログ上では指定できません。
            このオプションは画面に複数の画像を開いている場合にだけ意味が
            あります。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term lang="en">Auto Follow Active Image</term>
        <term lang="ja">アクティブな画像を自動的に追跡</term>
        <listitem>
          <para lang="en">
            This option is available in multi-window mode only.
            This option is also interesting only if you have several images
            open on your screen. Then, the information displayed in a dock
            is always that of the selected image in the Image Selection
            drop-down list. If the <guilabel>Auto Follow Active Image
            </guilabel> is disabled, the image can be selected only in the
            Image Selection. If enabled, you  can also select it by
            activating the image directly (clicking on its title bar).
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            このオプションはマルチウィンドウモードでのみ現れます。
            このオプションも画面に複数の画像を開いている場合にだけ意味が
            あります。 このときには画像選択メニューに表示されている画像とドック
            内の各ダイアログが表示している画像が常に同一です。 もし仮に
            <guimenuitem>アクティブな画像を自動的に追跡</guimenuitem> 
            を無効にしていたときは、 画像を選択できるのは画像選択メニューだけに
            なります。 もし有効ならば、 画像を直接活性化 (つまり画像
            ウィンドウのタイトルバーをクリック) しても画像を選択できます。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
