<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2009-02-19 j.h: revised for v2.6. No change
  2008-04-04 Mr.Dust : reviewed and added 'ko'
  2006-05-08 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-04-30 HdJ: added dutch translation.
  2006-04-10 Ciampix: added italian translation.
  2006-03-04 Lexa: added german translation and made docbook compliant.
  2005-11-28 Lexa: replaced informalfigures by figures.
  2005-05-08 added french translation
-->
<!--2009-07-02-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-gradients">
  <title lang="en">Gradients</title>
  <title lang="ja">グラデーション</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Gradient</primary>
    <secondary>Overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>グラデーション</primary>
    <secondary sortas="ガイカン">概観</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Some examples of GIMP gradients.</title>
    <title lang="ja"><acronym>GIMP</acronym>グラデーションの例</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/gradient-examples.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          Gradients from top to bottom: FG to BG (RGB); Full saturation
          spectrum; Nauseating headache; Browns; Four bars
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          いろいろなグラデーションを上から順に: 描画色から背景色へ
          (<acronym>RGB</acronym>); Full saturation spectrum;
          Nauseating headache; Browns; Four bars
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    A <emphasis>gradient</emphasis>
    is a set of colors arranged in a linear order. The most basic use of
    gradients is by the <link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">Blend tool</link>,
    sometimes known as the <quote>gradient tool</quote> or <quote>gradient
    fill tool</quote>: it works
    by filling the selection with colors from a gradient. You have many
    options to choose from for controlling the way the gradient colors are
    arranged within the selection. There are also other important ways to use
    gradients, including:
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <emphasis>グラデーション</emphasis> とは漸進的に変化する直線的な配色順の
    ことです。 グラデーションの最も基本的な利用法は、 <quote>グラデーション
    ツール</quote>や<quote>グラデーション塗りつぶしツール</quote>の異名がある
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">ブレンドツール</link> に依っています。
    このツールが選択範囲を塗りつぶすのにグラデーションから色を得ているのです。
    選べるツールオプションがたくさんあって、 選択範囲の内側でグラデーションを
    どんな形状や規則で描くかを調整できるようになっています。 このツール以外
    にも以下のような重要なグラデーションの利用方法があります。
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">Painting with a gradient</term>
      <term lang="ja">グラデーションで描画</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
          Each of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s basic painting tools allows you
          the option of using
          colors from a gradient. This enables you to create brushstrokes that
          change color from one end to the other.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の基本的な描画ツールはいずれもグラデーション
          から色を得るオプションがあります。 有効にすると筆運びの始めから終り
          まで色が変化します。
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term lang="en">The Gradient Map filter</term>
      <term lang="ja">グラデーションマップフィルタ</term>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">
           This filter is now in the Colors menu, and allows you to
           <quote>colorize</quote>
           an image, using the color intensity of each point with the
           corresponding color from the active gradient (the intensity 0, very
           dark, is replaced by the color at most left end of the gradient,
           progressively until the intensity is 255, very light, replaced by
           the most right color of the gradient). See
           <xref linkend="plug-in-gradmap"/> for more information.
         </para>
        <para lang="ja">
           現在このフィルタは
           <menuchoice>
             <guimenu>色(<accel>C</accel>)</guimenu>
             <guisubmenu>マップ(<accel>M</accel>)</guisubmenu>
             <guimenuitem>グラデーションマップ(<accel>G</accel>)</guimenuitem>
           </menuchoice>
           に置かれています。 このフィルタは画素の強度を読みとって現在活性化
           しているグラデーションから相応の位置の色に置き換えるしくみで画像に
           <quote>着色</quote>が可能となりました。 (強度0は最も暗い色をさし、
           グラデーションの左端の色で置き換えられます。 強度が増すにつれ徐々に
           異なる色が与えられ、 一番明るい色をさす強度255の画素はグラデーション
           の右端の色で置き換えられます。) より詳しくは
           <xref linkend="plug-in-gradmap"/> をご覧ください。
         </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para lang="en">
    When you install <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, it comes presupplied with a
    large number of
    interesting gradients, and you can add new ones that you create or
    download from other sources. You can access the full set of available
    gradients using the
    <link linkend="gimp-gradient-dialog">Gradients dialog</link>,
    a dockable dialog that you can either activate when you need it, or keep
    around as a tab in a dock. The <quote>current gradient</quote>, used in
    most gradient-related operations, is shown in the Brush/Pattern/Gradient
    area of the Toolbox. Clicking on the gradient symbol in the Toolbox is an
    alternative way of bringing up the Gradients dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Many quickly examples of working with gradient (for more information
    see <link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">Blend Tool</link>):
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>をインストールすると、 結構な数の興味深い
    グラデーションがついてきますが、 新たに作成したり外部の配布元から取得して
    きてそれらに追加することもできます。 利用可能なグラデーションは全て
    <link linkend="gimp-gradient-dialog">グラデーションダイアログ</link> に
    あります。 このダイアログはドッキング可能なダイアログなので、 必要なときに
    のみ呼び出すことも、 ドック上でタブ化して常設することもできます。
    <quote>現在選ばれているグラデーション</quote>はグラデーションに係わる大部分
    の操作に使われるもので、 ツールボックスの<quote>ブラシ / パターン /
    グラデーション</quote>の区画でも表示されています。 このツールボックス上の
    標識をクリックしてもグラデーションダイアログを呼び出せます。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    グラデーションを使った手短かな例を数点 (より詳しくは
    <link linkend="gimp-tool-blend">ブレンドツール</link> をご覧ください):
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">Put a gradient in a selection:</para>
      <para lang="ja">選択範囲をグラデーションで塗るには:</para>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para lang="en">Choose a gradient.</para>
          <para lang="ja">グラデーションをひとつ選びます。</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para lang="en">
            With the Blend Tool click and drag with the mouse between
            two points of a selection.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            ブレンドツールで選択範囲内の2点間をクリックして曳きます。
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para lang="en">
            Colors will distributed perpendicularly to the direction
            of the drag of the mouse and according to the length
            of it.
          </para>
          <para lang="ja">
            曳いた距離に従いその向きに直交して色が分布します。
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
      <figure>
        <title lang="en">How to use rapidly a gradient in a selection</title>
        <title lang="ja">選択範囲に素早くグラデーションをかける方法</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/using/gradient-draw.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">Use a gradient with a drawing tool:</para>
      <para lang="en">
        You can also use a gradient with pencil, brush or airbrush tools
        if you check <guilabel>Use color from gradient</guilabel>
        In the example below the option is checked for a pencil tool. You
        see in the drawing in the right side the succession of the colors
        of the gradient (to infinity...).
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">筆触ツールでグラデーションをかけるには:</para>
      <para lang="ja">
        鉛筆、 絵筆、 エアブラシの各ツールでもグラデーションが使えます。
        <guilabel>グラデーションで描画</guilabel> オプションにチェックを入れて
        ください。 つぎの例では<quote>鉛筆で描画</quote>ツールを起用しこの
        オプションを使っています。 下図右側の描線ではグラデーションの色順が
        (折り返しながら繰り返し) 現れているのがわかるでしょう。
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title lang="en">
          How to use rapidly a gradient with a drawing tool
        </title>
        <title lang="ja">筆触ツールで素早くグラデーションをかける方法</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG"
              fileref="images/using/color-gradient-pencil.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">Different productions with the same gradient:</para>
      <para lang="ja">同一のグラデーションを使っても結果の違う例:</para>
      <figure>
        <title lang="en">Gradient usage</title>
        <title lang="ja">グラデーションの使用法</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/using/gradient-usage.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            <para lang="en">
              Four ways of using the Tropical Colors gradient: a linear
              gradient fill, a shaped gradient fill, a stroke painted using
              colors from a gradient, and a stroke painted with a fuzzy brush
              then colored using the
              <link linkend="plug-in-gradmap">Gradient Map</link> filter.
            </para>
            <para lang="ja">
              <quote>Tropical Colors</quote>グラデーションを用いた4つの使用法:
              ブレンドツールで形状を線形に; ブレンドツールで形状広がり (球面);
              <quote>Pencil Sketch</quote>ブラシを用いグラデーションで描画;
              <quote>Fuzzy</quote>ブラシを用いて線を描いてから
              <link linkend="plug-in-gradmap">グラデーションマップ</link>
              フィルタで着色。
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para lang="en">
    A few useful things to know about <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s gradients:
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のグラデーションについて知っておきたい
    ちょっとした豆知識:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        The first four gradients in the list are special:  they use the
        Foreground and Background colors from the Toolbox Color Area,
        instead of being fixed. <guilabel>FG to BG (RGB)</guilabel> is the
        RGB representation of the gradient from the Foreground color to the
        Background color in Toolbox. <guilabel>FG to BG (HSV
        counter-clockwise) </guilabel> represents the hue succession in
        Color Circle from the selected hue to 360°. <guilabel>FG to BG
        (HSV clockwise</guilabel> represents the hue succession in Color
        Circle from the selected hue to 0°. With <guilabel>FG to transparent
        </guilabel>, the selected hue becomes more and more transparent. You
        can modify these colors by using the Color Selector. Thus, by
        altering the foreground and background colors, you can make these
        gradients transition smoothly between any two colors you want.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        グラデーションダイアログのリストの最初の4つは特別なグラデーションです:
        これらは固定した色順ではなくツールボックスに示されている描画色と
        背景色を使います。 <guilabel>描画色から背景色 (RGB)</guilabel> は
        ツールボックスで表された描画色から背景色へのグラデーションを<acronym>
        RGB</acronym> 上で表現したものです。 <guilabel>描画色から背景色 (HSV
        反時計回り)</guilabel> は選択された色相から色相環上を360°まで変転する
        ところを示しています。 <guilabel>描画色から背景色 (HSV 時計回り)
        </guilabel> は選択された色相から色相環上を0°まで進むところを示して
        います。 <guilabel>描画色から透明へ</guilabel> では選択された色相が
        徐々に透過していきます。 これらの色は色を変更するダイアログを通して
        変えられます。 要するにこれらのグラデーションは描画色と背景色を変えれば
        その2色がどんな色でもその間を徐々に移り変わる内容で作成できるという
        ことです。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        Gradients can involve not just color changes, but also changes in
        opacity. Some of the gradients are completely opaque; others include
        transparent or translucent parts. When you fill or paint with a
        non-opaque gradient, the existing contents of the layer will show
        through behind it.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        グラデーションは色の変転のみならず不透明度の変転をも含みます。 同梱の
        グラデーションには全くの不透明なものもいくつかありますが、 それ以外は
        透明もしくは半透明な部分が入っています。 完全不透明ではない
        グラデーションで塗りつぶしたり描画したりすれば、 その下側にあるレイヤ
        の内容が透けて見えることになるでしょう。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        You can create new <emphasis>custom</emphasis> gradients,
        using the <link linkend="gimp-gradient-editor-dialog">Gradient
        Editor</link>.  You cannot modify the gradients that are
        supplied with <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, but you can duplicate them or
        create new ones, and then edit those.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <link linkend="gimp-gradient-editor-dialog">グラデーションエディタ
        </link> を使って <emphasis>自作の</emphasis> グラデーションが作れます。
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>に添付されているグラデーションは変更が
        できませんが、 その複製をとるか新規に作成すればそれを編集できます。
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para lang="en">
    The gradients that are supplied with <acronym>GIMP</acronym> are stored in
    a system <filename>gradients</filename> folder.  By default, gradients
    that you create are stored in a folder called
    <filename>gradients</filename> in your personal <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    directory.  Any gradient files (ending with the extension
    <filename>.ggr</filename>) found in one of these folders, will
    automatically be loaded when you start <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  You can
    add more
    directories to the gradient search path, if you want to, in the
    Gradients tab of the <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Data
    Folders</link> pages of the Preferences dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    New in <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.2 is the ability to load gradient files
    in SVG format, used
    by many vector graphics programs. To make <acronym>GIMP</acronym> load an
    SVG gradient file,
    all you need to do is place it in the <filename>gradients</filename>
    folder of your personal <acronym>GIMP</acronym> directory, or any other
    folder in your gradient search path.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>に同梱のグラデーションファイルはシステム用の
    <filename class="directory">gradients</filename> フォルダに入っています。 
    初期設定では、 自作のグラデーションファイルは個人用の<acronym>GIMP
    </acronym>ディレクトリ内の <filename class="directory">gradients</filename>
    フォルダに入れられます。 グラデーションファイル (拡張子 <filename
    class="extension">.ggr</filename> で終わる名前のファイル) はいずれもどちら
    かのフォルダ内に入っていて、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>を起動すると自動的に
    読み込まれます。 この2つのディレクトリ以外のフォルダでもグラデーションを
    検索させるには、 
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">環境設定</link> ダイアログの左側の
    一覧から 
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>フォルダ</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>グラデーション</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    をクリックして出てくるページでそのフォルダを追加してください。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> 2.2 から新たに<acronym>SVG</acronym>形式の
    グラデーションファイルが読み込めるようになりました。 <acronym>SVG</acronym>
    形式はベクター画像を扱う多くのプログラムで使われています。 <acronym>GIMP
    </acronym>に<acronym>SVG</acronym>形式のグラデーションファイルを読み込ま
    せる方法はただ単にそのファイルを個人用の<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の
    <filename>gradients</filename> フォルダか、 あるいは検索パスに登録した
    他のフォルダに入れることだけです。
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para lang="en">
      You can find a large number of interesting SVG gradients on the web, in
      particular at OpenClipArt Gradients
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-openclipart-gradients"/>.
      You won't be able to see what these gradients look like unless your
      browser supports SVG, but that won't prevent you from downloading them.
    </para>
      <para lang="ja">
      面白い<acronym>SVG</acronym>形式のグラデーションファイルが多数ウェブ上に
      ありますが、 とくに OpenClipArt Gradients
      <xref linkend="bibliography-online-openclipart-gradients"/>
      を挙げておきましょう。 ただし<acronym>SVG</acronym>形式の画像ファイルを
      表示できるブラウザでないとどんなグラデーションの内容なのかが分からずに
      ダウンロードすることになります。
      </para>
  </tip>
</sect1>
