<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
          "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!--  section history:
  2012-04-12 j.h: update to v2.8
-->
<!--2012-06-15-->
<sect2 id="gimp-image-window">
  <title lang="en">Image Window</title>
  <title lang="ja">画像ウィンドウ</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Image windows</primary>
    <secondary>Description</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Status bar</primary>
    <secondary>Image window</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Navigation preview</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Preview</primary>
    <secondary>Navigation preview</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="ガゾウウィンドウ">画像ウィンドウ</primary>
    <secondary sortas="カイセツ">解説</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ステータスバー</primary>
    <secondary sortas="ガゾウウィンドウ">画像ウィンドウ</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ナビゲーションプレビュー</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>プレビュー</primary>
    <secondary>ナビゲーションプレビュー</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    GIMP user interface is now available in two modes: multi-window mode
    (default), and single-window mode (optional, through
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Windows</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>>Single-Window Mode</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    But, if you quit GIMP with this option enabled, GIMP will open in single
    mode next time).
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    In single-window mode, no new window is added: images and dialogs are added
    in tabs. Please see <xref linkend="single-window-mode"/>.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    When you start <acronym>GIMP</acronym> without any image open, the image
    window seems to be absent in single-window mode, while, in multi-window
    mode, an image window exists, even if no image is open.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> のユーザーインターフェースはマルチウィンドウモード
    (初期設定) とシングルウィンドウモードの 2 通りから選べるようになりました。
    シングルウィンドウモードに切り替えるには画像ウィンドウのメニューより
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>ウィンドウ</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>シングルウィンドウモード</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    を指定します。 ただしこのモードのまま <acronym>GIMP</acronym> を終了すれば、
    次回も <acronym>GIMP</acronym> はシングルウィンドウモードで起動します。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    シングルウィンドウモードのときはウィンドウが増えません。 新たに開いた画像も
    ダイアログもタブ化されて追加されます。
    <xref linkend="single-window-mode"/> をご覧ください。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    開く画像を指定せずに <acronym>GIMP</acronym> を起動したとき、 シングル
    ウィンドウモードでは画像ウィンドウが無い状態で開始しますが、 マルチ
    ウィンドウモードの場合はたとえ 1 枚も画像を開いていない状態でも画像
    ウィンドウが必ず 1 枚開かれます。
  </para>

  <para lang="en">
    We will begin with a brief description of the components that are
    present by default in an ordinary image window. Some of the
    components can be removed by using commands in the
    <link linkend="gimp-view-menu">View</link> menu.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    それでは一般的な画像ウィンドウについてその各部分の説明を手短にすすめて
    ゆきましょう。 画像ウィンドウの部品のいくつかは画像ウィンドウの 
    <link linkend="gimp-view-menu">表示</link> メニューのコマンドで隠せます。
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title lang="en">The Image Window in Multi-Window Mode</title>
    <title lang="ja">マルチウィンドウモードの画像ウィンドウ</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata format="PNG"
		  fileref="images/using/image-window-multi.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <figure>
    <title lang="en">The Image Area in Single-Window Mode</title>
    <title lang="ja">シングルウィンドウモードの画像ウィンドウ</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata format="PNG"
		  fileref="images/using/image-window-single.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <note>
    <para lang="en">
      Despite <emphasis>Single</emphasis>-window Mode, we will use
      <quote>image window</quote> for <quote>image area</quote>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      <emphasis>シングル</emphasis> ウィンドウモードの場合に厳密には
      画像ウィンドウに代わって画像の表示を画像表示領域が担います。 したがって
      このあとの説明で<quote>画像ウィンドウ</quote>と書いたところは
      <quote>画像表示領域</quote>と読み替えてください。 同様に
      <quote>画像ウィンドウのメニュー</quote>は<quote>本体のメニュー</quote>の
      ことを指しています。
    </para>
  </note>
    
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <!--1-->
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Title Bar:</emphasis>
        The Title Bar in an image window without an image displays
        <quote>GNU Image Manipulating Program</quote>.
        An image window with an image displays the image name
        and its specifications in the title bar according to the settings
        in <link linkend="gimp-prefs-dialog">Preference Dialog</link>.
        The Title Bar is provided by the operating system, not by
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, so its appearance is likely to vary with
        the operating system, window manager, and/or theme &mdash; in Linux 
        systems, this title bar has a button to display the image
        window on all your desktops. You also have this button in toolbox window
        and layer window.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        If you have opened a non-xcf image, it is <quote>(imported)</quote>
        as a .xcf file and its original name appears in the status bar at the
        bottom of the image window.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        When an image is modified, an asterisk appears in front of title.
      </para>      
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>タイトルバー:</emphasis>
        画像のない画像ウィンドウのタイトルは<quote>GIMP (GNU Image
        Manipulation Program)</quote>となります。 画像が表示されている
        ウィンドウではタイトルバーに画像の名前と画像の特徴を示した情報が 
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window-title">設定</link> ダイアログの
        <quote>画像ウィンドウのタイトルとステータスバー</quote>のページで設定
        されたとおりの形式で表示されます。 タイトルバーの表示自体は
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym> でなくウィンドウシステムが担っているので、
        使用するオペレーティングシステムとウィンドウマネージャー、 あるいはまた
        テーマ設定によってもかなり見た目が違ってきます。 例えば、 [原文筆者が
        使用している] Linux 系システムでは画像ウィンドウのタイトルバー上の
        とあるボタンをクリックすると仮想多重デスクトップのどの画面に切り
        替えても常にこのウィンドウが現れるようになります。 このボタンは
        ツールボックスウィンドウやレイヤーダイアログウィンドウの
        タイトルバーにもあります。
      </para>      
      <para lang="ja">
        <acronym>XCF</acronym> 以外の形式の画像ファイルを開いた場合は、
        タイトルバー表示 <guilabel>(インポートされた画像)</guilabel> が示す
        とおり画像が <filename class="extension">.xcf</filename> 化され、
        元のファイル名は画像ウィンドウの底部にあるステータスバーに表示されます。
      </para>      
      <para lang="ja">
        画像に未保存の変更があるとき、 タイトル表示の先頭にアスタリスク記号
        <quote>*</quote>がつきます。
      </para>      
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
      <!--2-->
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Image Menu:</emphasis>
        Directly below the Title Bar appears the Menu bar (unless it has
        been suppressed). The Image Menu provides access to nearly every
        operation you can perform on an image. You can also right-click
        on an image to display a pop-up image menu,
        <footnote><para>
            Users with an Apple Macintosh and a one button mouse can use
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
              <mousebutton>mousebutton</mousebutton>
            </keycombo> instead.
          </para></footnote>,
        or by left-clicking on the little <quote>arrow-head</quote> symbol in
        the upper left corner, called <emphasis>Menu Button</emphasis>,
        described just below.
        Many menu commands are also associated with keyboard
        <emphasis>shortcuts</emphasis> as shown in the menu.
        You can define your own custom shortcuts for menu actions, if
        you enable <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface"> Use Dynamic Keyboard
        Shortcuts</link> in the Preferences dialog.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>メニューバー:</emphasis> タイトルバーの真下にあるのが
        メニューバーです (
        <link linkend=\"gimp-view-show-menubar\">隠せます</link>)。 画像
        ウィンドウのメニューには画像に対して行なうほとんどすべての操作が
        並んでいます。 このメニューは画像の上を右クリック
        (<mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> クリック)
        <footnote>
          <para>
            アップルマッキントッシュの単ボタンマウスをお使いの方は
            <keycombo>
              <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><mousebutton>マウスボタン</mousebutton>
            </keycombo> で代用します。
          </para>
        </footnote> しても、
        あるいはウィンドウの左上隅の小さな<quote>メニューボタン</quote> 
        <guiicon>
          <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/callouts/3.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject><phrase>(3)</phrase></textobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>
        </guiicon>
        をクリックしても呼びだせるようになっています (メニューボタンについては
        すぐ後で説明します)。 メニューの数多くのコマンドはキーボードショート
        カットに関連づけられていて、 あればメニュー項目の右側にも表示されます。 
        メニューの項目に独自のショートカットを割り当てるには
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-interface">設定</link> 
        ダイアログの<quote>ユーザーインターフェース</quote>のページで 
        <guilabel>動的キーボードショートカットを使用する</guilabel>
        を有効にします。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--3-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-origin"/>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Menu Button:</emphasis>
        Click the Menu Button to display the Image Menu in a column,(essential
        in full screen mode).
        If you like to use keyboard shortcuts, use
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>
        to open the menu.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>メニューボタン:</emphasis> メニューボタンをクリックすると、 
        画像メニューが縦に並んで出てきます。 キーボードショートカットを好まれる
        なら
        <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>
        を使えばこのメニューが呼び出せます。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--4-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-ruler"/>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Ruler:</emphasis>
        In the default layout, rulers are shown above and to the left of the
        image. Use the rulers to determine coordinates within the image.
        The default unit for rulers is pixels; use the settings
        described below to use a unit other than pixels.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
        One of the most important uses of rulers is to create
        <emphasis>guides</emphasis>.
        Click and drag a ruler into the image to create a guide.
        A guide is a line that helps you accurately position
        things&mdash;or verify that another line is truly horizontal
        or vertical.
        Click and drag a guide to move it. Drag a guide out of the
        image to delete it; you can always drag another guide into the
        image. You can even use multiple guides at the same time.
      </para>
      <para lang="en">
	In ruler area, the mouse pointer position is marked with two small 
	arrow-heads pointing vertically and horizontally.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>定規:</emphasis> 初期設定での配置では左辺および上辺に
        定規があります。 画像上の座標を測るときにご利用ください。 初期設定では
        ピクセルを単位としていますが、 単位を変えるには後で述べる単位設定で
        行います。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        定規には <emphasis>ガイド (見当線)</emphasis> をつくるというとても
        重要なはたらきがあります。 定規をクリックしたまま画像上にドラッグして
        ゆくとガイドが作成できます。 ガイドをたよりに画像内の物体を正確に
        位置決めしやすくなります。 また画像に現れている線がぴったり水平もしくは
        垂直になっているかを検証しやすくします。 ガイドはドラッグすると移動が
        でき、 画像表示の外までドラッグすれば消去できます。 いつでもガイドを
        画像にドラッグして曳き込めますし、 同時に何本でも置けます。
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        定規上には小さな黒い三角形がそれぞれひとつづつ表示され、 マウス
        ポインターの現在地を常に示します。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--5-->
      <anchor id="quick-mask-toggle"/>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>QuickMask Toggle:</emphasis>
        The small button in the lower left corner of the image toggles the
        Quick Mask on and off. When the Quick Mask is on, the button is
        outlined in red. See <link linkend="gimp-qmask">QuickMask</link>
        for more details on this highly useful tool.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>クイックマスクモード:</emphasis>
        画像表示の左下隅にクイックマスクのオン/オフを切り替える小さなボタンが
        あります。 クイックマスクが有効な状態ではこのボタンが赤く縁取られます。
        <link linkend="gimp-qmask">クイックマスク</link> の節にはとても便利な
        このツールの詳しい解説があります。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--6-->
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Pointer Coordinates:</emphasis>
        When the pointer (mouse cursor, if you are using a mouse) is
        within the image boundaries, the rectangular area in the lower
        left corner of the window displays the current pointer
        coordinates. The units are the same as for the rulers.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>ポインターの座標:</emphasis> ポインター (マウスをお使いならば
        マウスカーソル) を画像の枠内に置くと、 ウィンドウの左下の一区画に現在の
        ポインターの座標が表示されます。 単位は定規と同じです。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--7-->
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Units Menu:</emphasis>
        Use the Units Menu to change the units used for rulers and several
        other purposes. The default unit is pixels, but you can quickly
        change to inches, cm, or several other possibilities using this menu.
        Note that the setting of
        <quote>Dot for dot</quote> in the View menu affects how the display is
        scaled: see <link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">Dot for Dot</link>
        for more information.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>単位メニュー:</emphasis> 定規をはじめいくつかの機能で使われる
        単位を単位メニューで変更できます。 初期設定ではピクセル単位ですが、 
        このメニューでインチやセンチメートルをはじめさまざまな尺度に素早く変更
        できます。 <guimenuitem>表示</guimenuitem>メニューの 
        <guilabel>ピクセル等倍</guilabel> を指定した場合に画像表示の
        大きさがどう変わるかに注意してください。
        <link linkend="gimp-view-dot-for-dot">ピクセル等倍で表示</link> 
        にさらに詳しい説明があります。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--8-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-zoom"/>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Zoom Button:</emphasis>
        There are a number of ways to zoom the image in or out, but the Zoom
        Button is perhaps the simplest. You can directly enter a zoom level in
        the text box for precise control.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>ズームボタン:</emphasis> ズームで近づいたり離れたりする方法
        はたくさん用意されていますが、 ズームボタンが最も単純かもしれません。
        表示倍率が数値記入欄で直接指定できますので非常に精密な伸縮が可能です。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--9-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-status-bar"/>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Status Area:</emphasis>
        The Status Area is at the bottom of the image window.
        By default, the Status Area displays the original name of the image.xcf
        file, and the amount of system memory used by the image. Please use
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Image Windows</guimenuitem>
          <guimenuitem>Title &amp; Status</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        to customize the information displayed in the Status Area.
        During time-consuming operations, the status area temporarily
        shows the running operation and how complete the operation is.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>状態情報:</emphasis> 状態情報は画像ウィンドウの底部の
        ステータスバーに現れます。 初期設定では状態情報の区画に画像を
        <acronym>XCF</acronym> 化する前の元のファイル名やこの画像のために
        消費されているメモリー量が表示されています。 
        <link linkend="gimp-prefs-image-window-title">設定</link> 
        ダイアログの<quote>画像タイトルとステータスバーの形式</quote>のページの
        下段で状態情報の区画に表示する情報の形式を設定できます。
        時間を多く費す作業をしているときに、 状態情報は一時的に
        その作業が何であるかの表示に切り替わり、 進み具合を報告します。
      </para>
      <note>
        <para lang="en">
          Note that the memory used by the image is very
          different from the image file size. For instance, a 70Kb .PNG
          image may occupy 246Kb in RAM when displayed.
          There are two primary reasons the difference in memory usage.
          First, a .PNG file is compressed format, and the image is
          reconstituted in RAM in uncompressed form.
          Second, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> uses extra memory, and copies
          of the image, for use by the Undo command.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          読み込んだ画像に使われるメモリー量は画像ファイルのサイズとは全く
          違います。 たとえば 70Kb の
          <filename class="extension">.png</filename> 画像が表示に 246Kb の
          <acronym>RAM</acronym> を占めるというふうなことです。 この理由は 2 つ
          あります。 第一に画像は、 読み込まれた圧縮
          <filename class="extension">.png</filename> ファイルのデータから
          再現されたものです。 第二に <acronym>GIMP</acronym> はそれ以上に
          メモリーを使用しますし、 取り消しコマンドに備え画像のコピーを控えて
          います。
        </para>
      </note>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--10-->
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Cancel Button:</emphasis>
        During complex time-consuming operations, usually a plug-in,
        a Cancel button temporarily appears in the lower right corner
        of the window. Use the Cancel button to stop the operation.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>中止ボタン:</emphasis> たいていはプラグインのような複雑で
        時間のかかる作業中に、 中止ボタンがウィンドウの右下の区画に一時的に
        現れます。 中止ボタンをクリックするとその作業を中止できます。
      </para>
      <note>
        <para lang="en">
          A few plug-ins respond badly to being canceled, sometimes
          leaving corrupted pieces of images behind.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          残念ながら中断するとまずいプラグインがまれにあり、 ときには
          壊れた画像を残して終了するおそれがあります。
        </para>
      </note>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--11-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-nav-button"/>
      <indexterm lang="en">
        <primary>Navigation</primary>
        <secondary>Navigation button</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm lang="ja">
        <primary>ナビゲーション</primary>
        <secondary>ナビゲーションボタン</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Navigation Control:</emphasis>
        This is a small cross-shaped button at the lower right corner of the
        image display. Click and hold (do not release the mouse button)
        on the navigation control to display the Navigation Preview.
        The Navigation Preview has a miniature view of the image
        with the displayed area outlined. Use the Navigation Preview
        to quickly pan to a different part of the
        image&mdash;move the mouse while keeping the button pressed.
        The Navigation Window is often the most convenient way to
        quickly navigate around a large image with only a small portion
        displayed. (See
        <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">Navigation Dialog</link>
        for other ways to access the Navigation Window). (If your mouse has a
        middle-button, click-drag with it to pan across the image).
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>ナビゲーションコントロール:</emphasis>
        これは小さな十字ボタンになっていて画像表示の右下隅にあります。
        ナビゲーションコントロールをクリックしたままマウスボタンを放さずに
        おくとナビゲーションプレビューが表示されます。 ナビゲーションプレビュー
        には表示領域が枠線で描かれた画像の縮小版があります。 ナビゲーション
        プレビューを使えば画像上での視野を別の位置に素早く移せます。 この操作は
        ボタンを放さずにマウスを移動してください。 表示枠よりも大きな画像のため
        一部しか見えないとき、 画像の見たい部分をとらえるのにナビゲーション
        ウィンドウだとたいてい一番簡単にできます (ナビゲーションウィンドウを
        呼びだす別の方法については、 
        <link linkend="gimp-navigation-dialog">ナビゲーションダイアログ</link> 
        を参考にしてください)。 (3 ボタンマウスをお使いの場合、 中ボタンで
        ドラッグすると同様に画像上を巡れます)。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--12-->
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Inactive Padding Area:</emphasis>
        When the image dimensions are smaller than the image window, this
        padding area separates the active image display and the inactive
        padding area, so you're able to distinguish between them. You cannot
        apply any Filters or Operations in general to the inactive area.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>外部不活性区域:</emphasis> 画像表示の大きさが画像ウィンドウ
        よりも小さいときは、 不活性な領域が画像を囲み、 画像上とそれ以外を
        区別できます。 不活性区域はどんなフィルターも操作も受け付けません。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--13-->
      <anchor id="imagewindow-display"/>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Image Display:</emphasis>
        The most important part of the image window is, of course, the image
        display or canvas. It occupies the central area of the window,
        surrounded by a yellow dotted line showing the image boundary, against
        a neutral gray background. You can change the zoom level of the image
        display in a variety of ways, including the Zoom setting described
        below.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>画像表示領域:</emphasis> 画像ウィンドウのうちで最も重要なのは
        当然ながら画像表示領域すなわちキャンバスです。 画像ウィンドウの中央を
        占め、 黄色の点線が画像とその外部の無色な灰色の背景との境界を
        示しています。 画像をズーム表示するその段階を調整する方法はいろいろ
        ありますが、 つぎに述べる表示倍率調整もそのひとつです。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <!--14-->
      <anchor id="gimp-image-window-zoom-follow-button"/>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Image Window Resize Toggle:</emphasis>
        Without enabling this feature, if you change the size of the image
        window by click-and-dragging border limits, the image size and zoom 
        does not change. If you make the
        window larger, for example, then you will see more of the image.
        If this button is pressed, however, the image resizes when the window
        resizes so that (mostly) the same portion of the image is displayed
        before and after the window is resized.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>ウィンドウと画像の連動伸縮の切り替え:</emphasis>
        この機能を無効にしている場合は画像ウィンドウの表示枠をクリックしながら
        ドラッグして大きさを変えても画像の表示倍率は変わりません。 
        例えばウィンドウを大きくすれば画像の見える部分が増すか外周不活性区域が
        拡がります。 その逆にこのボタンをクリックして押した状態にすると、 
        画像ウィンドウの大きさを変えると画像の表示される区画が変形の前後で 
        (ほぼ) 同じになるように画像の表示倍率が調整されます。
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  
<!--
  <para lang="en">
    <anchor id="dotted-strips"/>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Dotted strips</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <emphasis>Dotted strips</emphasis>:

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/left-vertical-line.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    
    In single-window mode,
    depending on your system and gtk theme, you can notice these small dotted
    strips, or nothing, on the left and the right side of the image. They 
    mark the limit between the image area and the panels, from top to bottom. 
    When the mouse pointer passes over this limit, it turns to a double-arrow.
    Then, click-and-drag to move the limit between image area and panels.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <anchor id="dotted-strips"/>
    <indexterm>
      <primary sortas="カドウセパレーター">可動セパレーター</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <emphasis>可動セパレーター</emphasis>:

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/using/left-vertical-line.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    
    シングルウィンドウモードの場合に、 画像表示領域の左右両辺の端部に図のような
    小さな間仕切りが現れます (その姿はお使いのシステムや <acronym>GTK</acronym>
    のテーマによって異なります)。 実際はこれらがウィンドウの上端から下端まで
    画像表示領域と両側パネルの区切りを示しています。 マウスポインターを
    この境界線上にかざすとセパレーターが二重矢印の表示に変化します。
    そこでクリックして曳くと間仕切りが移動しパネルやキャンバスの横幅が
    変更できます。
  </para>
-->
    
  <tip>
    <para lang="en">
      Drag and drop an image into the Toolbox window from a file browser to 
      open the image in its own Image window or tab.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Dragging an image file into the Layer dialog adds it to the image as a
      new layer.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ファイルブラウザーの画像アイコンをツールボックスまでドラッグして放つと
      その画像が新たな画像ウィンドウになって、 あるいは画像表示領域の新たな
      タブとなって開かれます。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      レイヤーダイアログに画像アイコンをドラッグしてきて放つと、 ドロップされた
      画像はレイヤー化されて現在の画像に追加されます。
    </para>
  </tip>  

  <para lang="en">
    Image size and image window size can be different. You can make image fit
    window, and vice versa, using two keyboard shortcuts:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>J</keycap></keycombo>: this
          command keeps the zoom level; it adapts window size to image size.
          The Shrink Wrap command does the same.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap>
          <keycap>J</keycap></keycombo>: this command modifies the zoom level
          to adapt the image display to the window.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    画像表示の大きさと画像ウィンドウの大きさがいつも同じとは限りません。 画像を
    画像ウィンドウにすっぽり入る大きさで表示させたり、 逆に画像表示に合わせて
    画像ウィンドウの大きさを調節するキーボードショートカットがあります。
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>J</keycap></keycombo>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            このコマンドは表示倍率を維持します。 画像ウィンドウの大きさが
            画像の表示寸法に合わせて変化します。
            <guimenuitem>ウィンドウサイズを合わせる</guimenuitem> コマンドと
            同じ働きです。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      <varlistentry>
      </varlistentry>
        <term>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>J</keycap>
          </keycombo>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            このコマンドは表示倍率を変更して画像ウィンドウ内で画像の全体像が
            見える最大限の大きさにします。
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </para>

</sect2>
