<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history
  2009-02-19 j.h:revised for v2.6. No change
  2007-03-26 reviewed Korean translation by Dust
  2006-08-28 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-05-02 added Korean translation by Dust
  2005-12-18 reviewed and added rewrote de image explenation by lexa
-->
<!--2012-06-10-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-image-types">
  <title lang="en">Image Types</title>
  <title lang="ja">画像の形式</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Images</primary>
    <secondary>Types</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="ガゾウ">画像</primary>
    <secondary sortas="ケイシキ">形式</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para lang="en">
    It is tempting to think of an <emphasis>image</emphasis> as
    something that corresponds with a single display window, or to a
    single file such as a <link linkend="file-jpeg-load">JPEG</link>
    file. In reality, however, a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image is a
    complicated structure,
    containing a stack of layers plus several other types of objects:
    a selection mask, a set of channels, a set of paths, an "undo"
    history, etc.  In this section we are take a detailed
    look at all of the components of a <acronym>GIMP</acronym> image,
    and the things you can do with them.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    The most basic property of an image is its
    <emphasis>mode</emphasis>.  There are three possible modes: RGB,
    grayscale, and indexed. RGB stands
    for Red-Green-Blue, and indicates that each point in the image
    is represented by a <quote>red</quote> level, a <quote>green</quote>
    level, and a <quote>blue</quote>
    level; representing a full-color image.
    Each color channel has 256 possible intensity
    levels. More details in <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">
    Color Models</link>
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    In a grayscale image, each point is represented by a brightness
    value, ranging from 0 (black) to 255 (white), with intermediate
    values representing different levels of gray.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    ここでは<emphasis>画像</emphasis>のことを単体の表示ウィンドウや 
    <link linkend="file-jpeg-load">JPEG</link> のようなファイルに対応する存在
    とする考え方で話をすすめます。 ただし本来の<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の画像は
    重ね合わされたレイヤーをはじめ、 選択マスクや数層のチャンネル、 パスや
    作業履歴など、 様々な要素からなるもっと複雑な構造を持っています。 この章では
    <acronym>GIMP<acronym>画像の構成要素をひとつづつ詳しく見てゆき、 
    それらをどのように使ったらよいか説明します。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
     画像の最も基本的な属性は <emphasis>モード</emphasis> です。 扱えるモードは
     <acronym>RGB</acronym>、 グレースケール、 インデックス化カラーの 3 つです。
     <acronym>RGB</acronym>とは赤・緑・青の頭文字からとられた言葉で、 画像の
     各点が<quote>赤色</quote>レベル、 <quote>緑色</quote>レベル、 
     <quote>青色</quote>レベルの 3 つで表せる状態を示しています。
     <!--人間の視覚できる色彩は赤緑青の混成ですべて表現できるため、-->
     <acronym>RGB</acronym>画像は総天然色です。
     色素チャンネルの強度ははそれぞれが 256 階調で表されています。
     <link linkend="glossary-colormodel">カラーモデル</link> に詳しい説明が
     あります。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    グレースケール画像ではその各点が明度で表され、
    その範囲は 0 (黒) から 255 (白) で中間色はさまざまな濃さの灰色です。
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Components of the RGB and CMY Color Model</title>
    <title lang="ja">
      <acronym>RGB</acronym>と<acronym>CMY</acronym>の各カラーモデルの相関図
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/glossary/color-model-additive.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          In the RGB Color Model, mixing Red, Green and Blue gives White,
          which is what happens on your screen.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <acronym>RGB</acronym>色モデルでは、 赤・緑・青の混色が白になります。
          画面の表示はこれを利用しています。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/glossary/color-model-subtractive.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          In the CMY(K) color model, mixing Cyan, Magenta and Yellow gives
          Black, which is what happens when you print on a white paper. The
          printer will actually use the black cartridge for economical
          reasons and better color rendering.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <acronym>CMY(K)</acronym>カラーモデルでは、 シアン、 マゼンタ、
          イエローの混色が黒になります。 これはプリンターで白紙に印刷すると
          起こります。 ただし実際はプリンターには黒インクカートリッジがあって、
          経済的かつ美しい仕上りが図られています。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    Conceptually, the difference between a grayscale image and an RGB
    image is the number of <quote>color channels</quote>: a grayscale image
    has one; an RGB image has three.  An RGB image can be thought of as
    three superimposed grayscale images, one colored red, one green,
    and one blue.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Actually, both RGB and grayscale images have one additional
    color channel, called the <emphasis>alpha</emphasis> channel, which
    represents opacity.  When the alpha value at a given location
    in a given layer is zero, the layer is completely transparent
    (you can see through it),
    and the color at that location is determined by what lies
    underneath.  When alpha is maximal (255), the layer is opaque
    (you cannot see through it), and the
    color is determined by the color of the layer.  Intermediate
    alpha values correspond to varying degrees of translucency / opacity:
    the
    color at the location is a proportional mixture of color from the
    layer and color from underneath.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>RGB</acronym>画像とグレースケール画像は概念上その
    <quote>色チャンネル</quote>の数が違います。 グレースケール画像は
    ひとつだけですが、 <acronym>RGB</acronym>画像には 3 つあります。 
    つまり<acronym>RGB</acronym>画像は、 赤・緑・青の各色がついた 3 つの
    グレースケール画像を重ね合わせたものと考えることができます。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    実際には<acronym>RGB</acronym>画像とグレースケール画像のどちらもさらに
    <emphasis>アルファ</emphasis> チャンネルと呼ばれるチャンネルが 1 つ加わって
    おり、 透明度を表すはたらきがあります。 たとえばあるレイヤーの一部の
    アルファ値がゼロだと、 このレイヤーのその部分は完全な透明になり、 その下が
    透けて見えるので背面側のレイヤーの色が表側に出てきます。 アルファ値が最大値
    (255) ならばレイヤーは不透明なので透かして見えませんから、 そのレイヤーの
    色が出ます。 アルファが中間値のところは透明度の違いが現れており、 その部分
    の色はそのレイヤーと背面側のレイヤーの色の比例配合です。
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title lang="en">
      Example of an image in RGB and Grayscale mode
    </title>
    <title lang="ja">
      <acronym>RGB</acronym>とグレースケールの各モードの画像の例
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/wilber-channel-rgb.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          An image in RGB mode, with the channels corresponding to Red,
          Green and Blue.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <acronym>RGB</acronym>モードの画像は、 赤・緑・青の
          各チャンネルからなる。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/using/wilber-channel-gray.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          An image in Grayscale mode, with the channel corresponding to
          Luminosity.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          グレースケールモードの画像は明るさを表すチャンネルからなる。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, every color channel, including the alpha
    channel, has a range
    of possible values from 0 to 255; in computing terminology, a depth of 8
    bits. Some digital cameras can produce image files with a depth of 16
    bits per color channel. <acronym>GIMP</acronym> cannot load such a file
    without losing
    resolution. In most cases the effects are too subtle to be detected by
    the human eye, but in some cases, mainly where there are large areas
    with slowly varying color gradients, the difference may be perceptible.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>では、それぞれの色チャンネルおよびアルファチャンネル
    は 0 から 255 の範囲の値をとっています。 これはコンピュータ用語で色深度 8 
    ビットといいます。 ディジタルカメラの機種によっては各色チャンネルが色深度
    16  ビットのファイルを生成するものもあります。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>で
    このようなファイルを読みこんだときは解像度が落とされます。
    その場合の影響は人間の眼にはかなり微妙な違いにしか見えませんが、
    場合によりとくに広い範囲を極めてゆるやかな勾配でかけられた
    グラデーションの見え方ではその違いがばれるかもしれません。
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Example of an image with alpha channel</title>
    <title lang="ja">アルファチャンネルの加わった画像の例</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/wilber-channels-red.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">Red channel</para>
        <para lang="ja">赤チャンネル</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/wilber-channels-green.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">Green channel</para>
        <para lang="ja">緑チャンネル</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/wilber-channels-blue.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">Blue channel</para>
        <para lang="ja">青チャンネル</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/wilber-channels-alpha.png"/>
      </imageobject>
        <para lang="en">
          The Alpha channel shows the image area which is transparent.
        </para>
      <caption>
        <para lang="ja">アルファチャンネルは画像の透明部分を表します。</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/dialogs/wilber-channels-combined.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para lang="en">
          A color image in RGB mode with an Alpha channel.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          アルファチャンネルつきの<acronym>RGB</acronym>モードのカラー画像。
        </para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    The third type, <emphasis>indexed</emphasis>
    images, is a bit more complicated to understand. In an indexed image,
    only a limited set of discrete colors are used, usually 256 or less.
    These colors form the <quote>colormap</quote> of the image, and each
    point in the image is assigned a color from the colormap. Indexed images
    have the advantage that they can be represented inside a computer in a
    way which consumes relatively little memory, and back in the dark ages
    (say, ten years ago), they were very commonly used. As time goes on, they
    are used less and less, but they are still important enough to be worth
    supporting in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. (Also, there are a few important
    kinds of image
    manipulation that are easier to implement with indexed images than with
    continuous-color RGB images.)
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    Some very commonly used types of files (including
    <link linkend="file-gif-load">GIF</link> and
    <link linkend="file-png-load">PNG</link>) produce
    indexed images when they are opened in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.  Many of
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
    tools don't work very well on indexed images?and many filters
    don't work at all?because of the limited number of colors
    available.  Because of this, it is usually best to convert an
    image to RGB mode before working on it.  If necessary, you can
    convert it back to indexed mode when you are ready to save it
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> makes it easy to convert from one image type to
    another,
    using the <link linkend="gimp-image-mode">Mode</link> command in
    the Image menu.  Some types of conversions, of course (RGB to
    grayscale or indexed, for example) lose information that cannot
    be regained by converting back in the other direction.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    第 3 の形式は <emphasis>インデックス</emphasis> 化カラー画像です。 この
    モードは理解するのに少々骨が折れます。 インデックス化カラー画像では、 
    不連続で大抵 256 色かそれ以下に限定された色数で描かれています。 これらの
    色は画像の<quote>カラーマップ</quote>を構成しており、 画像の各点の色はすべて
    カラーマップからとられています。 インデックス化カラー画像は比較的メモリー
    消費量が少なくてすむというコンピューターにとって有利な点があり、 かつての
    暗黒時代 (つまり十数年前)<!--「十年前」の執筆時は2007年2月--> はこれが
    あたりまえでした。 時代は移り、 
    だんだん使われなくなってきましたが、 まだその重要性はあるとして
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>はサポートしています。 (それから、 
    <acronym>RGB</acronym>の連続色画像よりもインデックス化カラー画像のほうが
    実装しやすい画像処理がほんの数種類あります。)
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">(
    <link linkend="file-gif-load">GIF</link> や 
    <link linkend="file-png-load">PNG</link> などのようないくつかのよく使われる
    ファイル形式では、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>で開いた画像をインデックス化
    カラー画像にして生成できます。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のインデックス化カラー
    画像の処理は大多数のツールがその実力をあまり発揮できませんし、 一部のものは
    全く作動しません。 使える色数が少ないのが原因です。 ですから、
    むしろこういった処理の前に画像を
    <acronym>RGB</acronym>モードに変換しておくのが良策です。 必要に応じて、
    ファイルに保存する前にインデックス化カラー画像に変換しなおせばよいでしょう。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>で画像のモードを他のモードに変換するには、
    <guimenu>画像</guimenu>メニューの
    <link linkend="gimp-image-mode">モード</link> 変換コマンドを用いれば
    簡単です。 もちろん<acronym>RGB</acronym>からグレースケールやインデックス
    化カラー画像へのような一部の変換は、 とり戻すことの不可能な情報の欠損を
    もたらします。
  </para>
  <note>
    <para lang="en">
      If you are trying to use a filter on an image, and it appears grayed out
      in the menu, usually the cause is that the image (or, more specifically,
      the layer) you are working on is the wrong type. Many filters can't be
      used on indexed images. Some can be used only on RGB images, or only on
      grayscale images. Some also require the presence or absence of an alpha
      channel. Usually the fix is to convert the image to a different type,
      most commonly RGB.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      使おうとしたフィルタがメニューで灰色無効にされているときは、 ほとんどが
      その画像 (とくにそのレイヤー) に問題があります。 大多数のフィルターは
      インデックス化カラー画像には適用できません。 <acronym>RGB</acronym>画像
      限定のものや、 グレースケール画像限定のものもあります。 ほかにも
      アルファチャンネルがあることを前提にしているものや、 逆に
      アルファチャンネルがあると作動しないものもあります。 ほとんどの問題は画像
      を別のモード (たいていは<acronym>RGB</acronym>) に変換すれば解決します。
    </para>
  </note>
</sect1>
