<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2008-04-05 Mr.Dust : reviewed and added 'ko'
  2007-01-09 manuq: added es translation
  2006-09-06 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-08-02 added italian translation by ciampix
  2006-05-11 added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-04-30 HdJ: Added dutch translation.
  2006-03-05 Lexa: added german translation and made docbook compliant
  2005-11-28 Lexa: replaced informalfigures by figures.
  2005-05-09 nn: added french translation
-->
<!--2012-03-20-->
<sect1 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="gimp-concepts-palettes">
  <title lang="en">Palettes</title>
  <title lang="ja">パレット</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Palette</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Color</primary>
    <secondary>Palettes (color map)</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary lang="en">Indexed palette</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>パレット</primary>
    <secondary sortas="アラマシ">あらまし</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="イロ">色</primary>
    <secondary>パレット(カラーマップ)</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="インデックスツキパレット">
      インデックスつきパレット
    </primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para lang="en">
    A <emphasis>palette</emphasis> is a set of discrete colors. In
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, palettes are used mainly for two purposes:
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <emphasis>パレット</emphasis> とは[必ずしも]連続しないさまざまな色の
    集合です。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>はパレットを主に 2 つの用途に使います。
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        They allow you to paint with a selected set of colors, in the same way
        an oil painter works with colors from a limited number of tubes.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        一定数の選ばれた色だけを用いて描くようにすること。 あたかも限られた数の
        チューブ入り油絵の具を使って絵を描くようなものです。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        They form the colormaps of indexed images. An indexed image can use a
        maximum of 256 different colors, but these can be any colors. The
        colormap of an indexed image is called an "indexed palette" in
        <acronym>GIMP</acronym>.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        インデックス (色索引) つき画像のカラーマップのように。 インデックス化
        カラー画像は使える色数が 256 までに制限されますが、 パレットは何色でも
        入ります。 インデックス化カラー画像のカラーマップのことを<acronym>GIMP
        </acronym>では<acronym>インデックス化パレット</acronym>と呼んでいます。
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang="en">
    Actually neither of these functions fall very much into the mainstream of
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> usage: it is possible to do rather sophisticated
    things in <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    without ever dealing with palettes. Still, they are something that an
    advanced user should understand, and even a less advanced user may need to
    think about them in some situations, as for example when working with GIF
    files.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    実際のところいずれの用途も<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の使用目的の主流にはなり
    そこねています。 パレットに頼らなくても洗練された方法をとることが
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>で可能だからです。 それでもなお達人にとっては知って
    おくべきこととはいえ、 達人ほどではない方にとっては<acronym>GIF</acronym>
    ファイルを扱うときのようなある種の場面になって思い出す必要がでてくる
    ことがらです。
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">The Palettes dialog</title>
    <title lang="ja">パレットダイアログ</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/palettes-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    When you install <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, it comes supplied with several
    dozen predefined
    palettes, and you can also create new ones. Some of the predefined
    palettes are commonly useful, such as the <quote>Web</quote> palette,
    which contains the set of colors considered <quote>web safe</quote>;
    many of the palettes seem to have been chosen more or less whimsically.
    You can access all of the available palettes using the
    <link linkend="gimp-palette-dialog">Palettes dialog</link>.
    This is also the starting point if you want to create a new palette.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>をインストールすると数十種類もの配色ずみパレットが
    ついてきますし、 新規に追加もできます。 <quote>ウェブセーフカラー</quote>
    を念頭に置いた<quote>Web</quote>パレットのような配色ずみパレットは並程度
    には有益ですが、 大多数のパレットは多かれ少なかれ気紛れに色を選んだように
    思えます。 利用可能なパレットは全て 
    <link linkend="gimp-palette-dialog">パレットダイアログ</link> を通して
    扱います。 これは新たなパレットを作るときの出発点にもなります。
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">The Palette Editor</title>
    <title lang="ja">パレット編集ダイアログ</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dialogs/palette-editor.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    Double-clicking on a palette in the Palettes dialog brings up the
    <link linkend="gimp-palette-editor-dialog">Palette Editor</link>,
    showing the colors from the palette you clicked on. You can use this to
    paint with the palette: clicking on a color sets <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
    foreground to that
    color, as shown in the Color Area of the Toolbox. Holding down the
    <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key while clicking, on the other hand, sets
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s
    background color to the color you click on.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    You can also, as the name implies, use the Palette Editor to change the
    colors in a palette, so long as it is a palette that you have created
    yourself. You cannot edit the palettes that are supplied with
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>;
    however you can duplicate them and then edit the copies.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    When you create palettes using the Palette Editor, they are automatically
    saved as soon as you exit <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, in the
    <filename>palettes</filename>
    folder of your personal <acronym>GIMP</acronym> directory. Any palette
    files in this
    directory, or in the system <filename>palettes</filename>
    directory created when <acronym>GIMP</acronym> is installed, are
    automatically loaded and
    shown in the Palettes dialog the next time you start
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. You can also
    add other folders to the palette search path using the
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">Palette Folders</link>
    page of the Preferences dialog.
  </para>
  <para lang="en">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym> palettes are stored using a special file format,
    in files with the
    extension <filename>.gpl</filename>.
    It is a very simple format, and they are ASCII files, so if you happen
    to obtain palettes from another source, and would like to use them in
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, it probably won't be very hard to convert them:
    just take a look at
    any <filename>.gpl</filename> and you will see what to do.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    パレットダイアログのパレットをダブルクリックするとそのパレットの色を表示
    する
    <link linkend="gimp-palette-editor-dialog">パレット編集</link> 
    ダイアログが開きます。 これを使ってパレットによる絵が描けます。 クリック
    した色が<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の描画色になり、 ツールボックスの色標識領域
    でも表されます。 一方で <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> キーを押しながらクリック
    するとその色が<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の背景色になります。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    パレット編集ダイアログはその名前のとおりパレット上の色を変更できます。
    (ただし変更は自作のパレットに限ります)。 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>に同梱の
    パレットは編集できませんが、 それらの複製を作って編集することは可能です。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    パレット編集ダイアログを使ってパレットを作成したあと、 <acronym>GIMP
    </acronym> を終了するとそれらは直ちに自動的に <acronym>GIMP</acronym>
    の個人用ディレクトリーの <filename>palettes</filename> フォルダー内へ保存
    されます。 このディレクトリー内や、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のインストール
    時に作成されたシステム用の <filename>palettes</filename> フォルダーに入って
    いるパレットは、 いずれも<acronym>GIMP</acronym>を起動したときに自動的に
    読み込まれ、 パレットダイアログ上にずらりと並びます。 他のディレクトリーを
    パレット用のフォルダーとして検索対象に加えたいときは、
    <link linkend="gimp-prefs-folders-data">環境設定</link> ダイアログの
    <quote>パレット用フォルダー</quote>のページで追加登録します。
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    <acronym>GIMP</acronym>のパレットは専用のファイル形式で保存され、 その名前
    には拡張子 <filename class="extension">.gpl</filename> が付きます。 内容は
    大変簡素な<acronym>ASCII</acronym>テキストのみによる形式なので、 仮に他所
    から取得したパレットを<acronym>GIMP</acronym>用に使う要求が生じたとしても、
    それを<acronym>GIMP</acronym>用に転換する作業は大して難しくはならない
    でしょう。 まずはどれかひとつ <filename class="extension">.gpl</filename> 
    形式のファイルの中身を見てください。 何をすればよいか理解できるはずです。
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title lang="en">Colormap</title>
    <title lang="ja">カラーマップ</title>
    <para lang="en">
      Confusingly, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> makes use of two types of palettes.
      The more
      noticeable are the type shown in the Palettes dialog: palettes that
      exist independently of any image. The second type,
      <emphasis>indexed palettes</emphasis>,
      form the colormaps of indexed images. Each indexed image has its own
      private indexed palette, defining the set of colors available in the
      image: the maximum number of colors allowed in an indexed palette is
      256. These palettes are called <quote>indexed</quote> because each
      color is associated with an index number. (Actually, the colors in
      ordinary palettes are numbered as well, but the numbers have no
      functional significance.)
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ややこしいことに、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>は 2 つの型のパレットを使い
      分けています。 一方のよく知られる型はパレットダイアログに出てくる
      ものです。 これらのパレットは画像とは独立して存在しています。 第 2 の型は 
      <emphasis>インデックス化パレット</emphasis> といい、 インデックス化カラー
      画像のカラーマップとしての役目があります。 インデックス化カラー画像は
      それぞれに固有のインデックス化パレットを持っており、 画像で使用される
      すべての色を定義しています。 インデックス化パレットに加えられる
      色数は最大で 256 色です。 このパレットが<quote>インデックス化</quote> 
      と言われる理由は、 それぞれの色に索引番号が付与されるからです。 
      (実際には前者の一般的なパレットの色にも通し番号が振られていますが、 
      こちらに機能的な意味はありません。)
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">The Colormap dialog</title>
      <title lang="ja">カラーマップダイアログ</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG"
            fileref="images/dialogs/colormap-dialog.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para lang="en">
      The colormap of an indexed image is shown in the
      <link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">Indexed Palette dialog</link>,
      which should not be confused with the Palettes dialog. The Palettes
      dialog shows a list of all of the palettes available; the Colormap
      dialog shows the colormap of the currently active image, if it is an
      indexed image - otherwise it shows nothing.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      You can, however, create an ordinary palette from the colors in an
      indexed image&mdash;actually from the colors in any image. To do this,
      choose <guimenuitem>Import Palette</guimenuitem>
      from the right-click popup menu in the Palettes dialog: this pops up a
      dialog that gives you several options, including the option to import
      the palette from an image. (You can also import any of
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s gradients
      as a palette.) This possibility becomes important if you want to create
      a set of indexed images that all use the same set of colors.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      When you convert an image into indexed mode, a major part of the process
      is the creation of an indexed palette for the image. How this happens is
      described in detail in <xref linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed"/>.
      Briefly, you have several methods to choose from, one of which is to
      use a specified palette from the Palettes dialog.
    </para>
    <para lang="en">
      Thus, to sum up the foregoing, ordinary palettes can be turned into
      indexed palettes when you convert an image into indexed mode; indexed
      palettes can be turned into ordinary palettes by importing them into the
      Palettes dialog.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      インデックス化カラー画像のカラーマップは
      <link linkend="gimp-indexed-palette-dialog">インデックス化パレットの
      ダイアログ</link> で見られます。 パレットダイアログと混同しないように気を
      つけましょう。 パレットダイアログは利用可能なパレットの一覧表です。
      カラーマップダイアログは現在活性化している画像がインデックス化されている
      画像であるときにそのカラーマップを表示します。 インデックス化されて
      いなければ何も表示しません。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      しかしインデックス化カラー画像の色から (現実的にはどんな画像の色からも)
      得た色で一般的なパレットを作成できます。 その方法は、 パレットダイアログ
      の上で <mousebutton>第2ボタン</mousebutton> クリックすると現れるメニュー
      で <guimenuitem>パレットをインポート...</guimenuitem> を選択するのです。
      出てきたダイアログにはいろいろオプションがありますが、 その中に画像から
      パレットを抽出するオプションがあります。 (<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の
      グラデーションもパレットに抽出転換できます。) この能力がインデックス化
      カラー画像を同じ配色で揃えることになった場合に重要になります。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      画像のモードをインデックスカラーの色空間に変換する際の処理のほとんどは、
      その画像の色を収めるインデックス化パレットを作成するのに費されます。
      <xref linkend="gimp-image-convert-indexed"/> で、 どんなことが起こって
      いるのかを詳しく説明しています。 ほんの一部のご紹介になりますが、 例えば
      パレットダイアログから選びだしたパレットをインデックス化に使う方法の
      ようないろいろな選択肢を説明しています。
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      以上をまとめると、 一般のパレットは画像の色空間をインデックスカラーに
      変換する際にインデックス化パレットに転換できること、 インデックス化
      パレットはパレットダイアログのメニューで一般のパレットに抽出転換できる
      こと、 となります。
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Colormap dialog (1) and Palette dialog (2)</title>
      <title lang="ja">
        カラーマップダイアログ (1) とパレットダイアログ (2)
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/using/palettes.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
