<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- section history:
  2009-02-21 j.h: revised for v2.6
  2007-09-30 lexa: threw away all content that is not valid for 2.4 anymore
  2006-09-06 added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-05-02 added Korean translation by Dust
  2005-12-20 added italian content by ciampix
  2005-12-12 reviewed and added de screenshots by lexa
  2005-11-28 replaced informalfigures by figures by lexa
-->
<!-- FIXME: cs it ko nl zh_CN Review needed! -->
<!--2009-06-22-->
<sect1 id="gimp-concepts-setup">
  <title lang="en">Starting GIMP the first time</title>
  <title lang="ja">初めて<acronym>GIMP</acronym>を使うとき</title>
  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Setup</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary sortas="ドウニュウセツエイ">導入設営</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para lang="en">
    The first time you run GIMP, it goes through a series of steps to set up
    options and directories. This process creates a subdirectory of your home
    directory called <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.6</filename>.
    All of the information about the choices you make here goes into that
    directory. If you later remove that directory, or rename it as something
    like <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.6.bak</filename>,
    then the next time you start GIMP, it will go through the whole setup
    sequence again, creating a new
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.6</filename>
    directory. You can exploit this if you want to explore the effect of
    different choices without destroying your existing installation, or if you
    have screwed things up so badly that your existing installation needs to
    be nuked.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    初めて<acronym>GIMP</acronym>を利用したときは、始めに装備調度とディレクトリ
    確保がなされます。この処置によりあなたのホームディレクトリに
    サブディレクトリ <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.6</filename>
    が掘られます。 今後使用中に採った選択の情報が全てここに集約されます。
    もしこのディレクトリを削除したり、
    <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.6.bak</filename> のような別名に変更
    したときは、この直後に<acronym>GIMP</acronym>を起動すれば再び初回処置が
    行われ、 <filename class="directory">.gimp-2.6</filename> ディレクトリが
    作られます。 この後者の手法を用いれば、 以前の設定を崩さずに新たな選択の
    効果を試すことが可能ですし、 あるいは設定を詰め込みすぎて困ったときに
    白紙に戻ってみることもできます。
  </para>
  <sect2>
    <title lang="en">Finally . . .</title>
    <title lang="ja">あと少し. . .</title>
    <para lang="en">
      Just a couple of suggestions before you start, though: First, when you
      run GIMP, by default it shows a "tip" each time it starts up. These tips
      tell you things that are very useful but not easy to learn by
      experimenting, so they are worth paying attention to. If you find it too
      distracting to look at them each time you start, you can disable them;
      but please go through them when you have the chance: for your
      convenience, you can read them at any time using the menu command
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Tips</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      Second, if at some point you are trying to do something, and GIMP
      seems to have suddenly stopped functioning, the section
      <link linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">Getting Unstuck</link>
      may help you out. Happy Gimping!
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      最後、起動までに二言つけくわえさせてください。まずひとつめ: <acronym>
      GIMP</acronym>を使うとデフォルトでは始めに<quote>今日の技</quote>
      が現れます。 今日の技は経験を詰むだけでは得難いがとても役に立つまめ知識が
      満載なので、 ぜひ読んでいただきたく思います。 とはいえ起動のたびに何度も
      見せられてはかなわないという方のために、 これは中止できるように
      なっています。 しかしできれば一通りは目を通して下さい。メニューより
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>ヘルプ(<accel>H</accel>)</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>今日の技(<accel>T</accel>)</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      と辿れば連続して読めるようになっています。ふたつめに: 何か作業している
      最中に、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>が突然動かなくなってしまったときは、
      <link linkend="gimp-using-getting-unstuck">固まったときの対処</link>
      の節がお役に立てるかもしれません。
      <emphasis>さあ Gimp で楽しもう!</emphasis>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
