<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                       "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- Version History:
  2009-02-19 j.h: added tip for Removing Wilber's eyes
  2008-12-10 JPL: updated to v2.6
  2008-06-04 prokoudine: fixes to Russian translation
  2008-01-04 ude: replaced calloutlist with orderedlist
  2007-02-15: fixed Korean translation by Dust
  2006-09-06: added norwegian translation by KoSt
  2006-05-02: added Korean translation by Dust
  2006-02-17: added italian translation by ciampix
  2005-09-03: Addition en;fr at file end
-->
<!--2012-03-20-->
<sect2 id="gimp-concepts-toolbox">
  <title lang="en">The Toolbox</title>
  <title lang="ja">ツールボックス</title>

  <indexterm lang="en">
    <primary>Toolbox</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm lang="ja">
    <primary>ツールボックス</primary>
    <secondary sortas="アラマシ">あらまし</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Screenshot of the Toolbox</title>
    <title lang="ja">ツールボックスのスクリーンショット</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG"
          fileref="images/using/toolbox-description.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para lang="en">
    The Toolbox is the heart of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. If you close it, you
    quit <acronym>GIMP</acronym>. Here is a quick tour of what you will find
    there.
  </para>
  <para lang="ja">
    ツールボックスは<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の心臓部です。
    これを閉じると<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は終了します。
    さて図にでているものを順に素早く見てゆきましょう。
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para lang="en">
      In the Toolbox, as in most parts of <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, moving the
      mouse over something and letting it rest for a moment, usually displays
      a <quote>tooltip</quote> that describes the thing. Short cut keys are
      also frequently shown in the tooltip. In many cases, you can hover the
      mouse over an item and press the <keycap>F1</keycap> key to get help
      about the thing that is underneath the mouse.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ツールボックスも<acronym>GIMP</acronym>の各所と同じく、 なにかの部品の
      上でポイントしたままちょっと待つと何かメッセージが書かれた<quote>
      ツールチップ</quote>が現れます。 ここにはたびたび使えるショートカットキー
      が表示されます。 さらにほとんどの部品はその上にマウスポインタを置いたまま
      <keycap>F1</keycap> キーを押せば関連するヘルプが立ち上がるように
      なっています。
    </para>
  </tip>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Tool icons:</emphasis> These icons are buttons which
        activate tools for a wide variety of purposes: selecting parts of
        images, painting an image, transforming an image, etc.
        <xref linkend="gimp-toolbox"/> gives an overview of how to work with
        tools, and each tools is described systematically in the
        <link linkend="gimp-tools">Tools</link> chapter.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>ツールアイコン:</emphasis>
        ここに並ぶアイコンは、 画像の一部を選択したり、 色付けしたり、 変換
        したりといった様々な目的にあわせたツールをそれぞれ表しています。
        <xref linkend="gimp-toolbox"/> の節では
        ツールの使い方が大まかに述べてありますが、 
        <link linkend="gimp-tools">ツール</link> の章全体では
        それぞれのツールについて体系的に説明しています。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Foreground/Background colors:</emphasis>
        The color areas here show you <acronym>GIMP</acronym>'s current
        foreground and background
        colors, which come into play in many operations. Clicking on either
        one of them brings up a color selector dialog that allows you to
        change to a different color. Clicking on the double-headed arrow swaps
        the two colors, and clicking on the small symbol in the lower left
        corner resets them to black and white.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>描画色/背景色:</emphasis> このふたつの色見本は現在の描画色
        および背景色を表していて、 <acronym>GIMP</acronym>の数多くの操作に関連
        しています。 それぞれの色は色見本をクリックして出てくる<quote>
        &hellip;色を変更</quote>ダイアログで別の色に変えられます。 右上の両矢印
        アイコンをクリックすれば描画色と背景色を交換でき、 左下隅の白黒アイコン
        をクリックすると描画色は黒、 背景色は白にリセットされます。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Brush/Pattern/Gradient:</emphasis>
        The symbols here show you <acronym>GIMP's</acronym>
        current selections for: the Paintbrush, used by all tools that allow
        you to paint on the image (<quote>painting</quote> includes
        operations like erasing and smudging, by the way); for the Pattern,
        which is used in filling selected areas of an image; and for the
        Gradient, which comes into play whenever an operation requires a
        smoothly varying range of colors. Clicking on any of these symbols
        brings up a dialog window that allows you to change it.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>ブラシ/パターン/グラデーション:</emphasis> (穂先、 文様、 
        勾配ぼかし塗り)
        これらは現在<acronym>GIMP</acronym>が使うツールを象徴
        しています。 ブラシは画像に描画するツールすべてに関わるものです。
        (ちなみに消去やにじみといった操作も<quote>描画</quote>に含みます。)
        パターンは画像の選択された部分を埋め尽くすのに使います。
        グラデーションは徐々に色が変わる表現をしたいときのものです。
        いずれもその象徴をクリックすればダイアログウィンドウが現れ、
        調整ができるようになっています。
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para lang="en">
        <emphasis>Active Image:</emphasis> In <acronym>GIMP</acronym>, you
        can work with many images at once, but at any given moment, only one
        image is the <quote>active image</quote>. Here you find a small
        iconic representation of the active image. Clicking the icon to display
        a dialog with a list of the currently open images, click an
        image in the dialog to make it active. You can also click an
        image window to make it the active image.
      </para>
      <para lang="ja">
        <emphasis>活性画像:</emphasis> <acronym>GIMP</acronym>では同時に複数の
        画像を扱えますが、 どの時点でもそのうちのただ一枚だけが<quote>活性画像
        </quote> (アクティブな画像) です。 今の活性画像をアイコン化したものが
        ここに表示されます。 これをクリックすると現在開かれているすべての
        画像をリストにしたダイアログが出てきて、 どれかの画像をクリックすると
        それが活性画像になります。 もちろん、 画像を表示しているウィンドウを
        クリックしてもその画像を活性化できます。
      </para>
      <note>
        <para lang="en">
          The <quote>Active Image</quote> preview is disabled by default. If
          you want it, you can enable it in the
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">Toolbox Preferences</link> tab.
        </para>
        <para lang="ja">
          <quote>活性画像</quote>のプレビュー機能は初期設定では無効に
          なっています。 これを使いたい場合は、 
          <link linkend="gimp-prefs-toolbox">環境設定</link> ダイアログの
          <quote>ツールオプション</quote>のページで有効にします。
        </para>
      </note>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <note>
    <para lang="en">
      At every start, <acronym>GIMP</acronym> selects a tool (the brush), a
      color, a brush and a pattern by default, always the same. If you
      want <acronym>GIMP</acronym> to select the
      last tool, color, brush and pattern you used when quitting your
      previous session, check the
      <guilabel>Save input device settings on exit</guilabel> in
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-input-devices">Preferences/Input
      Devices</link>.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      起動直後の<acronym>GIMP</acronym>は、いつも同じツール (絵筆) と色と
      ブラシおよびパターンを選ぶようになっています。 しかし前回
      <acronym>GIMP</acronym>を終了した際に使っていたツールと色とブラシと
      パターンをひきつづき使いたいという場合は、 
      <link linkend="gimp-prefs-input-devices">環境設定</link> ダイアログの
      <quote>入力デバイス</quote>のページで
      <guilabel>入力デバイスの設定を終了時に保存</guilabel> の項を有効にします。
    </para>
  </note>
  <tip>
    <para lang="en">
      The Toolbox window displays <quote>Wilber's eyes</quote> along the top
      of the dialog. You can get rid of the <quote>Wilber's eys</quote>
      by adding the following line to your <filename>gimprc</filename>
      file:
      <function>(toolbox-wilber&nbsp;no)</function>.
      It only affects the toolbox. The eyes in the Image window are only
      visible when you do not have an open image.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      ツールボックス上部にはウィルバーの目玉の絵が表示されています。 この空き地
      は個人用<acronym>GIMP</acronym>ディレクトリー内の <filename>gimprc
      </filename> ファイルに <function>(toolbox-wilber&nbsp;no)</function> の
      行を追加すると撤去できます。 この指示はツールボックスのみに適用されます。
      画像ウィンドウ内にもウィルバーの目玉の絵が表示されることがありますが、
      こちらは何も画像を開いていない時だけに限られています。
    </para>
  </tip>
  <tip>
    <para lang="en">
      Drag and drop an image into the Toolbox window to open the image
      in its own Image window. This is very differnt than dragging
      an image into an existing Image window, which adds it to the
      currently open image in a new layer&mdash;usually not what
      you want.
    </para>
    <para lang="ja">
      画像アイコンをツールボックスまでドラッグして放つとその画像用の画像で
      ウィンドウ画像が開かれます。 代わりに画像アイコンを他の画像ウィンドウ上
      に放つと全く異なる動作をします。 この場合はドラッグで曳き込まれた画像が
      新たなレイヤーとなってその画像に追加されますので、 大半の人にとっては
      想像通りではない動作でしょう。
    </para>
  </tip>
</sect2>
